<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Book osisId="Phil" sblId="Phil" name="Philippians" shortName="Phil" orderIndex="49" chaptersCount="4" versesCount="104">
  <chapters>
    <Chapter osisId="Phil.1" sblId="Phil 1" name="Philippians 1" shortName="Phil 1" orderIndex="0" versesCount="30">
      <verses>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.1" sblId="Phil 1:1" name="Philippians 1:1" shortName="Phil 1:1" orderIndex="0">Paul and Timothy, servants of Christ Jesus, To all the saints in Christ Jesus at Philippi, together with the overseers and deacons:</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.2" sblId="Phil 1:2" name="Philippians 1:2" shortName="Phil 1:2" orderIndex="1">Grace and peace to you from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.3" sblId="Phil 1:3" name="Philippians 1:3" shortName="Phil 1:3" orderIndex="2">I thank my God every time I remember you.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.4" sblId="Phil 1:4" name="Philippians 1:4" shortName="Phil 1:4" orderIndex="3">In all my prayers for all of you, I always pray with joy</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.5" sblId="Phil 1:5" name="Philippians 1:5" shortName="Phil 1:5" orderIndex="4">because of your partnership in the gospel from the first day until now,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.6" sblId="Phil 1:6" name="Philippians 1:6" shortName="Phil 1:6" orderIndex="5">being confident of this, that he who began a good work in you will carry it on to completion until the day of Christ Jesus.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.7" sblId="Phil 1:7" name="Philippians 1:7" shortName="Phil 1:7" orderIndex="6">It is right for me to feel this way about all of you, since I have you in my heart; for whether I am in chains or defending and confirming the gospel, all of you share in God's grace with me.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.8" sblId="Phil 1:8" name="Philippians 1:8" shortName="Phil 1:8" orderIndex="7">God can testify how I long for all of you with the affection of Christ Jesus.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.9" sblId="Phil 1:9" name="Philippians 1:9" shortName="Phil 1:9" orderIndex="8">And this is my prayer: that your love may abound more and more in knowledge and depth of insight,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.10" sblId="Phil 1:10" name="Philippians 1:10" shortName="Phil 1:10" orderIndex="9">so that you may be able to discern what is best and may be pure and blameless until the day of Christ,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.11" sblId="Phil 1:11" name="Philippians 1:11" shortName="Phil 1:11" orderIndex="10">filled with the fruit of righteousness that comes through Jesus Christ--to the glory and praise of God.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.12" sblId="Phil 1:12" name="Philippians 1:12" shortName="Phil 1:12" orderIndex="11">Now I want you to know, brothers, that what has happened to me has really served to advance the gospel.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.13" sblId="Phil 1:13" name="Philippians 1:13" shortName="Phil 1:13" orderIndex="12">As a result, it has become clear throughout the whole palace guard and to everyone else that I am in chains for Christ.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.14" sblId="Phil 1:14" name="Philippians 1:14" shortName="Phil 1:14" orderIndex="13">Because of my chains, most of the brothers in the Lord have been encouraged to speak the word of God more courageously and fearlessly.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.15" sblId="Phil 1:15" name="Philippians 1:15" shortName="Phil 1:15" orderIndex="14">It is true that some preach Christ out of envy and rivalry, but others out of goodwill.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.16" sblId="Phil 1:16" name="Philippians 1:16" shortName="Phil 1:16" orderIndex="15">The latter do so in love, knowing that I am put here for the defense of the gospel.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.17" sblId="Phil 1:17" name="Philippians 1:17" shortName="Phil 1:17" orderIndex="16">The former preach Christ out of selfish ambition, not sincerely, supposing that they can stir up trouble for me while I am in chains.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.18" sblId="Phil 1:18" name="Philippians 1:18" shortName="Phil 1:18" orderIndex="17">But what does it matter? The important thing is that in every way, whether from false motives or true, Christ is preached. And because of this I rejoice.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.19" sblId="Phil 1:19" name="Philippians 1:19" shortName="Phil 1:19" orderIndex="18">Yes, and I will continue to rejoice, for I know that through your prayers and the help given by the Spirit of Jesus Christ, what has happened to me will turn out for my deliverance.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.20" sblId="Phil 1:20" name="Philippians 1:20" shortName="Phil 1:20" orderIndex="19">I eagerly expect and hope that I will in no way be ashamed, but will have sufficient courage so that now as always Christ will be exalted in my body, whether by life or by death.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.21" sblId="Phil 1:21" name="Philippians 1:21" shortName="Phil 1:21" orderIndex="20">For to me, to live is Christ and to die is gain.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.22" sblId="Phil 1:22" name="Philippians 1:22" shortName="Phil 1:22" orderIndex="21">If I am to go on living in the body, this will mean fruitful labor for me. Yet what shall I choose? I do not know!</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.23" sblId="Phil 1:23" name="Philippians 1:23" shortName="Phil 1:23" orderIndex="22">I am torn between the two: I desire to depart and be with Christ, which is better by far;</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.24" sblId="Phil 1:24" name="Philippians 1:24" shortName="Phil 1:24" orderIndex="23">but it is more necessary for you that I remain in the body.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.25" sblId="Phil 1:25" name="Philippians 1:25" shortName="Phil 1:25" orderIndex="24">Convinced of this, I know that I will remain, and I will continue with all of you for your progress and joy in the faith,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.26" sblId="Phil 1:26" name="Philippians 1:26" shortName="Phil 1:26" orderIndex="25">so that through my being with you again your joy in Christ Jesus will overflow on account of me.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.27" sblId="Phil 1:27" name="Philippians 1:27" shortName="Phil 1:27" orderIndex="26">Whatever happens, conduct yourselves in a manner worthy of the gospel of Christ. Then, whether I come and see you or only hear about you in my absence, I will know that you stand firm in one spirit, contending as one man for the faith of the gospel</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.28" sblId="Phil 1:28" name="Philippians 1:28" shortName="Phil 1:28" orderIndex="27">without being frightened in any way by those who oppose you. This is a sign to them that they will be destroyed, but that you will be saved--and that by God.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.29" sblId="Phil 1:29" name="Philippians 1:29" shortName="Phil 1:29" orderIndex="28">For it has been granted to you on behalf of Christ not only to believe on him, but also to suffer for him,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.1.30" sblId="Phil 1:30" name="Philippians 1:30" shortName="Phil 1:30" orderIndex="29">since you are going through the same struggle you saw I had, and now hear that I still have.</Verse>
      </verses>
    </Chapter>
    <Chapter osisId="Phil.2" sblId="Phil 2" name="Philippians 2" shortName="Phil 2" orderIndex="1" versesCount="30">
      <verses>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.1" sblId="Phil 2:1" name="Philippians 2:1" shortName="Phil 2:1" orderIndex="0">If you have any encouragement from being united with Christ, if any comfort from his love, if any fellowship with the Spirit, if any tenderness and compassion,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.2" sblId="Phil 2:2" name="Philippians 2:2" shortName="Phil 2:2" orderIndex="1">then make my joy complete by being like-minded, having the same love, being one in spirit and purpose.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.3" sblId="Phil 2:3" name="Philippians 2:3" shortName="Phil 2:3" orderIndex="2">Do nothing out of selfish ambition or vain conceit, but in humility consider others better than yourselves.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.4" sblId="Phil 2:4" name="Philippians 2:4" shortName="Phil 2:4" orderIndex="3">Each of you should look not only to your own interests, but also to the interests of others.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.5" sblId="Phil 2:5" name="Philippians 2:5" shortName="Phil 2:5" orderIndex="4">Your attitude should be the same as that of Christ Jesus:</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.6" sblId="Phil 2:6" name="Philippians 2:6" shortName="Phil 2:6" orderIndex="5">Who, being in very nature God, did not consider equality with God something to be grasped,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.7" sblId="Phil 2:7" name="Philippians 2:7" shortName="Phil 2:7" orderIndex="6">but made himself nothing, taking the very nature of a servant, being made in human likeness.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.8" sblId="Phil 2:8" name="Philippians 2:8" shortName="Phil 2:8" orderIndex="7">And being found in appearance as a man, he humbled himself and became obedient to death--even death on a cross!</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.9" sblId="Phil 2:9" name="Philippians 2:9" shortName="Phil 2:9" orderIndex="8">Therefore God exalted him to the highest place and gave him the name that is above every name,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.10" sblId="Phil 2:10" name="Philippians 2:10" shortName="Phil 2:10" orderIndex="9">that at the name of Jesus every knee should bow, in heaven and on earth and under the earth,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.11" sblId="Phil 2:11" name="Philippians 2:11" shortName="Phil 2:11" orderIndex="10">and every tongue confess that Jesus Christ is Lord, to the glory of God the Father.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.12" sblId="Phil 2:12" name="Philippians 2:12" shortName="Phil 2:12" orderIndex="11">Therefore, my dear friends, as you have always obeyed--not only in my presence, but now much more in my absence--continue to work out your salvation with fear and trembling,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.13" sblId="Phil 2:13" name="Philippians 2:13" shortName="Phil 2:13" orderIndex="12">for it is God who works in you to will and to act according to his good purpose.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.14" sblId="Phil 2:14" name="Philippians 2:14" shortName="Phil 2:14" orderIndex="13">Do everything without complaining or arguing,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.15" sblId="Phil 2:15" name="Philippians 2:15" shortName="Phil 2:15" orderIndex="14">so that you may become blameless and pure, children of God without fault in a crooked and depraved generation, in which you shine like stars in the universe</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.16" sblId="Phil 2:16" name="Philippians 2:16" shortName="Phil 2:16" orderIndex="15">as you hold out the word of life--in order that I may boast on the day of Christ that I did not run or labor for nothing.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.17" sblId="Phil 2:17" name="Philippians 2:17" shortName="Phil 2:17" orderIndex="16">But even if I am being poured out like a drink offering on the sacrifice and service coming from your faith, I am glad and rejoice with all of you.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.18" sblId="Phil 2:18" name="Philippians 2:18" shortName="Phil 2:18" orderIndex="17">So you too should be glad and rejoice with me.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.19" sblId="Phil 2:19" name="Philippians 2:19" shortName="Phil 2:19" orderIndex="18">I hope in the Lord Jesus to send Timothy to you soon, that I also may be cheered when I receive news about you.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.20" sblId="Phil 2:20" name="Philippians 2:20" shortName="Phil 2:20" orderIndex="19">I have no one else like him, who takes a genuine interest in your welfare.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.21" sblId="Phil 2:21" name="Philippians 2:21" shortName="Phil 2:21" orderIndex="20">For everyone looks out for his own interests, not those of Jesus Christ.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.22" sblId="Phil 2:22" name="Philippians 2:22" shortName="Phil 2:22" orderIndex="21">But you know that Timothy has proved himself, because as a son with his father he has served with me in the work of the gospel.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.23" sblId="Phil 2:23" name="Philippians 2:23" shortName="Phil 2:23" orderIndex="22">I hope, therefore, to send him as soon as I see how things go with me.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.24" sblId="Phil 2:24" name="Philippians 2:24" shortName="Phil 2:24" orderIndex="23">And I am confident in the Lord that I myself will come soon.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.25" sblId="Phil 2:25" name="Philippians 2:25" shortName="Phil 2:25" orderIndex="24">But I think it is necessary to send back to you Epaphroditus, my brother, fellow worker and fellow soldier, who is also your messenger, whom you sent to take care of my needs.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.26" sblId="Phil 2:26" name="Philippians 2:26" shortName="Phil 2:26" orderIndex="25">For he longs for all of you and is distressed because you heard he was ill.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.27" sblId="Phil 2:27" name="Philippians 2:27" shortName="Phil 2:27" orderIndex="26">Indeed he was ill, and almost died. But God had mercy on him, and not on him only but also on me, to spare me sorrow upon sorrow.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.28" sblId="Phil 2:28" name="Philippians 2:28" shortName="Phil 2:28" orderIndex="27">Therefore I am all the more eager to send him, so that when you see him again you may be glad and I may have less anxiety.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.29" sblId="Phil 2:29" name="Philippians 2:29" shortName="Phil 2:29" orderIndex="28">Welcome him in the Lord with great joy, and honor men like him,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.2.30" sblId="Phil 2:30" name="Philippians 2:30" shortName="Phil 2:30" orderIndex="29">because he almost died for the work of Christ, risking his life to make up for the help you could not give me.</Verse>
      </verses>
    </Chapter>
    <Chapter osisId="Phil.3" sblId="Phil 3" name="Philippians 3" shortName="Phil 3" orderIndex="2" versesCount="21">
      <verses>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.3.1" sblId="Phil 3:1" name="Philippians 3:1" shortName="Phil 3:1" orderIndex="0">Finally, my brothers, rejoice in the Lord! It is no trouble for me to write the same things to you again, and it is a safeguard for you.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.3.2" sblId="Phil 3:2" name="Philippians 3:2" shortName="Phil 3:2" orderIndex="1">Watch out for those dogs, those men who do evil, those mutilators of the flesh.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.3.3" sblId="Phil 3:3" name="Philippians 3:3" shortName="Phil 3:3" orderIndex="2">For it is we who are the circumcision, we who worship by the Spirit of God, who glory in Christ Jesus, and who put no confidence in the flesh--</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.3.4" sblId="Phil 3:4" name="Philippians 3:4" shortName="Phil 3:4" orderIndex="3">though I myself have reasons for such confidence. If anyone else thinks he has reasons to put confidence in the flesh, I have more:</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.3.5" sblId="Phil 3:5" name="Philippians 3:5" shortName="Phil 3:5" orderIndex="4">circumcised on the eighth day, of the people of Israel, of the tribe of Benjamin, a Hebrew of Hebrews; in regard to the law, a Pharisee;</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.3.6" sblId="Phil 3:6" name="Philippians 3:6" shortName="Phil 3:6" orderIndex="5">as for zeal, persecuting the church; as for legalistic righteousness, faultless.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.3.7" sblId="Phil 3:7" name="Philippians 3:7" shortName="Phil 3:7" orderIndex="6">But whatever was to my profit I now consider loss for the sake of Christ.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.3.8" sblId="Phil 3:8" name="Philippians 3:8" shortName="Phil 3:8" orderIndex="7">What is more, I consider everything a loss compared to the surpassing greatness of knowing Christ Jesus my Lord, for whose sake I have lost all things. I consider them rubbish, that I may gain Christ</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.3.9" sblId="Phil 3:9" name="Philippians 3:9" shortName="Phil 3:9" orderIndex="8">and be found in him, not having a righteousness of my own that comes from the law, but that which is through faith in Christ--the righteousness that comes from God and is by faith.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.3.10" sblId="Phil 3:10" name="Philippians 3:10" shortName="Phil 3:10" orderIndex="9">I want to know Christ and the power of his resurrection and the fellowship of sharing in his sufferings, becoming like him in his death,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.3.11" sblId="Phil 3:11" name="Philippians 3:11" shortName="Phil 3:11" orderIndex="10">and so, somehow, to attain to the resurrection from the dead.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.3.12" sblId="Phil 3:12" name="Philippians 3:12" shortName="Phil 3:12" orderIndex="11">Not that I have already obtained all this, or have already been made perfect, but I press on to take hold of that for which Christ Jesus took hold of me.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.3.13" sblId="Phil 3:13" name="Philippians 3:13" shortName="Phil 3:13" orderIndex="12">Brothers, I do not consider myself yet to have taken hold of it. But one thing I do: Forgetting what is behind and straining toward what is ahead,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.3.14" sblId="Phil 3:14" name="Philippians 3:14" shortName="Phil 3:14" orderIndex="13">I press on toward the goal to win the prize for which God has called me heavenward in Christ Jesus.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.3.15" sblId="Phil 3:15" name="Philippians 3:15" shortName="Phil 3:15" orderIndex="14">All of us who are mature should take such a view of things. And if on some point you think differently, that too God will make clear to you.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.3.16" sblId="Phil 3:16" name="Philippians 3:16" shortName="Phil 3:16" orderIndex="15">Only let us live up to what we have already attained.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.3.17" sblId="Phil 3:17" name="Philippians 3:17" shortName="Phil 3:17" orderIndex="16">Join with others in following my example, brothers, and take note of those who live according to the pattern we gave you.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.3.18" sblId="Phil 3:18" name="Philippians 3:18" shortName="Phil 3:18" orderIndex="17">For, as I have often told you before and now say again even with tears, many live as enemies of the cross of Christ.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.3.19" sblId="Phil 3:19" name="Philippians 3:19" shortName="Phil 3:19" orderIndex="18">Their destiny is destruction, their god is their stomach, and their glory is in their shame. Their mind is on earthly things.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.3.20" sblId="Phil 3:20" name="Philippians 3:20" shortName="Phil 3:20" orderIndex="19">But our citizenship is in heaven. And we eagerly await a Savior from there, the Lord Jesus Christ,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.3.21" sblId="Phil 3:21" name="Philippians 3:21" shortName="Phil 3:21" orderIndex="20">who, by the power that enables him to bring everything under his control, will transform our lowly bodies so that they will be like his glorious body.</Verse>
      </verses>
    </Chapter>
    <Chapter osisId="Phil.4" sblId="Phil 4" name="Philippians 4" shortName="Phil 4" orderIndex="3" versesCount="23">
      <verses>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.1" sblId="Phil 4:1" name="Philippians 4:1" shortName="Phil 4:1" orderIndex="0">Therefore, my brothers, you whom I love and long for, my joy and crown, that is how you should stand firm in the Lord, dear friends!</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.2" sblId="Phil 4:2" name="Philippians 4:2" shortName="Phil 4:2" orderIndex="1">I plead with Euodia and I plead with Syntyche to agree with each other in the Lord.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.3" sblId="Phil 4:3" name="Philippians 4:3" shortName="Phil 4:3" orderIndex="2">Yes, and I ask you, loyal yokefellow, help these women who have contended at my side in the cause of the gospel, along with Clement and the rest of my fellow workers, whose names are in the book of life.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.4" sblId="Phil 4:4" name="Philippians 4:4" shortName="Phil 4:4" orderIndex="3">Rejoice in the Lord always. I will say it again: Rejoice!</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.5" sblId="Phil 4:5" name="Philippians 4:5" shortName="Phil 4:5" orderIndex="4">Let your gentleness be evident to all. The Lord is near.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.6" sblId="Phil 4:6" name="Philippians 4:6" shortName="Phil 4:6" orderIndex="5">Do not be anxious about anything, but in everything, by prayer and petition, with thanksgiving, present your requests to God.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.7" sblId="Phil 4:7" name="Philippians 4:7" shortName="Phil 4:7" orderIndex="6">And the peace of God, which transcends all understanding, will guard your hearts and your minds in Christ Jesus.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.8" sblId="Phil 4:8" name="Philippians 4:8" shortName="Phil 4:8" orderIndex="7">Finally, brothers, whatever is true, whatever is noble, whatever is right, whatever is pure, whatever is lovely, whatever is admirable--if anything is excellent or praiseworthy--think about such things.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.9" sblId="Phil 4:9" name="Philippians 4:9" shortName="Phil 4:9" orderIndex="8">Whatever you have learned or received or heard from me, or seen in me--put it into practice. And the God of peace will be with you.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.10" sblId="Phil 4:10" name="Philippians 4:10" shortName="Phil 4:10" orderIndex="9">I rejoice greatly in the Lord that at last you have renewed your concern for me. Indeed, you have been concerned, but you had no opportunity to show it.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.11" sblId="Phil 4:11" name="Philippians 4:11" shortName="Phil 4:11" orderIndex="10">I am not saying this because I am in need, for I have learned to be content whatever the circumstances.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.12" sblId="Phil 4:12" name="Philippians 4:12" shortName="Phil 4:12" orderIndex="11">I know what it is to be in need, and I know what it is to have plenty. I have learned the secret of being content in any and every situation, whether well fed or hungry, whether living in plenty or in want.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.13" sblId="Phil 4:13" name="Philippians 4:13" shortName="Phil 4:13" orderIndex="12">I can do everything through him who gives me strength.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.14" sblId="Phil 4:14" name="Philippians 4:14" shortName="Phil 4:14" orderIndex="13">Yet it was good of you to share in my troubles.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.15" sblId="Phil 4:15" name="Philippians 4:15" shortName="Phil 4:15" orderIndex="14">Moreover, as you Philippians know, in the early days of your acquaintance with the gospel, when I set out from Macedonia, not one church shared with me in the matter of giving and receiving, except you only;</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.16" sblId="Phil 4:16" name="Philippians 4:16" shortName="Phil 4:16" orderIndex="15">for even when I was in Thessalonica, you sent me aid again and again when I was in need.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.17" sblId="Phil 4:17" name="Philippians 4:17" shortName="Phil 4:17" orderIndex="16">Not that I am looking for a gift, but I am looking for what may be credited to your account.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.18" sblId="Phil 4:18" name="Philippians 4:18" shortName="Phil 4:18" orderIndex="17">I have received full payment and even more; I am amply supplied, now that I have received from Epaphroditus the gifts you sent. They are a fragrant offering, an acceptable sacrifice, pleasing to God.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.19" sblId="Phil 4:19" name="Philippians 4:19" shortName="Phil 4:19" orderIndex="18">And my God will meet all your needs according to his glorious riches in Christ Jesus.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.20" sblId="Phil 4:20" name="Philippians 4:20" shortName="Phil 4:20" orderIndex="19">To our God and Father be glory for ever and ever. Amen.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.21" sblId="Phil 4:21" name="Philippians 4:21" shortName="Phil 4:21" orderIndex="20">Greet all the saints in Christ Jesus. The brothers who are with me send greetings.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.22" sblId="Phil 4:22" name="Philippians 4:22" shortName="Phil 4:22" orderIndex="21">All the saints send you greetings, especially those who belong to Caesar's household.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="Phil.4.23" sblId="Phil 4:23" name="Philippians 4:23" shortName="Phil 4:23" orderIndex="22">The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. Amen.</Verse>
      </verses>
    </Chapter>
  </chapters>
</Book>