<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Book osisId="3John" sblId="3John" name="3 John" shortName="3 John" orderIndex="63" chaptersCount="1" versesCount="14">
  <chapters>
    <Chapter osisId="3John.1" sblId="3John 1" name="3 John 1" shortName="3 John 1" orderIndex="0" versesCount="14">
      <verses>
        <Verse osisId="3John.1.1" sblId="3John 1:1" name="3 John 1:1" shortName="3 John 1:1" orderIndex="0">The elder, To my dear friend Gaius, whom I love in the truth.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="3John.1.2" sblId="3John 1:2" name="3 John 1:2" shortName="3 John 1:2" orderIndex="1">Dear friend, I pray that you may enjoy good health and that all may go well with you, even as your soul is getting along well.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="3John.1.3" sblId="3John 1:3" name="3 John 1:3" shortName="3 John 1:3" orderIndex="2">It gave me great joy to have some brothers come and tell about your faithfulness to the truth and how you continue to walk in the truth.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="3John.1.4" sblId="3John 1:4" name="3 John 1:4" shortName="3 John 1:4" orderIndex="3">I have no greater joy than to hear that my children are walking in the truth.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="3John.1.5" sblId="3John 1:5" name="3 John 1:5" shortName="3 John 1:5" orderIndex="4">Dear friend, you are faithful in what you are doing for the brothers, even though they are strangers to you.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="3John.1.6" sblId="3John 1:6" name="3 John 1:6" shortName="3 John 1:6" orderIndex="5">They have told the church about your love. You will do well to send them on their way in a manner worthy of God.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="3John.1.7" sblId="3John 1:7" name="3 John 1:7" shortName="3 John 1:7" orderIndex="6">It was for the sake of the Name that they went out, receiving no help from the pagans.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="3John.1.8" sblId="3John 1:8" name="3 John 1:8" shortName="3 John 1:8" orderIndex="7">We ought therefore to show hospitality to such men so that we may work together for the truth.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="3John.1.9" sblId="3John 1:9" name="3 John 1:9" shortName="3 John 1:9" orderIndex="8">I wrote to the church, but Diotrephes, who loves to be first, will have nothing to do with us.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="3John.1.10" sblId="3John 1:10" name="3 John 1:10" shortName="3 John 1:10" orderIndex="9">So if I come, I will call attention to what he is doing, gossiping maliciously about us. Not satisfied with that, he refuses to welcome the brothers. He also stops those who want to do so and puts them out of the church.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="3John.1.11" sblId="3John 1:11" name="3 John 1:11" shortName="3 John 1:11" orderIndex="10">Dear friend, do not imitate what is evil but what is good. Anyone who does what is good is from God. Anyone who does what is evil has not seen God.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="3John.1.12" sblId="3John 1:12" name="3 John 1:12" shortName="3 John 1:12" orderIndex="11">Demetrius is well spoken of by everyone--and even by the truth itself. We also speak well of him, and you know that our testimony is true.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="3John.1.13" sblId="3John 1:13" name="3 John 1:13" shortName="3 John 1:13" orderIndex="12">I have much to write you, but I do not want to do so with pen and ink.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="3John.1.14" sblId="3John 1:14" name="3 John 1:14" shortName="3 John 1:14" orderIndex="13">I hope to see you soon, and we will talk face to face. Peace to you. The friends here send their greetings. Greet the friends there by name.</Verse>
      </verses>
    </Chapter>
  </chapters>
</Book>