<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Book osisId="2Thess" sblId="2Thess" name="2 Thessalonians" shortName="2 Thess" orderIndex="52" chaptersCount="3" versesCount="47">
  <chapters>
    <Chapter osisId="2Thess.1" sblId="2Thess 1" name="2 Thessalonians 1" shortName="2 Thess 1" orderIndex="0" versesCount="12">
      <verses>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.1.1" sblId="2Thess 1:1" name="2 Thessalonians 1:1" shortName="2 Thess 1:1" orderIndex="0">Paul, Silvanus, and Timothy, To the church of the Thessalonians in God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ:</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.1.2" sblId="2Thess 1:2" name="2 Thessalonians 1:2" shortName="2 Thess 1:2" orderIndex="1">Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.1.3" sblId="2Thess 1:3" name="2 Thessalonians 1:3" shortName="2 Thess 1:3" orderIndex="2">We ought always to give thanks to God for you, brothers, as is right, because your faith is growing abundantly, and the love of every one of you for one another is increasing.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.1.4" sblId="2Thess 1:4" name="2 Thessalonians 1:4" shortName="2 Thess 1:4" orderIndex="3">Therefore we ourselves boast about you in the churches of God for your steadfastness and faith in all your persecutions and in the afflictions that you are enduring.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.1.5" sblId="2Thess 1:5" name="2 Thessalonians 1:5" shortName="2 Thess 1:5" orderIndex="4">This is evidence of the righteous judgment of God, that you may be considered worthy of the kingdom of God, for which you are also suffering-</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.1.6" sblId="2Thess 1:6" name="2 Thessalonians 1:6" shortName="2 Thess 1:6" orderIndex="5">since indeed God considers it just to repay with affliction those who afflict you,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.1.7" sblId="2Thess 1:7" name="2 Thessalonians 1:7" shortName="2 Thess 1:7" orderIndex="6">and to grant relief to you who are afflicted as well as to us, when the Lord Jesus is revealed from heaven with his mighty angels</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.1.8" sblId="2Thess 1:8" name="2 Thessalonians 1:8" shortName="2 Thess 1:8" orderIndex="7">in flaming fire, inflicting vengeance on those who do not know God and on those who do not obey the gospel of our Lord Jesus.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.1.9" sblId="2Thess 1:9" name="2 Thessalonians 1:9" shortName="2 Thess 1:9" orderIndex="8">They will suffer the punishment of eternal destruction, away from the presence of the Lord and from the glory of his might,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.1.10" sblId="2Thess 1:10" name="2 Thessalonians 1:10" shortName="2 Thess 1:10" orderIndex="9">when he comes on that day to be glorified in his saints, and to be marveled at among all who have believed, because our testimony to you was believed.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.1.11" sblId="2Thess 1:11" name="2 Thessalonians 1:11" shortName="2 Thess 1:11" orderIndex="10">To this end we always pray for you, that our God may make you worthy of his calling and may fulfill every resolve for good and every work of faith by his power,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.1.12" sblId="2Thess 1:12" name="2 Thessalonians 1:12" shortName="2 Thess 1:12" orderIndex="11">so that the name of our Lord Jesus may be glorified in you, and you in him, according to the grace of our God and the Lord Jesus Christ.</Verse>
      </verses>
    </Chapter>
    <Chapter osisId="2Thess.2" sblId="2Thess 2" name="2 Thessalonians 2" shortName="2 Thess 2" orderIndex="1" versesCount="17">
      <verses>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.2.1" sblId="2Thess 2:1" name="2 Thessalonians 2:1" shortName="2 Thess 2:1" orderIndex="0">Now concerning the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ and our being gathered together to him, we ask you, brothers,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.2.2" sblId="2Thess 2:2" name="2 Thessalonians 2:2" shortName="2 Thess 2:2" orderIndex="1">not to be quickly shaken in mind or alarmed, either by a spirit or a spoken word, or a letter seeming to be from us, to the effect that the day of the Lord has come.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.2.3" sblId="2Thess 2:3" name="2 Thessalonians 2:3" shortName="2 Thess 2:3" orderIndex="2">Let no one deceive you in any way. For that day will not come, unless the rebellion comes first, and the man of lawlessness is revealed, the son of destruction,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.2.4" sblId="2Thess 2:4" name="2 Thessalonians 2:4" shortName="2 Thess 2:4" orderIndex="3">who opposes and exalts himself against every so-called god or object of worship, so that he takes his seat in the temple of God, proclaiming himself to be God.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.2.5" sblId="2Thess 2:5" name="2 Thessalonians 2:5" shortName="2 Thess 2:5" orderIndex="4">Do you not remember that when I was still with you I told you these things?</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.2.6" sblId="2Thess 2:6" name="2 Thessalonians 2:6" shortName="2 Thess 2:6" orderIndex="5">And you know what is restraining him now so that he may be revealed in his time.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.2.7" sblId="2Thess 2:7" name="2 Thessalonians 2:7" shortName="2 Thess 2:7" orderIndex="6">For the mystery of lawlessness is already at work. Only he who now restrains it will do so until he is out of the way.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.2.8" sblId="2Thess 2:8" name="2 Thessalonians 2:8" shortName="2 Thess 2:8" orderIndex="7">And then the lawless one will be revealed, whom the Lord Jesus will kill with the breath of his mouth and bring to nothing by the appearance of his coming.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.2.9" sblId="2Thess 2:9" name="2 Thessalonians 2:9" shortName="2 Thess 2:9" orderIndex="8">The coming of the lawless one is by the activity of Satan with all power and false signs and wonders,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.2.10" sblId="2Thess 2:10" name="2 Thessalonians 2:10" shortName="2 Thess 2:10" orderIndex="9">and with all wicked deception for those who are perishing, because they refused to love the truth and so be saved.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.2.11" sblId="2Thess 2:11" name="2 Thessalonians 2:11" shortName="2 Thess 2:11" orderIndex="10">Therefore God sends them a strong delusion, so that they may believe what is false,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.2.12" sblId="2Thess 2:12" name="2 Thessalonians 2:12" shortName="2 Thess 2:12" orderIndex="11">in order that all may be condemned who did not believe the truth but had pleasure in unrighteousness.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.2.13" sblId="2Thess 2:13" name="2 Thessalonians 2:13" shortName="2 Thess 2:13" orderIndex="12">But we ought always to give thanks to God for you, brothers beloved by the Lord, because God chose you as the first fruits to be saved, through sanctification by the Spirit and belief in the truth.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.2.14" sblId="2Thess 2:14" name="2 Thessalonians 2:14" shortName="2 Thess 2:14" orderIndex="13">To this he called you through our gospel, so that you may obtain the glory of our Lord Jesus Christ.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.2.15" sblId="2Thess 2:15" name="2 Thessalonians 2:15" shortName="2 Thess 2:15" orderIndex="14">So then, brothers, stand firm and hold to the traditions that you were taught by us, either by our spoken word or by our letter.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.2.16" sblId="2Thess 2:16" name="2 Thessalonians 2:16" shortName="2 Thess 2:16" orderIndex="15">Now may our Lord Jesus Christ himself, and God our Father, who loved us and gave us eternal comfort and good hope through grace,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.2.17" sblId="2Thess 2:17" name="2 Thessalonians 2:17" shortName="2 Thess 2:17" orderIndex="16">comfort your hearts and establish them in every good work and word.</Verse>
      </verses>
    </Chapter>
    <Chapter osisId="2Thess.3" sblId="2Thess 3" name="2 Thessalonians 3" shortName="2 Thess 3" orderIndex="2" versesCount="18">
      <verses>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.3.1" sblId="2Thess 3:1" name="2 Thessalonians 3:1" shortName="2 Thess 3:1" orderIndex="0">Finally, brothers, pray for us, that the word of the Lord may speed ahead and be honored, as happened among you,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.3.2" sblId="2Thess 3:2" name="2 Thessalonians 3:2" shortName="2 Thess 3:2" orderIndex="1">and that we may be delivered from wicked and evil men. For not all have faith.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.3.3" sblId="2Thess 3:3" name="2 Thessalonians 3:3" shortName="2 Thess 3:3" orderIndex="2">But the Lord is faithful. He will establish you and guard you against the evil one.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.3.4" sblId="2Thess 3:4" name="2 Thessalonians 3:4" shortName="2 Thess 3:4" orderIndex="3">And we have confidence in the Lord about you, that you are doing and will do the things that we command.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.3.5" sblId="2Thess 3:5" name="2 Thessalonians 3:5" shortName="2 Thess 3:5" orderIndex="4">May the Lord direct your hearts to the love of God and to the steadfastness of Christ.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.3.6" sblId="2Thess 3:6" name="2 Thessalonians 3:6" shortName="2 Thess 3:6" orderIndex="5">Now we command you, brothers, in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that you keep away from any brother who is walking in idleness and not in accord with the tradition that you received from us.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.3.7" sblId="2Thess 3:7" name="2 Thessalonians 3:7" shortName="2 Thess 3:7" orderIndex="6">For you yourselves know how you ought to imitate us, because we were not idle when we were with you,</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.3.8" sblId="2Thess 3:8" name="2 Thessalonians 3:8" shortName="2 Thess 3:8" orderIndex="7">nor did we eat anyone's bread without paying for it, but with toil and labor we worked night and day, that we might not be a burden to any of you.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.3.9" sblId="2Thess 3:9" name="2 Thessalonians 3:9" shortName="2 Thess 3:9" orderIndex="8">It was not because we do not have that right, but to give you in ourselves an example to imitate.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.3.10" sblId="2Thess 3:10" name="2 Thessalonians 3:10" shortName="2 Thess 3:10" orderIndex="9">For even when we were with you, we would give you this command: If anyone is not willing to work, let him not eat.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.3.11" sblId="2Thess 3:11" name="2 Thessalonians 3:11" shortName="2 Thess 3:11" orderIndex="10">For we hear that some among you walk in idleness, not busy at work, but busybodies.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.3.12" sblId="2Thess 3:12" name="2 Thessalonians 3:12" shortName="2 Thess 3:12" orderIndex="11">Now such persons we command and encourage in the Lord Jesus Christ to do their work quietly and to earn their own living.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.3.13" sblId="2Thess 3:13" name="2 Thessalonians 3:13" shortName="2 Thess 3:13" orderIndex="12">As for you, brothers, do not grow weary in doing good.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.3.14" sblId="2Thess 3:14" name="2 Thessalonians 3:14" shortName="2 Thess 3:14" orderIndex="13">If anyone does not obey what we say in this letter, take note of that person, and have nothing to do with him, that he may be ashamed.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.3.15" sblId="2Thess 3:15" name="2 Thessalonians 3:15" shortName="2 Thess 3:15" orderIndex="14">Do not regard him as an enemy, but warn him as a brother.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.3.16" sblId="2Thess 3:16" name="2 Thessalonians 3:16" shortName="2 Thess 3:16" orderIndex="15">Now may the Lord of peace himself give you peace at all times in every way. The Lord be with you all.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.3.17" sblId="2Thess 3:17" name="2 Thessalonians 3:17" shortName="2 Thess 3:17" orderIndex="16">I, Paul, write this greeting with my own hand. This is the sign of genuineness in every letter of mine; it is the way I write.</Verse>
        <Verse osisId="2Thess.3.18" sblId="2Thess 3:18" name="2 Thessalonians 3:18" shortName="2 Thess 3:18" orderIndex="17">The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all.</Verse>
      </verses>
    </Chapter>
  </chapters>
</Book>