<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader/>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book" n="Ps">
        <div type="chapter" n="1">
          <ab n="1">Blessed is the man who does not walk in the counsel of the wicked or stand in the way of sinners or sit in the seat of mockers.</ab>
          <ab n="2">But his delight is in the law of the LORD, and on his law he meditates day and night.</ab>
          <ab n="3">He is like a tree planted by streams of water, which yields its fruit in season and whose leaf does not wither. Whatever he does prospers.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Not so the wicked! They are like chaff that the wind blows away.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Therefore the wicked will not stand in the judgment, nor sinners in the assembly of the righteous.</ab>
          <ab n="6">For the LORD watches over the way of the righteous, but the way of the wicked will perish.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="2">
          <ab n="1">Why do the nations conspire and the peoples plot in vain?</ab>
          <ab n="2">The kings of the earth take their stand and the rulers gather together against the LORD and against his Anointed One.</ab>
          <ab n="3">"Let us break their chains," they say, "and throw off their fetters."</ab>
          <ab n="4">The One enthroned in heaven laughs; the Lord scoffs at them.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Then he rebukes them in his anger and terrifies them in his wrath, saying,</ab>
          <ab n="6">"I have installed my King on Zion, my holy hill."</ab>
          <ab n="7">I will proclaim the decree of the LORD: He said to me, "You are my Son; today I have become your Father.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Ask of me, and I will make the nations your inheritance, the ends of the earth your possession.</ab>
          <ab n="9">You will rule them with an iron scepter; you will dash them to pieces like pottery."</ab>
          <ab n="10">Therefore, you kings, be wise; be warned, you rulers of the earth.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Serve the LORD with fear and rejoice with trembling.</ab>
          <ab n="12">Kiss the Son, lest he be angry and you be destroyed in your way, for his wrath can flare up in a moment. Blessed are all who take refuge in him.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="3">
          <ab n="1">O LORD, how many are my foes! How many rise up against me!</ab>
          <ab n="2">Many are saying of me, "God will not deliver him." Selah</ab>
          <ab n="3">But you are a shield around me, O LORD; you bestow glory on me and lift up my head.</ab>
          <ab n="4">To the LORD I cry aloud, and he answers me from his holy hill. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="5">I lie down and sleep; I wake again, because the LORD sustains me.</ab>
          <ab n="6">I will not fear the tens of thousands drawn up against me on every side.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Arise, O LORD! Deliver me, O my God! Strike all my enemies on the jaw; break the teeth of the wicked.</ab>
          <ab n="8">From the LORD comes deliverance. May your blessing be on your people. Selah</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="4">
          <ab n="1">Answer me when I call to you, O my righteous God. Give me relief from my distress; be merciful to me and hear my prayer.</ab>
          <ab n="2">How long, O men, will you turn my glory into shame? How long will you love delusions and seek false gods? Selah</ab>
          <ab n="3">Know that the LORD has set apart the godly for himself; the LORD will hear when I call to him.</ab>
          <ab n="4">In your anger do not sin; when you are on your beds, search your hearts and be silent. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="5">Offer right sacrifices and trust in the LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Many are asking, "Who can show us any good?" Let the light of your face shine upon us, O LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="7">You have filled my heart with greater joy than when their grain and new wine abound.</ab>
          <ab n="8">I will lie down and sleep in peace, for you alone, O LORD, make me dwell in safety.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="5">
          <ab n="1">Give ear to my words, O LORD, consider my sighing.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Listen to my cry for help, my King and my God, for to you I pray.</ab>
          <ab n="3">In the morning, O LORD, you hear my voice; in the morning I lay my requests before you and wait in expectation.</ab>
          <ab n="4">You are not a God who takes pleasure in evil; with you the wicked cannot dwell.</ab>
          <ab n="5">The arrogant cannot stand in your presence; you hate all who do wrong.</ab>
          <ab n="6">You destroy those who tell lies; bloodthirsty and deceitful men the LORD abhors.</ab>
          <ab n="7">But I, by your great mercy, will come into your house; in reverence will I bow down toward your holy temple.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Lead me, O LORD, in your righteousness because of my enemies- make straight your way before me.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Not a word from their mouth can be trusted; their heart is filled with destruction. Their throat is an open grave; with their tongue they speak deceit.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Declare them guilty, O God! Let their intrigues be their downfall. Banish them for their many sins, for they have rebelled against you.</ab>
          <ab n="11">But let all who take refuge in you be glad; let them ever sing for joy. Spread your protection over them, that those who love your name may rejoice in you.</ab>
          <ab n="12">For surely, O LORD, you bless the righteous; you surround them with your favor as with a shield.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="6">
          <ab n="1">O LORD, do not rebuke me in your anger or discipline me in your wrath.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Be merciful to me, LORD, for I am faint; O LORD, heal me, for my bones are in agony.</ab>
          <ab n="3">My soul is in anguish. How long, O LORD, how long?</ab>
          <ab n="4">Turn, O LORD, and deliver me; save me because of your unfailing love.</ab>
          <ab n="5">No one remembers you when he is dead. Who praises you from the grave?</ab>
          <ab n="6">I am worn out from groaning; all night long I flood my bed with weeping and drench my couch with tears.</ab>
          <ab n="7">My eyes grow weak with sorrow; they fail because of all my foes.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Away from me, all you who do evil, for the LORD has heard my weeping.</ab>
          <ab n="9">The LORD has heard my cry for mercy; the LORD accepts my prayer.</ab>
          <ab n="10">All my enemies will be ashamed and dismayed; they will turn back in sudden disgrace.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="7">
          <ab n="1">O LORD my God, I take refuge in you; save and deliver me from all who pursue me,</ab>
          <ab n="2">or they will tear me like a lion and rip me to pieces with no one to rescue me.</ab>
          <ab n="3">O LORD my God, if I have done this and there is guilt on my hands-</ab>
          <ab n="4">if I have done evil to him who is at peace with me or without cause have robbed my foe-</ab>
          <ab n="5">then let my enemy pursue and overtake me; let him trample my life to the ground and make me sleep in the dust. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="6">Arise, O LORD, in your anger; rise up against the rage of my enemies. Awake, my God; decree justice.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Let the assembled peoples gather around you. Rule over them from on high;</ab>
          <ab n="8">let the LORD judge the peoples. Judge me, O LORD, according to my righteousness, according to my integrity, O Most High.</ab>
          <ab n="9">O righteous God, who searches minds and hearts, bring to an end the violence of the wicked and make the righteous secure.</ab>
          <ab n="10">My shield is God Most High, who saves the upright in heart.</ab>
          <ab n="11">God is a righteous judge, a God who expresses his wrath every day.</ab>
          <ab n="12">If he does not relent, he will sharpen his sword; he will bend and string his bow.</ab>
          <ab n="13">He has prepared his deadly weapons; he makes ready his flaming arrows.</ab>
          <ab n="14">He who is pregnant with evil and conceives trouble gives birth to disillusionment.</ab>
          <ab n="15">He who digs a hole and scoops it out falls into the pit he has made.</ab>
          <ab n="16">The trouble he causes recoils on himself; his violence comes down on his own head.</ab>
          <ab n="17">I will give thanks to the LORD because of his righteousness and will sing praise to the name of the LORD Most High.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="8">
          <ab n="1">O LORD, our Lord, how majestic is your name in all the earth! You have set your glory above the heavens.</ab>
          <ab n="2">From the lips of children and infants you have ordained praise because of your enemies, to silence the foe and the avenger.</ab>
          <ab n="3">When I consider your heavens, the work of your fingers, the moon and the stars, which you have set in place,</ab>
          <ab n="4">what is man that you are mindful of him, the son of man that you care for him?</ab>
          <ab n="5">You made him a little lower than the heavenly beings and crowned him with glory and honor.</ab>
          <ab n="6">You made him ruler over the works of your hands; you put everything under his feet:</ab>
          <ab n="7">all flocks and herds, and the beasts of the field,</ab>
          <ab n="8">the birds of the air, and the fish of the sea, all that swim the paths of the seas.</ab>
          <ab n="9">O LORD, our Lord, how majestic is your name in all the earth!</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="9">
          <ab n="1">I will praise you, O LORD, with all my heart; I will tell of all your wonders.</ab>
          <ab n="2">I will be glad and rejoice in you; I will sing praise to your name, O Most High.</ab>
          <ab n="3">My enemies turn back; they stumble and perish before you.</ab>
          <ab n="4">For you have upheld my right and my cause; you have sat on your throne, judging righteously.</ab>
          <ab n="5">You have rebuked the nations and destroyed the wicked; you have blotted out their name for ever and ever.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Endless ruin has overtaken the enemy, you have uprooted their cities; even the memory of them has perished.</ab>
          <ab n="7">The LORD reigns forever; he has established his throne for judgment.</ab>
          <ab n="8">He will judge the world in righteousness; he will govern the peoples with justice.</ab>
          <ab n="9">The LORD is a refuge for the oppressed, a stronghold in times of trouble.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Those who know your name will trust in you, for you, LORD, have never forsaken those who seek you.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Sing praises to the LORD, enthroned in Zion; proclaim among the nations what he has done.</ab>
          <ab n="12">For he who avenges blood remembers; he does not ignore the cry of the afflicted.</ab>
          <ab n="13">O LORD, see how my enemies persecute me! Have mercy and lift me up from the gates of death,</ab>
          <ab n="14">that I may declare your praises in the gates of the Daughter of Zion and there rejoice in your salvation.</ab>
          <ab n="15">The nations have fallen into the pit they have dug; their feet are caught in the net they have hidden.</ab>
          <ab n="16">The LORD is known by his justice; the wicked are ensnared by the work of their hands. Higgaion. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="17">The wicked return to the grave, all the nations that forget God.</ab>
          <ab n="18">But the needy will not always be forgotten, nor the hope of the afflicted ever perish.</ab>
          <ab n="19">Arise, O LORD, let not man triumph; let the nations be judged in your presence.</ab>
          <ab n="20">Strike them with terror, O LORD; let the nations know they are but men. Selah</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="10">
          <ab n="1">Why, O LORD, do you stand far off? Why do you hide yourself in times of trouble?</ab>
          <ab n="2">In his arrogance the wicked man hunts down the weak, who are caught in the schemes he devises.</ab>
          <ab n="3">He boasts of the cravings of his heart; he blesses the greedy and reviles the LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="4">In his pride the wicked does not seek him; in all his thoughts there is no room for God.</ab>
          <ab n="5">His ways are always prosperous; he is haughty and your laws are far from him; he sneers at all his enemies.</ab>
          <ab n="6">He says to himself, "Nothing will shake me; I'll always be happy and never have trouble."</ab>
          <ab n="7">His mouth is full of curses and lies and threats; trouble and evil are under his tongue.</ab>
          <ab n="8">He lies in wait near the villages; from ambush he murders the innocent, watching in secret for his victims.</ab>
          <ab n="9">He lies in wait like a lion in cover; he lies in wait to catch the helpless; he catches the helpless and drags them off in his net.</ab>
          <ab n="10">His victims are crushed, they collapse; they fall under his strength.</ab>
          <ab n="11">He says to himself, "God has forgotten; he covers his face and never sees."</ab>
          <ab n="12">Arise, LORD! Lift up your hand, O God. Do not forget the helpless.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Why does the wicked man revile God? Why does he say to himself, "He won't call me to account"?</ab>
          <ab n="14">But you, O God, do see trouble and grief; you consider it to take it in hand. The victim commits himself to you; you are the helper of the fatherless.</ab>
          <ab n="15">Break the arm of the wicked and evil man; call him to account for his wickedness that would not be found out.</ab>
          <ab n="16">The LORD is King for ever and ever; the nations will perish from his land.</ab>
          <ab n="17">You hear, O LORD, the desire of the afflicted; you encourage them, and you listen to their cry,</ab>
          <ab n="18">defending the fatherless and the oppressed, in order that man, who is of the earth, may terrify no more.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="11">
          <ab n="1">In the LORD I take refuge. How then can you say to me: "Flee like a bird to your mountain.</ab>
          <ab n="2">For look, the wicked bend their bows; they set their arrows against the strings to shoot from the shadows at the upright in heart.</ab>
          <ab n="3">When the foundations are being destroyed, what can the righteous do?"</ab>
          <ab n="4">The LORD is in his holy temple; the LORD is on his heavenly throne. He observes the sons of men; his eyes examine them.</ab>
          <ab n="5">The LORD examines the righteous, but the wicked and those who love violence his soul hates.</ab>
          <ab n="6">On the wicked he will rain fiery coals and burning sulfur; a scorching wind will be their lot.</ab>
          <ab n="7">For the LORD is righteous, he loves justice; upright men will see his face.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="12">
          <ab n="1">Help, LORD, for the godly are no more; the faithful have vanished from among men.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Everyone lies to his neighbor; their flattering lips speak with deception.</ab>
          <ab n="3">May the LORD cut off all flattering lips and every boastful tongue</ab>
          <ab n="4">that says, "We will triumph with our tongues; we own our lips -who is our master?"</ab>
          <ab n="5">"Because of the oppression of the weak and the groaning of the needy, I will now arise," says the LORD. "I will protect them from those who malign them."</ab>
          <ab n="6">And the words of the LORD are flawless, like silver refined in a furnace of clay, purified seven times.</ab>
          <ab n="7">O LORD, you will keep us safe and protect us from such people forever.</ab>
          <ab n="8">The wicked freely strut about when what is vile is honored among men.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="13">
          <ab n="1">How long, O LORD? Will you forget me forever? How long will you hide your face from me?</ab>
          <ab n="2">How long must I wrestle with my thoughts and every day have sorrow in my heart? How long will my enemy triumph over me?</ab>
          <ab n="3">Look on me and answer, O LORD my God. Give light to my eyes, or I will sleep in death;</ab>
          <ab n="4">my enemy will say, "I have overcome him," and my foes will rejoice when I fall.</ab>
          <ab n="5">But I trust in your unfailing love; my heart rejoices in your salvation.</ab>
          <ab n="6">I will sing to the LORD, for he has been good to me.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="14">
          <ab n="1">The fool says in his heart, "There is no God." They are corrupt, their deeds are vile; there is no one who does good.</ab>
          <ab n="2">The LORD looks down from heaven on the sons of men to see if there are any who understand, any who seek God.</ab>
          <ab n="3">All have turned aside, they have together become corrupt; there is no one who does good, not even one.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Will evildoers never learn- those who devour my people as men eat bread and who do not call on the LORD?</ab>
          <ab n="5">There they are, overwhelmed with dread, for God is present in the company of the righteous.</ab>
          <ab n="6">You evildoers frustrate the plans of the poor, but the LORD is their refuge.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Oh, that salvation for Israel would come out of Zion! When the LORD restores the fortunes of his people, let Jacob rejoice and Israel be glad!</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="15">
          <ab n="1">LORD, who may dwell in your sanctuary? Who may live on your holy hill?</ab>
          <ab n="2">He whose walk is blameless and who does what is righteous, who speaks the truth from his heart</ab>
          <ab n="3">and has no slander on his tongue, who does his neighbor no wrong and casts no slur on his fellowman,</ab>
          <ab n="4">who despises a vile man but honors those who fear the LORD, who keeps his oath even when it hurts,</ab>
          <ab n="5">who lends his money without usury and does not accept a bribe against the innocent. He who does these things will never be shaken.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="16">
          <ab n="1">Keep me safe, O God, for in you I take refuge.</ab>
          <ab n="2">I said to the LORD, "You are my Lord; apart from you I have no good thing."</ab>
          <ab n="3">As for the saints who are in the land, they are the glorious ones in whom is all my delight.</ab>
          <ab n="4">The sorrows of those will increase who run after other gods. I will not pour out their libations of blood or take up their names on my lips.</ab>
          <ab n="5">LORD, you have assigned me my portion and my cup; you have made my lot secure.</ab>
          <ab n="6">The boundary lines have fallen for me in pleasant places; surely I have a delightful inheritance.</ab>
          <ab n="7">I will praise the LORD, who counsels me; even at night my heart instructs me.</ab>
          <ab n="8">I have set the LORD always before me. Because he is at my right hand, I will not be shaken.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Therefore my heart is glad and my tongue rejoices; my body also will rest secure,</ab>
          <ab n="10">because you will not abandon me to the grave, nor will you let your Holy One see decay.</ab>
          <ab n="11">You have made known to me the path of life; you will fill me with joy in your presence, with eternal pleasures at your right hand.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="17">
          <ab n="1">Hear, O LORD, my righteous plea; listen to my cry. Give ear to my prayer- it does not rise from deceitful lips.</ab>
          <ab n="2">May my vindication come from you; may your eyes see what is right.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Though you probe my heart and examine me at night, though you test me, you will find nothing; I have resolved that my mouth will not sin.</ab>
          <ab n="4">As for the deeds of men- by the word of your lips I have kept myself from the ways of the violent.</ab>
          <ab n="5">My steps have held to your paths; my feet have not slipped.</ab>
          <ab n="6">I call on you, O God, for you will answer me; give ear to me and hear my prayer.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Show the wonder of your great love, you who save by your right hand those who take refuge in you from their foes.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Keep me as the apple of your eye; hide me in the shadow of your wings</ab>
          <ab n="9">from the wicked who assail me, from my mortal enemies who surround me.</ab>
          <ab n="10">They close up their callous hearts, and their mouths speak with arrogance.</ab>
          <ab n="11">They have tracked me down, they now surround me, with eyes alert, to throw me to the ground.</ab>
          <ab n="12">They are like a lion hungry for prey, like a great lion crouching in cover.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Rise up, O LORD, confront them, bring them down; rescue me from the wicked by your sword.</ab>
          <ab n="14">O LORD, by your hand save me from such men, from men of this world whose reward is in this life. You still the hunger of those you cherish; their sons have plenty, and they store up wealth for their children.</ab>
          <ab n="15">And I-in righteousness I will see your face; when I awake, I will be satisfied with seeing your likeness.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="18">
          <ab n="1">I love you, O LORD, my strength.</ab>
          <ab n="2">The LORD is my rock, my fortress and my deliverer; my God is my rock, in whom I take refuge. He is my shield and the horn of my salvation, my stronghold.</ab>
          <ab n="3">I call to the LORD, who is worthy of praise, and I am saved from my enemies.</ab>
          <ab n="4">The cords of death entangled me; the torrents of destruction overwhelmed me.</ab>
          <ab n="5">The cords of the grave coiled around me; the snares of death confronted me.</ab>
          <ab n="6">In my distress I called to the LORD; I cried to my God for help. From his temple he heard my voice; my cry came before him, into his ears.</ab>
          <ab n="7">The earth trembled and quaked, and the foundations of the mountains shook; they trembled because he was angry.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Smoke rose from his nostrils; consuming fire came from his mouth, burning coals blazed out of it.</ab>
          <ab n="9">He parted the heavens and came down; dark clouds were under his feet.</ab>
          <ab n="10">He mounted the cherubim and flew; he soared on the wings of the wind.</ab>
          <ab n="11">He made darkness his covering, his canopy around him- the dark rain clouds of the sky.</ab>
          <ab n="12">Out of the brightness of his presence clouds advanced, with hailstones and bolts of lightning.</ab>
          <ab n="13">The LORD thundered from heaven; the voice of the Most High resounded.</ab>
          <ab n="14">He shot his arrows and scattered the enemies, great bolts of lightning and routed them.</ab>
          <ab n="15">The valleys of the sea were exposed and the foundations of the earth laid bare at your rebuke, O LORD, at the blast of breath from your nostrils.</ab>
          <ab n="16">He reached down from on high and took hold of me; he drew me out of deep waters.</ab>
          <ab n="17">He rescued me from my powerful enemy, from my foes, who were too strong for me.</ab>
          <ab n="18">They confronted me in the day of my disaster, but the LORD was my support.</ab>
          <ab n="19">He brought me out into a spacious place; he rescued me because he delighted in me.</ab>
          <ab n="20">The LORD has dealt with me according to my righteousness; according to the cleanness of my hands he has rewarded me.</ab>
          <ab n="21">For I have kept the ways of the LORD; I have not done evil by turning from my God.</ab>
          <ab n="22">All his laws are before me; I have not turned away from his decrees.</ab>
          <ab n="23">I have been blameless before him and have kept myself from sin.</ab>
          <ab n="24">The LORD has rewarded me according to my righteousness, according to the cleanness of my hands in his sight.</ab>
          <ab n="25">To the faithful you show yourself faithful, to the blameless you show yourself blameless,</ab>
          <ab n="26">to the pure you show yourself pure, but to the crooked you show yourself shrewd.</ab>
          <ab n="27">You save the humble but bring low those whose eyes are haughty.</ab>
          <ab n="28">You, O LORD, keep my lamp burning; my God turns my darkness into light.</ab>
          <ab n="29">With your help I can advance against a troop; with my God I can scale a wall.</ab>
          <ab n="30">As for God, his way is perfect; the word of the LORD is flawless. He is a shield for all who take refuge in him.</ab>
          <ab n="31">For who is God besides the LORD? And who is the Rock except our God?</ab>
          <ab n="32">It is God who arms me with strength and makes my way perfect.</ab>
          <ab n="33">He makes my feet like the feet of a deer; he enables me to stand on the heights.</ab>
          <ab n="34">He trains my hands for battle; my arms can bend a bow of bronze.</ab>
          <ab n="35">You give me your shield of victory, and your right hand sustains me; you stoop down to make me great.</ab>
          <ab n="36">You broaden the path beneath me, so that my ankles do not turn.</ab>
          <ab n="37">I pursued my enemies and overtook them; I did not turn back till they were destroyed.</ab>
          <ab n="38">I crushed them so that they could not rise; they fell beneath my feet.</ab>
          <ab n="39">You armed me with strength for battle; you made my adversaries bow at my feet.</ab>
          <ab n="40">You made my enemies turn their backs in flight, and I destroyed my foes.</ab>
          <ab n="41">They cried for help, but there was no one to save them- to the LORD, but he did not answer.</ab>
          <ab n="42">I beat them as fine as dust borne on the wind; I poured them out like mud in the streets.</ab>
          <ab n="43">You have delivered me from the attacks of the people; you have made me the head of nations; people I did not know are subject to me.</ab>
          <ab n="44">As soon as they hear me, they obey me; foreigners cringe before me.</ab>
          <ab n="45">They all lose heart; they come trembling from their strongholds.</ab>
          <ab n="46">The LORD lives! Praise be to my Rock! Exalted be God my Savior!</ab>
          <ab n="47">He is the God who avenges me, who subdues nations under me,</ab>
          <ab n="48">who saves me from my enemies. You exalted me above my foes; from violent men you rescued me.</ab>
          <ab n="49">Therefore I will praise you among the nations, O LORD; I will sing praises to your name.</ab>
          <ab n="50">He gives his king great victories; he shows unfailing kindness to his anointed, to David and his descendants forever.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="19">
          <ab n="1">The heavens declare the glory of God; the skies proclaim the work of his hands.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Day after day they pour forth speech; night after night they display knowledge.</ab>
          <ab n="3">There is no speech or language where their voice is not heard.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Their voice goes out into all the earth, their words to the ends of the world. In the heavens he has pitched a tent for the sun,</ab>
          <ab n="5">which is like a bridegroom coming forth from his pavilion, like a champion rejoicing to run his course.</ab>
          <ab n="6">It rises at one end of the heavens and makes its circuit to the other; nothing is hidden from its heat.</ab>
          <ab n="7">The law of the LORD is perfect, reviving the soul. The statutes of the LORD are trustworthy, making wise the simple.</ab>
          <ab n="8">The precepts of the LORD are right, giving joy to the heart. The commands of the LORD are radiant, giving light to the eyes.</ab>
          <ab n="9">The fear of the LORD is pure, enduring forever. The ordinances of the LORD are sure and altogether righteous.</ab>
          <ab n="10">They are more precious than gold, than much pure gold; they are sweeter than honey, than honey from the comb.</ab>
          <ab n="11">By them is your servant warned; in keeping them there is great reward.</ab>
          <ab n="12">Who can discern his errors? Forgive my hidden faults.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Keep your servant also from willful sins; may they not rule over me. Then will I be blameless, innocent of great transgression.</ab>
          <ab n="14">May the words of my mouth and the meditation of my heart be pleasing in your sight, O Lord, my Rock and my Redeemer.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="20">
          <ab n="1">May the LORD answer you when you are in distress; may the name of the God of Jacob protect you.</ab>
          <ab n="2">May he send you help from the sanctuary and grant you support from Zion.</ab>
          <ab n="3">May he remember all your sacrifices and accept your burnt offerings. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="4">May he give you the desire of your heart and make all your plans succeed.</ab>
          <ab n="5">We will shout for joy when you are victorious and will lift up our banners in the name of our God. May the LORD grant all your requests.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Now I know that the LORD saves his anointed; he answers him from his holy heaven with the saving power of his right hand.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Some trust in chariots and some in horses, but we trust in the name of the LORD our God.</ab>
          <ab n="8">They are brought to their knees and fall, but we rise up and stand firm.</ab>
          <ab n="9">O LORD, save the king! Answer us when we call!</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="21">
          <ab n="1">O LORD, the king rejoices in your strength. How great is his joy in the victories you give!</ab>
          <ab n="2">You have granted him the desire of his heart and have not withheld the request of his lips. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="3">You welcomed him with rich blessings and placed a crown of pure gold on his head.</ab>
          <ab n="4">He asked you for life, and you gave it to him- length of days, for ever and ever.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Through the victories you gave, his glory is great; you have bestowed on him splendor and majesty.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Surely you have granted him eternal blessings and made him glad with the joy of your presence.</ab>
          <ab n="7">For the king trusts in the LORD; through the unfailing love of the Most High he will not be shaken.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Your hand will lay hold on all your enemies; your right hand will seize your foes.</ab>
          <ab n="9">At the time of your appearing you will make them like a fiery furnace. In his wrath the LORD will swallow them up, and his fire will consume them.</ab>
          <ab n="10">You will destroy their descendants from the earth, their posterity from mankind.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Though they plot evil against you and devise wicked schemes, they cannot succeed;</ab>
          <ab n="12">for you will make them turn their backs when you aim at them with drawn bow.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Be exalted, O LORD, in your strength; we will sing and praise your might.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="22">
          <ab n="1">My God, my God, why have you forsaken me? Why are you so far from saving me, so far from the words of my groaning?</ab>
          <ab n="2">O my God, I cry out by day, but you do not answer, by night, and am not silent.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Yet you are enthroned as the Holy One; you are the praise of Israel.</ab>
          <ab n="4">In you our fathers put their trust; they trusted and you delivered them.</ab>
          <ab n="5">They cried to you and were saved; in you they trusted and were not disappointed.</ab>
          <ab n="6">But I am a worm and not a man, scorned by men and despised by the people.</ab>
          <ab n="7">All who see me mock me; they hurl insults, shaking their heads:</ab>
          <ab n="8">"He trusts in the LORD; let the LORD rescue him. Let him deliver him, since he delights in him."</ab>
          <ab n="9">Yet you brought me out of the womb; you made me trust in you even at my mother's breast.</ab>
          <ab n="10">From birth I was cast upon you; from my mother's womb you have been my God.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Do not be far from me, for trouble is near and there is no one to help.</ab>
          <ab n="12">Many bulls surround me; strong bulls of Bashan encircle me.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Roaring lions tearing their prey open their mouths wide against me.</ab>
          <ab n="14">I am poured out like water, and all my bones are out of joint. My heart has turned to wax; it has melted away within me.</ab>
          <ab n="15">My strength is dried up like a potsherd, and my tongue sticks to the roof of my mouth; you lay me in the dust of death.</ab>
          <ab n="16">Dogs have surrounded me; a band of evil men has encircled me, they have pierced my hands and my feet.</ab>
          <ab n="17">I can count all my bones; people stare and gloat over me.</ab>
          <ab n="18">They divide my garments among them and cast lots for my clothing.</ab>
          <ab n="19">But you, O LORD, be not far off; O my Strength, come quickly to help me.</ab>
          <ab n="20">Deliver my life from the sword, my precious life from the power of the dogs.</ab>
          <ab n="21">Rescue me from the mouth of the lions; save me from the horns of the wild oxen.</ab>
          <ab n="22">I will declare your name to my brothers; in the congregation I will praise you.</ab>
          <ab n="23">You who fear the LORD, praise him! All you descendants of Jacob, honor him! Revere him, all you descendants of Israel!</ab>
          <ab n="24">For he has not despised or disdained the suffering of the afflicted one; he has not hidden his face from him but has listened to his cry for help.</ab>
          <ab n="25">From you comes the theme of my praise in the great assembly; before those who fear you will I fulfill my vows.</ab>
          <ab n="26">The poor will eat and be satisfied; they who seek the LORD will praise him- may your hearts live forever!</ab>
          <ab n="27">All the ends of the earth will remember and turn to the LORD, and all the families of the nations will bow down before him,</ab>
          <ab n="28">for dominion belongs to the LORD and he rules over the nations.</ab>
          <ab n="29">All the rich of the earth will feast and worship; all who go down to the dust will kneel before him- those who cannot keep themselves alive.</ab>
          <ab n="30">Posterity will serve him; future generations will be told about the Lord.</ab>
          <ab n="31">They will proclaim his righteousness to a people yet unborn- for he has done it.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="23">
          <ab n="1">The LORD is my shepherd, I shall not be in want.</ab>
          <ab n="2">He makes me lie down in green pastures, he leads me beside quiet waters,</ab>
          <ab n="3">he restores my soul. He guides me in paths of righteousness for his name's sake.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Even though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death, I will fear no evil, for you are with me; your rod and your staff, they comfort me.</ab>
          <ab n="5">You prepare a table before me in the presence of my enemies. You anoint my head with oil; my cup overflows.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Surely goodness and love will follow me all the days of my life, and I will dwell in the house of the LORD forever.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="24">
          <ab n="1">The earth is the LORD's, and everything in it, the world, and all who live in it;</ab>
          <ab n="2">for he founded it upon the seas and established it upon the waters.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Who may ascend the hill of the LORD? Who may stand in his holy place?</ab>
          <ab n="4">He who has clean hands and a pure heart, who does not lift up his soul to an idol or swear by what is false.</ab>
          <ab n="5">He will receive blessing from the LORD and vindication from God his Savior.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Such is the generation of those who seek him, who seek your face, O God of Jacob. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="7">Lift up your heads, O you gates; be lifted up, you ancient doors, that the King of glory may come in.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Who is this King of glory? The LORD strong and mighty, the LORD mighty in battle.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Lift up your heads, O you gates; lift them up, you ancient doors, that the King of glory may come in.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Who is he, this King of glory? The LORD Almighty- he is the King of glory. Selah</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="25">
          <ab n="1">To you, O LORD, I lift up my soul;</ab>
          <ab n="2">in you I trust, O my God. Do not let me be put to shame, nor let my enemies triumph over me.</ab>
          <ab n="3">No one whose hope is in you will ever be put to shame, but they will be put to shame who are treacherous without excuse.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Show me your ways, O LORD, teach me your paths;</ab>
          <ab n="5">guide me in your truth and teach me, for you are God my Savior, and my hope is in you all day long.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Remember, O LORD, your great mercy and love, for they are from of old.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Remember not the sins of my youth and my rebellious ways; according to your love remember me, for you are good, O LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Good and upright is the LORD; therefore he instructs sinners in his ways.</ab>
          <ab n="9">He guides the humble in what is right and teaches them his way.</ab>
          <ab n="10">All the ways of the LORD are loving and faithful for those who keep the demands of his covenant.</ab>
          <ab n="11">For the sake of your name, O LORD, forgive my iniquity, though it is great.</ab>
          <ab n="12">Who, then, is the man that fears the LORD? He will instruct him in the way chosen for him.</ab>
          <ab n="13">He will spend his days in prosperity, and his descendants will inherit the land.</ab>
          <ab n="14">The LORD confides in those who fear him; he makes his covenant known to them.</ab>
          <ab n="15">My eyes are ever on the LORD, for only he will release my feet from the snare.</ab>
          <ab n="16">Turn to me and be gracious to me, for I am lonely and afflicted.</ab>
          <ab n="17">The troubles of my heart have multiplied; free me from my anguish.</ab>
          <ab n="18">Look upon my affliction and my distress and take away all my sins.</ab>
          <ab n="19">See how my enemies have increased and how fiercely they hate me!</ab>
          <ab n="20">Guard my life and rescue me; let me not be put to shame, for I take refuge in you.</ab>
          <ab n="21">May integrity and uprightness protect me, because my hope is in you.</ab>
          <ab n="22">Redeem Israel, O God, from all their troubles!</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="26">
          <ab n="1">Vindicate me, O LORD, for I have led a blameless life; I have trusted in the LORD without wavering.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Test me, O LORD, and try me, examine my heart and my mind;</ab>
          <ab n="3">for your love is ever before me, and I walk continually in your truth.</ab>
          <ab n="4">I do not sit with deceitful men, nor do I consort with hypocrites;</ab>
          <ab n="5">I abhor the assembly of evildoers and refuse to sit with the wicked.</ab>
          <ab n="6">I wash my hands in innocence, and go about your altar, O LORD,</ab>
          <ab n="7">proclaiming aloud your praise and telling of all your wonderful deeds.</ab>
          <ab n="8">I love the house where you live, O LORD, the place where your glory dwells.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Do not take away my soul along with sinners, my life with bloodthirsty men,</ab>
          <ab n="10">in whose hands are wicked schemes, whose right hands are full of bribes.</ab>
          <ab n="11">But I lead a blameless life; redeem me and be merciful to me.</ab>
          <ab n="12">My feet stand on level ground; in the great assembly I will praise the LORD.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="27">
          <ab n="1">The LORD is my light and my salvation- whom shall I fear? The LORD is the stronghold of my life- of whom shall I be afraid?</ab>
          <ab n="2">When evil men advance against me to devour my flesh, when my enemies and my foes attack me, they will stumble and fall.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Though an army besiege me, my heart will not fear; though war break out against me, even then will I be confident.</ab>
          <ab n="4">One thing I ask of the LORD, this is what I seek: that I may dwell in the house of the LORD all the days of my life, to gaze upon the beauty of the LORD and to seek him in his temple.</ab>
          <ab n="5">For in the day of trouble he will keep me safe in his dwelling; he will hide me in the shelter of his tabernacle and set me high upon a rock.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Then my head will be exalted above the enemies who surround me; at his tabernacle will I sacrifice with shouts of joy; I will sing and make music to the LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Hear my voice when I call, O LORD; be merciful to me and answer me.</ab>
          <ab n="8">My heart says of you, "Seek his face!" Your face, LORD, I will seek.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Do not hide your face from me, do not turn your servant away in anger; you have been my helper. Do not reject me or forsake me, O God my Savior.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Though my father and mother forsake me, the LORD will receive me.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Teach me your way, O LORD; lead me in a straight path because of my oppressors.</ab>
          <ab n="12">Do not turn me over to the desire of my foes, for false witnesses rise up against me, breathing out violence.</ab>
          <ab n="13">I am still confident of this: I will see the goodness of the LORD in the land of the living.</ab>
          <ab n="14">Wait for the LORD; be strong and take heart and wait for the LORD.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="28">
          <ab n="1">To you I call, O LORD my Rock; do not turn a deaf ear to me. For if you remain silent, I will be like those who have gone down to the pit.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Hear my cry for mercy as I call to you for help, as I lift up my hands toward your Most Holy Place.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Do not drag me away with the wicked, with those who do evil, who speak cordially with their neighbors but harbor malice in their hearts.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Repay them for their deeds and for their evil work; repay them for what their hands have done and bring back upon them what they deserve.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Since they show no regard for the works of the LORD and what his hands have done, he will tear them down and never build them up again.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Praise be to the LORD, for he has heard my cry for mercy.</ab>
          <ab n="7">The LORD is my strength and my shield; my heart trusts in him, and I am helped. My heart leaps for joy and I will give thanks to him in song.</ab>
          <ab n="8">The LORD is the strength of his people, a fortress of salvation for his anointed one.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Save your people and bless your inheritance; be their shepherd and carry them forever.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="29">
          <ab n="1">Ascribe to the LORD, O mighty ones, ascribe to the LORD glory and strength.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Ascribe to the LORD the glory due his name; worship the LORD in the splendor of his holiness.</ab>
          <ab n="3">The voice of the LORD is over the waters; the God of glory thunders, the LORD thunders over the mighty waters.</ab>
          <ab n="4">The voice of the LORD is powerful; the voice of the LORD is majestic.</ab>
          <ab n="5">The voice of the LORD breaks the cedars; the LORD breaks in pieces the cedars of Lebanon.</ab>
          <ab n="6">He makes Lebanon skip like a calf, Sirion like a young wild ox.</ab>
          <ab n="7">The voice of the LORD strikes with flashes of lightning.</ab>
          <ab n="8">The voice of the LORD shakes the desert; the LORD shakes the Desert of Kadesh.</ab>
          <ab n="9">The voice of the LORD twists the oaks and strips the forests bare. And in his temple all cry, "Glory!"</ab>
          <ab n="10">The LORD sits enthroned over the flood; the LORD is enthroned as King forever.</ab>
          <ab n="11">The LORD gives strength to his people; the LORD blesses his people with peace.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="30">
          <ab n="1">I will exalt you, O LORD, for you lifted me out of the depths and did not let my enemies gloat over me.</ab>
          <ab n="2">O LORD my God, I called to you for help and you healed me.</ab>
          <ab n="3">O LORD, you brought me up from the grave; you spared me from going down into the pit.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Sing to the LORD, you saints of his; praise his holy name.</ab>
          <ab n="5">For his anger lasts only a moment, but his favor lasts a lifetime; weeping may remain for a night, but rejoicing comes in the morning.</ab>
          <ab n="6">When I felt secure, I said, "I will never be shaken."</ab>
          <ab n="7">O LORD, when you favored me, you made my mountain stand firm; but when you hid your face, I was dismayed.</ab>
          <ab n="8">To you, O LORD, I called; to the Lord I cried for mercy:</ab>
          <ab n="9">"What gain is there in my destruction, in my going down into the pit? Will the dust praise you? Will it proclaim your faithfulness?</ab>
          <ab n="10">Hear, O LORD, and be merciful to me; O LORD, be my help."</ab>
          <ab n="11">You turned my wailing into dancing; you removed my sackcloth and clothed me with joy,</ab>
          <ab n="12">that my heart may sing to you and not be silent. O LORD my God, I will give you thanks forever.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="31">
          <ab n="1">In you, O LORD, I have taken refuge; let me never be put to shame; deliver me in your righteousness.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Turn your ear to me, come quickly to my rescue; be my rock of refuge, a strong fortress to save me.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Since you are my rock and my fortress, for the sake of your name lead and guide me.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Free me from the trap that is set for me, for you are my refuge.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Into your hands I commit my spirit; redeem me, O LORD, the God of truth.</ab>
          <ab n="6">I hate those who cling to worthless idols; I trust in the LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="7">I will be glad and rejoice in your love, for you saw my affliction and knew the anguish of my soul.</ab>
          <ab n="8">You have not handed me over to the enemy but have set my feet in a spacious place.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Be merciful to me, O LORD, for I am in distress; my eyes grow weak with sorrow, my soul and my body with grief.</ab>
          <ab n="10">My life is consumed by anguish and my years by groaning; my strength fails because of my affliction, and my bones grow weak.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Because of all my enemies, I am the utter contempt of my neighbors; I am a dread to my friends- those who see me on the street flee from me.</ab>
          <ab n="12">I am forgotten by them as though I were dead; I have become like broken pottery.</ab>
          <ab n="13">For I hear the slander of many; there is terror on every side; they conspire against me and plot to take my life.</ab>
          <ab n="14">But I trust in you, O LORD; I say, "You are my God."</ab>
          <ab n="15">My times are in your hands; deliver me from my enemies and from those who pursue me.</ab>
          <ab n="16">Let your face shine on your servant; save me in your unfailing love.</ab>
          <ab n="17">Let me not be put to shame, O LORD, for I have cried out to you; but let the wicked be put to shame and lie silent in the grave.</ab>
          <ab n="18">Let their lying lips be silenced, for with pride and contempt they speak arrogantly against the righteous.</ab>
          <ab n="19">How great is your goodness, which you have stored up for those who fear you, which you bestow in the sight of men on those who take refuge in you.</ab>
          <ab n="20">In the shelter of your presence you hide them from the intrigues of men; in your dwelling you keep them safe from accusing tongues.</ab>
          <ab n="21">Praise be to the LORD, for he showed his wonderful love to me when I was in a besieged city.</ab>
          <ab n="22">In my alarm I said, "I am cut off from your sight!" Yet you heard my cry for mercy when I called to you for help.</ab>
          <ab n="23">Love the LORD, all his saints! The LORD preserves the faithful, but the proud he pays back in full.</ab>
          <ab n="24">Be strong and take heart, all you who hope in the LORD.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="32">
          <ab n="1">Blessed is he whose transgressions are forgiven, whose sins are covered.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Blessed is the man whose sin the LORD does not count against him and in whose spirit is no deceit.</ab>
          <ab n="3">When I kept silent, my bones wasted away through my groaning all day long.</ab>
          <ab n="4">For day and night your hand was heavy upon me; my strength was sapped as in the heat of summer. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="5">Then I acknowledged my sin to you and did not cover up my iniquity. I said, "I will confess my transgressions to the LORD "- and you forgave the guilt of my sin. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="6">Therefore let everyone who is godly pray to you while you may be found; surely when the mighty waters rise, they will not reach him.</ab>
          <ab n="7">You are my hiding place; you will protect me from trouble and surround me with songs of deliverance. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="8">I will instruct you and teach you in the way you should go; I will counsel you and watch over you.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Do not be like the horse or the mule, which have no understanding but must be controlled by bit and bridle or they will not come to you.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Many are the woes of the wicked, but the LORD's unfailing love surrounds the man who trusts in him.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Rejoice in the LORD and be glad, you righteous; sing, all you who are upright in heart!</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="33">
          <ab n="1">Sing joyfully to the LORD, you righteous; it is fitting for the upright to praise him.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Praise the LORD with the harp; make music to him on the ten-stringed lyre.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Sing to him a new song; play skillfully, and shout for joy.</ab>
          <ab n="4">For the word of the LORD is right and true; he is faithful in all he does.</ab>
          <ab n="5">The LORD loves righteousness and justice; the earth is full of his unfailing love.</ab>
          <ab n="6">By the word of the LORD were the heavens made, their starry host by the breath of his mouth.</ab>
          <ab n="7">He gathers the waters of the sea into jars; he puts the deep into storehouses.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Let all the earth fear the LORD; let all the people of the world revere him.</ab>
          <ab n="9">For he spoke, and it came to be; he commanded, and it stood firm.</ab>
          <ab n="10">The LORD foils the plans of the nations; he thwarts the purposes of the peoples.</ab>
          <ab n="11">But the plans of the LORD stand firm forever, the purposes of his heart through all generations.</ab>
          <ab n="12">Blessed is the nation whose God is the LORD, the people he chose for his inheritance.</ab>
          <ab n="13">From heaven the LORD looks down and sees all mankind;</ab>
          <ab n="14">from his dwelling place he watches all who live on earth-</ab>
          <ab n="15">he who forms the hearts of all, who considers everything they do.</ab>
          <ab n="16">No king is saved by the size of his army; no warrior escapes by his great strength.</ab>
          <ab n="17">A horse is a vain hope for deliverance; despite all its great strength it cannot save.</ab>
          <ab n="18">But the eyes of the LORD are on those who fear him, on those whose hope is in his unfailing love,</ab>
          <ab n="19">to deliver them from death and keep them alive in famine.</ab>
          <ab n="20">We wait in hope for the LORD; he is our help and our shield.</ab>
          <ab n="21">In him our hearts rejoice, for we trust in his holy name.</ab>
          <ab n="22">May your unfailing love rest upon us, O LORD, even as we put our hope in you.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="34">
          <ab n="1">I will extol the LORD at all times; his praise will always be on my lips.</ab>
          <ab n="2">My soul will boast in the LORD; let the afflicted hear and rejoice.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Glorify the LORD with me; let us exalt his name together.</ab>
          <ab n="4">I sought the LORD, and he answered me; he delivered me from all my fears.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Those who look to him are radiant; their faces are never covered with shame.</ab>
          <ab n="6">This poor man called, and the LORD heard him; he saved him out of all his troubles.</ab>
          <ab n="7">The angel of the LORD encamps around those who fear him, and he delivers them.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Taste and see that the LORD is good; blessed is the man who takes refuge in him.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Fear the LORD, you his saints, for those who fear him lack nothing.</ab>
          <ab n="10">The lions may grow weak and hungry, but those who seek the LORD lack no good thing.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Come, my children, listen to me; I will teach you the fear of the LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="12">Whoever of you loves life and desires to see many good days,</ab>
          <ab n="13">keep your tongue from evil and your lips from speaking lies.</ab>
          <ab n="14">Turn from evil and do good; seek peace and pursue it.</ab>
          <ab n="15">The eyes of the LORD are on the righteous and his ears are attentive to their cry;</ab>
          <ab n="16">the face of the LORD is against those who do evil, to cut off the memory of them from the earth.</ab>
          <ab n="17">The righteous cry out, and the LORD hears them; he delivers them from all their troubles.</ab>
          <ab n="18">The LORD is close to the brokenhearted and saves those who are crushed in spirit.</ab>
          <ab n="19">A righteous man may have many troubles, but the LORD delivers him from them all;</ab>
          <ab n="20">he protects all his bones, not one of them will be broken.</ab>
          <ab n="21">Evil will slay the wicked; the foes of the righteous will be condemned.</ab>
          <ab n="22">The LORD redeems his servants; no one will be condemned who takes refuge in him.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="35">
          <ab n="1">Contend, O LORD, with those who contend with me; fight against those who fight against me.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Take up shield and buckler; arise and come to my aid.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Brandish spear and javelin against those who pursue me. Say to my soul, "I am your salvation."</ab>
          <ab n="4">May those who seek my life be disgraced and put to shame; may those who plot my ruin be turned back in dismay.</ab>
          <ab n="5">May they be like chaff before the wind, with the angel of the LORD driving them away;</ab>
          <ab n="6">may their path be dark and slippery, with the angel of the LORD pursuing them.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Since they hid their net for me without cause and without cause dug a pit for me,</ab>
          <ab n="8">may ruin overtake them by surprise- may the net they hid entangle them, may they fall into the pit, to their ruin.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Then my soul will rejoice in the LORD and delight in his salvation.</ab>
          <ab n="10">My whole being will exclaim, "Who is like you, O LORD? You rescue the poor from those too strong for them, the poor and needy from those who rob them."</ab>
          <ab n="11">Ruthless witnesses come forward; they question me on things I know nothing about.</ab>
          <ab n="12">They repay me evil for good and leave my soul forlorn.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Yet when they were ill, I put on sackcloth and humbled myself with fasting. When my prayers returned to me unanswered,</ab>
          <ab n="14">I went about mourning as though for my friend or brother. I bowed my head in grief as though weeping for my mother.</ab>
          <ab n="15">But when I stumbled, they gathered in glee; attackers gathered against me when I was unaware. They slandered me without ceasing.</ab>
          <ab n="16">Like the ungodly they maliciously mocked; they gnashed their teeth at me.</ab>
          <ab n="17">O Lord, how long will you look on? Rescue my life from their ravages, my precious life from these lions.</ab>
          <ab n="18">I will give you thanks in the great assembly; among throngs of people I will praise you.</ab>
          <ab n="19">Let not those gloat over me who are my enemies without cause; let not those who hate me without reason maliciously wink the eye.</ab>
          <ab n="20">They do not speak peaceably, but devise false accusations against those who live quietly in the land.</ab>
          <ab n="21">They gape at me and say, "Aha! Aha! With our own eyes we have seen it."</ab>
          <ab n="22">O LORD, you have seen this; be not silent. Do not be far from me, O Lord.</ab>
          <ab n="23">Awake, and rise to my defense! Contend for me, my God and Lord.</ab>
          <ab n="24">Vindicate me in your righteousness, O LORD my God; do not let them gloat over me.</ab>
          <ab n="25">Do not let them think, "Aha, just what we wanted!" or say, "We have swallowed him up."</ab>
          <ab n="26">May all who gloat over my distress be put to shame and confusion; may all who exalt themselves over me be clothed with shame and disgrace.</ab>
          <ab n="27">May those who delight in my vindication shout for joy and gladness; may they always say, "The LORD be exalted, who delights in the well-being of his servant."</ab>
          <ab n="28">My tongue will speak of your righteousness and of your praises all day long.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="36">
          <ab n="1">An oracle is within my heart concerning the sinfulness of the wicked: There is no fear of God before his eyes.</ab>
          <ab n="2">For in his own eyes he flatters himself too much to detect or hate his sin.</ab>
          <ab n="3">The words of his mouth are wicked and deceitful; he has ceased to be wise and to do good.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Even on his bed he plots evil; he commits himself to a sinful course and does not reject what is wrong.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Your love, O LORD, reaches to the heavens, your faithfulness to the skies.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Your righteousness is like the mighty mountains, your justice like the great deep. O LORD, you preserve both man and beast.</ab>
          <ab n="7">How priceless is your unfailing love! Both high and low among men find refuge in the shadow of your wings.</ab>
          <ab n="8">They feast on the abundance of your house; you give them drink from your river of delights.</ab>
          <ab n="9">For with you is the fountain of life; in your light we see light.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Continue your love to those who know you, your righteousness to the upright in heart.</ab>
          <ab n="11">May the foot of the proud not come against me, nor the hand of the wicked drive me away.</ab>
          <ab n="12">See how the evildoers lie fallen- thrown down, not able to rise!</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="37">
          <ab n="1">Do not fret because of evil men or be envious of those who do wrong;</ab>
          <ab n="2">for like the grass they will soon wither, like green plants they will soon die away.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Trust in the LORD and do good; dwell in the land and enjoy safe pasture.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Delight yourself in the LORD and he will give you the desires of your heart.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Commit your way to the LORD; trust in him and he will do this:</ab>
          <ab n="6">He will make your righteousness shine like the dawn, the justice of your cause like the noonday sun.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Be still before the LORD and wait patiently for him; do not fret when men succeed in their ways, when they carry out their wicked schemes.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Refrain from anger and turn from wrath; do not fret-it leads only to evil.</ab>
          <ab n="9">For evil men will be cut off, but those who hope in the LORD will inherit the land.</ab>
          <ab n="10">A little while, and the wicked will be no more; though you look for them, they will not be found.</ab>
          <ab n="11">But the meek will inherit the land and enjoy great peace.</ab>
          <ab n="12">The wicked plot against the righteous and gnash their teeth at them;</ab>
          <ab n="13">but the Lord laughs at the wicked, for he knows their day is coming.</ab>
          <ab n="14">The wicked draw the sword and bend the bow to bring down the poor and needy, to slay those whose ways are upright.</ab>
          <ab n="15">But their swords will pierce their own hearts, and their bows will be broken.</ab>
          <ab n="16">Better the little that the righteous have than the wealth of many wicked;</ab>
          <ab n="17">for the power of the wicked will be broken, but the LORD upholds the righteous.</ab>
          <ab n="18">The days of the blameless are known to the LORD, and their inheritance will endure forever.</ab>
          <ab n="19">In times of disaster they will not wither; in days of famine they will enjoy plenty.</ab>
          <ab n="20">But the wicked will perish: The LORD's enemies will be like the beauty of the fields, they will vanish-vanish like smoke.</ab>
          <ab n="21">The wicked borrow and do not repay, but the righteous give generously;</ab>
          <ab n="22">those the LORD blesses will inherit the land, but those he curses will be cut off.</ab>
          <ab n="23">If the LORD delights in a man's way, he makes his steps firm;</ab>
          <ab n="24">though he stumble, he will not fall, for the LORD upholds him with his hand.</ab>
          <ab n="25">I was young and now I am old, yet I have never seen the righteous forsaken or their children begging bread.</ab>
          <ab n="26">They are always generous and lend freely; their children will be blessed.</ab>
          <ab n="27">Turn from evil and do good; then you will dwell in the land forever.</ab>
          <ab n="28">For the LORD loves the just and will not forsake his faithful ones. They will be protected forever, but the offspring of the wicked will be cut off;</ab>
          <ab n="29">the righteous will inherit the land and dwell in it forever.</ab>
          <ab n="30">The mouth of the righteous man utters wisdom, and his tongue speaks what is just.</ab>
          <ab n="31">The law of his God is in his heart; his feet do not slip.</ab>
          <ab n="32">The wicked lie in wait for the righteous, seeking their very lives;</ab>
          <ab n="33">but the LORD will not leave them in their power or let them be condemned when brought to trial.</ab>
          <ab n="34">Wait for the LORD and keep his way. He will exalt you to inherit the land; when the wicked are cut off, you will see it.</ab>
          <ab n="35">I have seen a wicked and ruthless man flourishing like a green tree in its native soil,</ab>
          <ab n="36">but he soon passed away and was no more; though I looked for him, he could not be found.</ab>
          <ab n="37">Consider the blameless, observe the upright; there is a future for the man of peace.</ab>
          <ab n="38">But all sinners will be destroyed; the future of the wicked will be cut off.</ab>
          <ab n="39">The salvation of the righteous comes from the LORD; he is their stronghold in time of trouble.</ab>
          <ab n="40">The LORD helps them and delivers them; he delivers them from the wicked and saves them, because they take refuge in him.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="38">
          <ab n="1">O LORD, do not rebuke me in your anger or discipline me in your wrath.</ab>
          <ab n="2">For your arrows have pierced me, and your hand has come down upon me.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Because of your wrath there is no health in my body; my bones have no soundness because of my sin.</ab>
          <ab n="4">My guilt has overwhelmed me like a burden too heavy to bear.</ab>
          <ab n="5">My wounds fester and are loathsome because of my sinful folly.</ab>
          <ab n="6">I am bowed down and brought very low; all day long I go about mourning.</ab>
          <ab n="7">My back is filled with searing pain; there is no health in my body.</ab>
          <ab n="8">I am feeble and utterly crushed; I groan in anguish of heart.</ab>
          <ab n="9">All my longings lie open before you, O Lord; my sighing is not hidden from you.</ab>
          <ab n="10">My heart pounds, my strength fails me; even the light has gone from my eyes.</ab>
          <ab n="11">My friends and companions avoid me because of my wounds; my neighbors stay far away.</ab>
          <ab n="12">Those who seek my life set their traps, those who would harm me talk of my ruin; all day long they plot deception.</ab>
          <ab n="13">I am like a deaf man, who cannot hear, like a mute, who cannot open his mouth;</ab>
          <ab n="14">I have become like a man who does not hear, whose mouth can offer no reply.</ab>
          <ab n="15">I wait for you, O LORD; you will answer, O Lord my God.</ab>
          <ab n="16">For I said, "Do not let them gloat or exalt themselves over me when my foot slips."</ab>
          <ab n="17">For I am about to fall, and my pain is ever with me.</ab>
          <ab n="18">I confess my iniquity; I am troubled by my sin.</ab>
          <ab n="19">Many are those who are my vigorous enemies; those who hate me without reason are numerous.</ab>
          <ab n="20">Those who repay my good with evil slander me when I pursue what is good.</ab>
          <ab n="21">O LORD, do not forsake me; be not far from me, O my God.</ab>
          <ab n="22">Come quickly to help me, O Lord my Savior.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="39">
          <ab n="1">I said, "I will watch my ways and keep my tongue from sin; I will put a muzzle on my mouth as long as the wicked are in my presence."</ab>
          <ab n="2">But when I was silent and still, not even saying anything good, my anguish increased.</ab>
          <ab n="3">My heart grew hot within me, and as I meditated, the fire burned; then I spoke with my tongue:</ab>
          <ab n="4">"Show me, O LORD, my life's end and the number of my days; let me know how fleeting is my life.</ab>
          <ab n="5">You have made my days a mere handbreadth; the span of my years is as nothing before you. Each man's life is but a breath. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="6">Man is a mere phantom as he goes to and fro: He bustles about, but only in vain; he heaps up wealth, not knowing who will get it.</ab>
          <ab n="7">"But now, Lord, what do I look for? My hope is in you.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Save me from all my transgressions; do not make me the scorn of fools.</ab>
          <ab n="9">I was silent; I would not open my mouth, for you are the one who has done this.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Remove your scourge from me; I am overcome by the blow of your hand.</ab>
          <ab n="11">You rebuke and discipline men for their sin; you consume their wealth like a moth- each man is but a breath. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="12">"Hear my prayer, O LORD, listen to my cry for help; be not deaf to my weeping. For I dwell with you as an alien, a stranger, as all my fathers were.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Look away from me, that I may rejoice again before I depart and am no more."</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="40">
          <ab n="1">I waited patiently for the LORD; he turned to me and heard my cry.</ab>
          <ab n="2">He lifted me out of the slimy pit, out of the mud and mire; he set my feet on a rock and gave me a firm place to stand.</ab>
          <ab n="3">He put a new song in my mouth, a hymn of praise to our God. Many will see and fear and put their trust in the LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Blessed is the man who makes the LORD his trust, who does not look to the proud, to those who turn aside to false gods.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Many, O LORD my God, are the wonders you have done. The things you planned for us no one can recount to you; were I to speak and tell of them, they would be too many to declare.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Sacrifice and offering you did not desire, but my ears you have pierced,; burnt offerings and sin offerings you did not require.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Then I said, "Here I am, I have come- it is written about me in the scroll.</ab>
          <ab n="8">I desire to do your will, O my God; your law is within my heart."</ab>
          <ab n="9">I proclaim righteousness in the great assembly; I do not seal my lips, as you know, O LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="10">I do not hide your righteousness in my heart; I speak of your faithfulness and salvation. I do not conceal your love and your truth from the great assembly.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Do not withhold your mercy from me, O LORD; may your love and your truth always protect me.</ab>
          <ab n="12">For troubles without number surround me; my sins have overtaken me, and I cannot see. They are more than the hairs of my head, and my heart fails within me.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Be pleased, O LORD, to save me; O LORD, come quickly to help me.</ab>
          <ab n="14">May all who seek to take my life be put to shame and confusion; may all who desire my ruin be turned back in disgrace.</ab>
          <ab n="15">May those who say to me, "Aha! Aha!" be appalled at their own shame.</ab>
          <ab n="16">But may all who seek you rejoice and be glad in you; may those who love your salvation always say, "The LORD be exalted!"</ab>
          <ab n="17">Yet I am poor and needy; may the Lord think of me. You are my help and my deliverer; O my God, do not delay.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="41">
          <ab n="1">Blessed is he who has regard for the weak; the LORD delivers him in times of trouble.</ab>
          <ab n="2">The LORD will protect him and preserve his life; he will bless him in the land and not surrender him to the desire of his foes.</ab>
          <ab n="3">The LORD will sustain him on his sickbed and restore him from his bed of illness.</ab>
          <ab n="4">I said, "O LORD, have mercy on me; heal me, for I have sinned against you."</ab>
          <ab n="5">My enemies say of me in malice, "When will he die and his name perish?"</ab>
          <ab n="6">Whenever one comes to see me, he speaks falsely, while his heart gathers slander; then he goes out and spreads it abroad.</ab>
          <ab n="7">All my enemies whisper together against me; they imagine the worst for me, saying,</ab>
          <ab n="8">"A vile disease has beset him; he will never get up from the place where he lies."</ab>
          <ab n="9">Even my close friend, whom I trusted, he who shared my bread, has lifted up his heel against me.</ab>
          <ab n="10">But you, O LORD, have mercy on me; raise me up, that I may repay them.</ab>
          <ab n="11">I know that you are pleased with me, for my enemy does not triumph over me.</ab>
          <ab n="12">In my integrity you uphold me and set me in your presence forever.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Praise be to the LORD, the God of Israel, from everlasting to everlasting. Amen and Amen.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="42">
          <ab n="1">As the deer pants for streams of water, so my soul pants for you, O God.</ab>
          <ab n="2">My soul thirsts for God, for the living God. When can I go and meet with God?</ab>
          <ab n="3">My tears have been my food day and night, while men say to me all day long, "Where is your God?"</ab>
          <ab n="4">These things I remember as I pour out my soul: how I used to go with the multitude, leading the procession to the house of God, with shouts of joy and thanksgiving among the festive throng.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Why are you downcast, O my soul? Why so disturbed within me? Put your hope in God, for I will yet praise him, my Savior and</ab>
          <ab n="6">my God. My soul is downcast within me; therefore I will remember you from the land of the Jordan, the heights of Hermon-from Mount Mizar.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Deep calls to deep in the roar of your waterfalls; all your waves and breakers have swept over me.</ab>
          <ab n="8">By day the LORD directs his love, at night his song is with me- a prayer to the God of my life.</ab>
          <ab n="9">I say to God my Rock, "Why have you forgotten me? Why must I go about mourning, oppressed by the enemy?"</ab>
          <ab n="10">My bones suffer mortal agony as my foes taunt me, saying to me all day long, "Where is your God?"</ab>
          <ab n="11">Why are you downcast, O my soul? Why so disturbed within me? Put your hope in God, for I will yet praise him, my Savior and my God.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="43">
          <ab n="1">Vindicate me, O God, and plead my cause against an ungodly nation; rescue me from deceitful and wicked men.</ab>
          <ab n="2">You are God my stronghold. Why have you rejected me? Why must I go about mourning, oppressed by the enemy?</ab>
          <ab n="3">Send forth your light and your truth, let them guide me; let them bring me to your holy mountain, to the place where you dwell.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Then will I go to the altar of God, to God, my joy and my delight. I will praise you with the harp, O God, my God.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Why are you downcast, O my soul? Why so disturbed within me? Put your hope in God, for I will yet praise him, my Savior and my God.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="44">
          <ab n="1">We have heard with our ears, O God; our fathers have told us what you did in their days, in days long ago.</ab>
          <ab n="2">With your hand you drove out the nations and planted our fathers; you crushed the peoples and made our fathers flourish.</ab>
          <ab n="3">It was not by their sword that they won the land, nor did their arm bring them victory; it was your right hand, your arm, and the light of your face, for you loved them.</ab>
          <ab n="4">You are my King and my God, who decrees victories for Jacob.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Through you we push back our enemies; through your name we trample our foes.</ab>
          <ab n="6">I do not trust in my bow, my sword does not bring me victory;</ab>
          <ab n="7">but you give us victory over our enemies, you put our adversaries to shame.</ab>
          <ab n="8">In God we make our boast all day long, and we will praise your name forever. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="9">But now you have rejected and humbled us; you no longer go out with our armies.</ab>
          <ab n="10">You made us retreat before the enemy, and our adversaries have plundered us.</ab>
          <ab n="11">You gave us up to be devoured like sheep and have scattered us among the nations.</ab>
          <ab n="12">You sold your people for a pittance, gaining nothing from their sale.</ab>
          <ab n="13">You have made us a reproach to our neighbors, the scorn and derision of those around us.</ab>
          <ab n="14">You have made us a byword among the nations; the peoples shake their heads at us.</ab>
          <ab n="15">My disgrace is before me all day long, and my face is covered with shame</ab>
          <ab n="16">at the taunts of those who reproach and revile me, because of the enemy, who is bent on revenge.</ab>
          <ab n="17">All this happened to us, though we had not forgotten you or been false to your covenant.</ab>
          <ab n="18">Our hearts had not turned back; our feet had not strayed from your path.</ab>
          <ab n="19">But you crushed us and made us a haunt for jackals and covered us over with deep darkness.</ab>
          <ab n="20">If we had forgotten the name of our God or spread out our hands to a foreign god,</ab>
          <ab n="21">would not God have discovered it, since he knows the secrets of the heart?</ab>
          <ab n="22">Yet for your sake we face death all day long; we are considered as sheep to be slaughtered.</ab>
          <ab n="23">Awake, O Lord! Why do you sleep? Rouse yourself! Do not reject us forever.</ab>
          <ab n="24">Why do you hide your face and forget our misery and oppression?</ab>
          <ab n="25">We are brought down to the dust; our bodies cling to the ground.</ab>
          <ab n="26">Rise up and help us; redeem us because of your unfailing love.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="45">
          <ab n="1">My heart is stirred by a noble theme as I recite my verses for the king; my tongue is the pen of a skillful writer.</ab>
          <ab n="2">You are the most excellent of men and your lips have been anointed with grace, since God has blessed you forever.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Gird your sword upon your side, O mighty one; clothe yourself with splendor and majesty.</ab>
          <ab n="4">In your majesty ride forth victoriously in behalf of truth, humility and righteousness; let your right hand display awesome deeds.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Let your sharp arrows pierce the hearts of the king's enemies; let the nations fall beneath your feet.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Your throne, O God, will last for ever and ever; a scepter of justice will be the scepter of your kingdom.</ab>
          <ab n="7">You love righteousness and hate wickedness; therefore God, your God, has set you above your companions by anointing you with the oil of joy.</ab>
          <ab n="8">All your robes are fragrant with myrrh and aloes and cassia; from palaces adorned with ivory the music of the strings makes you glad.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Daughters of kings are among your honored women; at your right hand is the royal bride in gold of Ophir.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Listen, O daughter, consider and give ear: Forget your people and your father's house.</ab>
          <ab n="11">The king is enthralled by your beauty; honor him, for he is your lord.</ab>
          <ab n="12">The Daughter of Tyre will come with a gift, men of wealth will seek your favor.</ab>
          <ab n="13">All glorious is the princess within her chamber; her gown is interwoven with gold.</ab>
          <ab n="14">In embroidered garments she is led to the king; her virgin companions follow her and are brought to you.</ab>
          <ab n="15">They are led in with joy and gladness; they enter the palace of the king.</ab>
          <ab n="16">Your sons will take the place of your fathers; you will make them princes throughout the land.</ab>
          <ab n="17">I will perpetuate your memory through all generations; therefore the nations will praise you for ever and ever.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="46">
          <ab n="1">God is our refuge and strength, an ever-present help in trouble.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Therefore we will not fear, though the earth give way and the mountains fall into the heart of the sea,</ab>
          <ab n="3">though its waters roar and foam and the mountains quake with their surging. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="4">There is a river whose streams make glad the city of God, the holy place where the Most High dwells.</ab>
          <ab n="5">God is within her, she will not fall; God will help her at break of day.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Nations are in uproar, kingdoms fall; he lifts his voice, the earth melts.</ab>
          <ab n="7">The LORD Almighty is with us; the God of Jacob is our fortress. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="8">Come and see the works of the LORD, the desolations he has brought on the earth.</ab>
          <ab n="9">He makes wars cease to the ends of the earth; he breaks the bow and shatters the spear, he burns the shields with fire.</ab>
          <ab n="10">"Be still, and know that I am God; I will be exalted among the nations, I will be exalted in the earth."</ab>
          <ab n="11">The LORD Almighty is with us; the God of Jacob is our fortress. Selah</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="47">
          <ab n="1">Clap your hands, all you nations; shout to God with cries of joy.</ab>
          <ab n="2">How awesome is the LORD Most High, the great King over all the earth!</ab>
          <ab n="3">He subdued nations under us, peoples under our feet.</ab>
          <ab n="4">He chose our inheritance for us, the pride of Jacob, whom he loved. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="5">God has ascended amid shouts of joy, the LORD amid the sounding of trumpets.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Sing praises to God, sing praises; sing praises to our King, sing praises.</ab>
          <ab n="7">For God is the King of all the earth; sing to him a psalm of praise.</ab>
          <ab n="8">God reigns over the nations; God is seated on his holy throne.</ab>
          <ab n="9">The nobles of the nations assemble as the people of the God of Abraham, for the kings of the earth belong to God; he is greatly exalted.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="48">
          <ab n="1">Great is the LORD, and most worthy of praise, in the city of our God, his holy mountain.</ab>
          <ab n="2">It is beautiful in its loftiness, the joy of the whole earth. Like the utmost heights of Zaphon is Mount Zion, the city of the Great King.</ab>
          <ab n="3">God is in her citadels; he has shown himself to be her fortress.</ab>
          <ab n="4">When the kings joined forces, when they advanced together,</ab>
          <ab n="5">they saw her and were astounded; they fled in terror.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Trembling seized them there, pain like that of a woman in labor.</ab>
          <ab n="7">You destroyed them like ships of Tarshish shattered by an east wind.</ab>
          <ab n="8">As we have heard, so have we seen in the city of the LORD Almighty, in the city of our God: God makes her secure forever. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="9">Within your temple, O God, we meditate on your unfailing love.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Like your name, O God, your praise reaches to the ends of the earth; your right hand is filled with righteousness.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Mount Zion rejoices, the villages of Judah are glad because of your judgments.</ab>
          <ab n="12">Walk about Zion, go around her, count her towers,</ab>
          <ab n="13">consider well her ramparts, view her citadels, that you may tell of them to the next generation.</ab>
          <ab n="14">For this God is our God for ever and ever; he will be our guide even to the end.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="49">
          <ab n="1">Hear this, all you peoples; listen, all who live in this world,</ab>
          <ab n="2">both low and high, rich and poor alike:</ab>
          <ab n="3">My mouth will speak words of wisdom; the utterance from my heart will give understanding.</ab>
          <ab n="4">I will turn my ear to a proverb; with the harp I will expound my riddle:</ab>
          <ab n="5">Why should I fear when evil days come, when wicked deceivers surround me-</ab>
          <ab n="6">those who trust in their wealth and boast of their great riches?</ab>
          <ab n="7">No man can redeem the life of another or give to God a ransom for him-</ab>
          <ab n="8">the ransom for a life is costly, no payment is ever enough-</ab>
          <ab n="9">that he should live on forever and not see decay.</ab>
          <ab n="10">For all can see that wise men die; the foolish and the senseless alike perish and leave their wealth to others.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Their tombs will remain their houses forever, their dwellings for endless generations, though they had named lands after themselves.</ab>
          <ab n="12">But man, despite his riches, does not endure; he is like the beasts that perish.</ab>
          <ab n="13">This is the fate of those who trust in themselves, and of their followers, who approve their sayings. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="14">Like sheep they are destined for the grave, and death will feed on them. The upright will rule over them in the morning; their forms will decay in the grave, far from their princely mansions.</ab>
          <ab n="15">But God will redeem my life from the grave; he will surely take me to himself. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="16">Do not be overawed when a man grows rich, when the splendor of his house increases;</ab>
          <ab n="17">for he will take nothing with him when he dies, his splendor will not descend with him.</ab>
          <ab n="18">Though while he lived he counted himself blessed- and men praise you when you prosper-</ab>
          <ab n="19">he will join the generation of his fathers, who will never see the light of life.</ab>
          <ab n="20">A man who has riches without understanding is like the beasts that perish.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="50">
          <ab n="1">The Mighty One, God, the LORD, speaks and summons the earth from the rising of the sun to the place where it sets.</ab>
          <ab n="2">From Zion, perfect in beauty, God shines forth.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Our God comes and will not be silent; a fire devours before him, and around him a tempest rages.</ab>
          <ab n="4">He summons the heavens above, and the earth, that he may judge his people:</ab>
          <ab n="5">"Gather to me my consecrated ones, who made a covenant with me by sacrifice."</ab>
          <ab n="6">And the heavens proclaim his righteousness, for God himself is judge. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="7">"Hear, O my people, and I will speak, O Israel, and I will testify against you: I am God, your God.</ab>
          <ab n="8">I do not rebuke you for your sacrifices or your burnt offerings, which are ever before me.</ab>
          <ab n="9">I have no need of a bull from your stall or of goats from your pens,</ab>
          <ab n="10">for every animal of the forest is mine, and the cattle on a thousand hills.</ab>
          <ab n="11">I know every bird in the mountains, and the creatures of the field are mine.</ab>
          <ab n="12">If I were hungry I would not tell you, for the world is mine, and all that is in it.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Do I eat the flesh of bulls or drink the blood of goats?</ab>
          <ab n="14">Sacrifice thank offerings to God, fulfill your vows to the Most High,</ab>
          <ab n="15">and call upon me in the day of trouble; I will deliver you, and you will honor me."</ab>
          <ab n="16">But to the wicked, God says: "What right have you to recite my laws or take my covenant on your lips?</ab>
          <ab n="17">You hate my instruction and cast my words behind you.</ab>
          <ab n="18">When you see a thief, you join with him; you throw in your lot with adulterers.</ab>
          <ab n="19">You use your mouth for evil and harness your tongue to deceit.</ab>
          <ab n="20">You speak continually against your brother and slander your own mother's son.</ab>
          <ab n="21">These things you have done and I kept silent; you thought I was altogether like you. But I will rebuke you and accuse you to your face.</ab>
          <ab n="22">"Consider this, you who forget God, or I will tear you to pieces, with none to rescue:</ab>
          <ab n="23">He who sacrifices thank offerings honors me, and he prepares the way so that I may show him the salvation of God."</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="51">
          <ab n="1">Have mercy on me, O God, according to your unfailing love; according to your great compassion blot out my transgressions.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Wash away all my iniquity and cleanse me from my sin.</ab>
          <ab n="3">For I know my transgressions, and my sin is always before me.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Against you, you only, have I sinned and done what is evil in your sight, so that you are proved right when you speak and justified when you judge.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Surely I was sinful at birth, sinful from the time my mother conceived me.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Surely you desire truth in the inner parts; you teach me wisdom in the inmost place.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Cleanse me with hyssop, and I will be clean; wash me, and I will be whiter than snow.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Let me hear joy and gladness; let the bones you have crushed rejoice.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Hide your face from my sins and blot out all my iniquity.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Create in me a pure heart, O God, and renew a steadfast spirit within me.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Do not cast me from your presence or take your Holy Spirit from me.</ab>
          <ab n="12">Restore to me the joy of your salvation and grant me a willing spirit, to sustain me.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Then I will teach transgressors your ways, and sinners will turn back to you.</ab>
          <ab n="14">Save me from bloodguilt, O God, the God who saves me, and my tongue will sing of your righteousness.</ab>
          <ab n="15">O Lord, open my lips, and my mouth will declare your praise.</ab>
          <ab n="16">You do not delight in sacrifice, or I would bring it; you do not take pleasure in burnt offerings.</ab>
          <ab n="17">The sacrifices of God are a broken spirit; a broken and contrite heart, O God, you will not despise.</ab>
          <ab n="18">In your good pleasure make Zion prosper; build up the walls of Jerusalem.</ab>
          <ab n="19">Then there will be righteous sacrifices, whole burnt offerings to delight you; then bulls will be offered on your altar.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="52">
          <ab n="1">Why do you boast of evil, you mighty man? Why do you boast all day long, you who are a disgrace in the eyes of God?</ab>
          <ab n="2">Your tongue plots destruction; it is like a sharpened razor, you who practice deceit.</ab>
          <ab n="3">You love evil rather than good, falsehood rather than speaking the truth. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="4">You love every harmful word, O you deceitful tongue!</ab>
          <ab n="5">Surely God will bring you down to everlasting ruin: He will snatch you up and tear you from your tent; he will uproot you from the land of the living. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="6">The righteous will see and fear; they will laugh at him, saying,</ab>
          <ab n="7">"Here now is the man who did not make God his stronghold but trusted in his great wealth and grew strong by destroying others!"</ab>
          <ab n="8">But I am like an olive tree flourishing in the house of God; I trust in God's unfailing love for ever and ever.</ab>
          <ab n="9">I will praise you forever for what you have done; in your name I will hope, for your name is good. I will praise you in the presence of your saints.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="53">
          <ab n="1">The fool says in his heart, "There is no God." They are corrupt, and their ways are vile; there is no one who does good.</ab>
          <ab n="2">God looks down from heaven on the sons of men to see if there are any who understand, any who seek God.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Everyone has turned away, they have together become corrupt; there is no one who does good, not even one.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Will the evildoers never learn- those who devour my people as men eat bread and who do not call on God?</ab>
          <ab n="5">There they were, overwhelmed with dread, where there was nothing to dread. God scattered the bones of those who attacked you; you put them to shame, for God despised them.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Oh, that salvation for Israel would come out of Zion! When God restores the fortunes of his people, let Jacob rejoice and Israel be glad!</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="54">
          <ab n="1">Save me, O God, by your name; vindicate me by your might.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Hear my prayer, O God; listen to the words of my mouth.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Strangers are attacking me; ruthless men seek my life- men without regard for God. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="4">Surely God is my help; the Lord is the one who sustains me.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Let evil recoil on those who slander me; in your faithfulness destroy them.</ab>
          <ab n="6">I will sacrifice a freewill offering to you; I will praise your name, O LORD, for it is good.</ab>
          <ab n="7">For he has delivered me from all my troubles, and my eyes have looked in triumph on my foes.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="55">
          <ab n="1">Listen to my prayer, O God, do not ignore my plea;</ab>
          <ab n="2">hear me and answer me. My thoughts trouble me and I am distraught</ab>
          <ab n="3">at the voice of the enemy, at the stares of the wicked; for they bring down suffering upon me and revile me in their anger.</ab>
          <ab n="4">My heart is in anguish within me; the terrors of death assail me.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Fear and trembling have beset me; horror has overwhelmed me.</ab>
          <ab n="6">I said, "Oh, that I had the wings of a dove! I would fly away and be at rest-</ab>
          <ab n="7">I would flee far away and stay in the desert; Selah</ab>
          <ab n="8">I would hurry to my place of shelter, far from the tempest and storm."</ab>
          <ab n="9">Confuse the wicked, O Lord, confound their speech, for I see violence and strife in the city.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Day and night they prowl about on its walls; malice and abuse are within it.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Destructive forces are at work in the city; threats and lies never leave its streets.</ab>
          <ab n="12">If an enemy were insulting me, I could endure it; if a foe were raising himself against me, I could hide from him.</ab>
          <ab n="13">But it is you, a man like myself, my companion, my close friend,</ab>
          <ab n="14">with whom I once enjoyed sweet fellowship as we walked with the throng at the house of God.</ab>
          <ab n="15">Let death take my enemies by surprise; let them go down alive to the grave, for evil finds lodging among them.</ab>
          <ab n="16">But I call to God, and the LORD saves me.</ab>
          <ab n="17">Evening, morning and noon I cry out in distress, and he hears my voice.</ab>
          <ab n="18">He ransoms me unharmed from the battle waged against me, even though many oppose me.</ab>
          <ab n="19">God, who is enthroned forever, will hear them and afflict them- Selah men who never change their ways and have no fear of God.</ab>
          <ab n="20">My companion attacks his friends; he violates his covenant.</ab>
          <ab n="21">His speech is smooth as butter, yet war is in his heart; his words are more soothing than oil, yet they are drawn swords.</ab>
          <ab n="22">Cast your cares on the LORD and he will sustain you; he will never let the righteous fall.</ab>
          <ab n="23">But you, O God, will bring down the wicked into the pit of corruption; bloodthirsty and deceitful men will not live out half their days. But as for me, I trust in you.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="56">
          <ab n="1">Be merciful to me, O God, for men hotly pursue me; all day long they press their attack.</ab>
          <ab n="2">My slanderers pursue me all day long; many are attacking me in their pride.</ab>
          <ab n="3">When I am afraid, I will trust in you.</ab>
          <ab n="4">In God, whose word I praise, in God I trust; I will not be afraid. What can mortal man do to me?</ab>
          <ab n="5">All day long they twist my words; they are always plotting to harm me.</ab>
          <ab n="6">They conspire, they lurk, they watch my steps, eager to take my life.</ab>
          <ab n="7">On no account let them escape; in your anger, O God, bring down the nations.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Record my lament; list my tears on your scroll - are they not in your record?</ab>
          <ab n="9">Then my enemies will turn back when I call for help. By this I will know that God is for me.</ab>
          <ab n="10">In God, whose word I praise, in the LORD, whose word I praise-</ab>
          <ab n="11">in God I trust; I will not be afraid. What can man do to me?</ab>
          <ab n="12">I am under vows to you, O God; I will present my thank offerings to you.</ab>
          <ab n="13">For you have delivered me from death and my feet from stumbling, that I may walk before God in the light of life.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="57">
          <ab n="1">Have mercy on me, O God, have mercy on me, for in you my soul takes refuge. I will take refuge in the shadow of your wings until the disaster has passed.</ab>
          <ab n="2">I cry out to God Most High, to God, who fulfills {his purpose} for me.</ab>
          <ab n="3">He sends from heaven and saves me, rebuking those who hotly pursue me; Selah God sends his love and his faithfulness.</ab>
          <ab n="4">I am in the midst of lions; I lie among ravenous beasts- men whose teeth are spears and arrows, whose tongues are sharp swords.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Be exalted, O God, above the heavens; let your glory be over all the earth.</ab>
          <ab n="6">They spread a net for my feet- I was bowed down in distress. They dug a pit in my path- but they have fallen into it themselves. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="7">My heart is steadfast, O God, my heart is steadfast; I will sing and make music.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Awake, my soul! Awake, harp and lyre! I will awaken the dawn.</ab>
          <ab n="9">I will praise you, O Lord, among the nations; I will sing of you among the peoples.</ab>
          <ab n="10">For great is your love, reaching to the heavens; your faithfulness reaches to the skies.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Be exalted, O God, above the heavens; let your glory be over all the earth.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="58">
          <ab n="1">Do you rulers indeed speak justly? Do you judge uprightly among men?</ab>
          <ab n="2">No, in your heart you devise injustice, and your hands mete out violence on the earth.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Even from birth the wicked go astray; from the womb they are wayward and speak lies.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Their venom is like the venom of a snake, like that of a cobra that has stopped its ears,</ab>
          <ab n="5">that will not heed the tune of the charmer, however skillful the enchanter may be.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Break the teeth in their mouths, O God; tear out, O LORD, the fangs of the lions!</ab>
          <ab n="7">Let them vanish like water that flows away; when they draw the bow, let their arrows be blunted.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Like a slug melting away as it moves along, like a stillborn child, may they not see the sun.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Before your pots can feel the heat of the thorns- whether they be green or dry-the wicked will be swept away.</ab>
          <ab n="10">The righteous will be glad when they are avenged, when they bathe their feet in the blood of the wicked.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Then men will say, "Surely the righteous still are rewarded; surely there is a God who judges the earth."</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="59">
          <ab n="1">Deliver me from my enemies, O God; protect me from those who rise up against me.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Deliver me from evildoers and save me from bloodthirsty men.</ab>
          <ab n="3">See how they lie in wait for me! Fierce men conspire against me for no offense or sin of mine, O LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="4">I have done no wrong, yet they are ready to attack me. Arise to help me; look on my plight!</ab>
          <ab n="5">O LORD God Almighty, the God of Israel, rouse yourself to punish all the nations; show no mercy to wicked traitors. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="6">They return at evening, snarling like dogs, and prowl about the city.</ab>
          <ab n="7">See what they spew from their mouths- they spew out swords from their lips, and they say, "Who can hear us?"</ab>
          <ab n="8">But you, O LORD, laugh at them; you scoff at all those nations.</ab>
          <ab n="9">O my Strength, I watch for you; you, O God, are my fortress,</ab>
          <ab n="10">my loving God. God will go before me and will let me gloat over those who slander me.</ab>
          <ab n="11">But do not kill them, O Lord our shield, or my people will forget. In your might make them wander about, and bring them down.</ab>
          <ab n="12">For the sins of their mouths, for the words of their lips, let them be caught in their pride. For the curses and lies they utter,</ab>
          <ab n="13">consume them in wrath, consume them till they are no more. Then it will be known to the ends of the earth that God rules over Jacob. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="14">They return at evening, snarling like dogs, and prowl about the city.</ab>
          <ab n="15">They wander about for food and howl if not satisfied.</ab>
          <ab n="16">But I will sing of your strength, in the morning I will sing of your love; for you are my fortress, my refuge in times of trouble.</ab>
          <ab n="17">O my Strength, I sing praise to you; you, O God, are my fortress, my loving God.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="60">
          <ab n="1">You have rejected us, O God, and burst forth upon us; you have been angry-now restore us!</ab>
          <ab n="2">You have shaken the land and torn it open; mend its fractures, for it is quaking.</ab>
          <ab n="3">You have shown your people desperate times; you have given us wine that makes us stagger.</ab>
          <ab n="4">But for those who fear you, you have raised a banner to be unfurled against the bow. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="5">Save us and help us with your right hand, that those you love may be delivered.</ab>
          <ab n="6">God has spoken from his sanctuary: "In triumph I will parcel out Shechem and measure off the Valley of Succoth.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Gilead is mine, and Manasseh is mine; Ephraim is my helmet, Judah my scepter.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Moab is my washbasin, upon Edom I toss my sandal; over Philistia I shout in triumph."</ab>
          <ab n="9">Who will bring me to the fortified city? Who will lead me to Edom?</ab>
          <ab n="10">Is it not you, O God, you who have rejected us and no longer go out with our armies?</ab>
          <ab n="11">Give us aid against the enemy, for the help of man is worthless.</ab>
          <ab n="12">With God we will gain the victory, and he will trample down our enemies.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="61">
          <ab n="1">Hear my cry, O God; listen to my prayer.</ab>
          <ab n="2">From the ends of the earth I call to you, I call as my heart grows faint; lead me to the rock that is higher than I.</ab>
          <ab n="3">For you have been my refuge, a strong tower against the foe.</ab>
          <ab n="4">I long to dwell in your tent forever and take refuge in the shelter of your wings. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="5">For you have heard my vows, O God; you have given me the heritage of those who fear your name.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Increase the days of the king's life, his years for many generations.</ab>
          <ab n="7">May he be enthroned in God's presence forever; appoint your love and faithfulness to protect him.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Then will I ever sing praise to your name and fulfill my vows day after day.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="62">
          <ab n="1">My soul finds rest in God alone; my salvation comes from him.</ab>
          <ab n="2">He alone is my rock and my salvation; he is my fortress, I will never be shaken.</ab>
          <ab n="3">How long will you assault a man? Would all of you throw him down- this leaning wall, this tottering fence?</ab>
          <ab n="4">They fully intend to topple him from his lofty place; they take delight in lies. With their mouths they bless, but in their hearts they curse. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="5">Find rest, O my soul, in God alone; my hope comes from him.</ab>
          <ab n="6">He alone is my rock and my salvation; he is my fortress, I will not be shaken.</ab>
          <ab n="7">My salvation and my honor depend on God; he is my mighty rock, my refuge.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Trust in him at all times, O people; pour out your hearts to him, for God is our refuge. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="9">Lowborn men are but a breath, the highborn are but a lie; if weighed on a balance, they are nothing; together they are only a breath.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Do not trust in extortion or take pride in stolen goods; though your riches increase, do not set your heart on them.</ab>
          <ab n="11">One thing God has spoken, two things have I heard: that you, O God, are strong,</ab>
          <ab n="12">and that you, O Lord, are loving. Surely you will reward each person according to what he has done.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="63">
          <ab n="1">O God, you are my God, earnestly I seek you; my soul thirsts for you, my body longs for you, in a dry and weary land where there is no water.</ab>
          <ab n="2">I have seen you in the sanctuary and beheld your power and your glory.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Because your love is better than life, my lips will glorify you.</ab>
          <ab n="4">I will praise you as long as I live, and in your name I will lift up my hands.</ab>
          <ab n="5">My soul will be satisfied as with the richest of foods; with singing lips my mouth will praise you.</ab>
          <ab n="6">On my bed I remember you; I think of you through the watches of the night.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Because you are my help, I sing in the shadow of your wings.</ab>
          <ab n="8">My soul clings to you; your right hand upholds me.</ab>
          <ab n="9">They who seek my life will be destroyed; they will go down to the depths of the earth.</ab>
          <ab n="10">They will be given over to the sword and become food for jackals.</ab>
          <ab n="11">But the king will rejoice in God; all who swear by God's name will praise him, while the mouths of liars will be silenced.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="64">
          <ab n="1">Hear me, O God, as I voice my complaint; protect my life from the threat of the enemy.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Hide me from the conspiracy of the wicked, from that noisy crowd of evildoers.</ab>
          <ab n="3">They sharpen their tongues like swords and aim their words like deadly arrows.</ab>
          <ab n="4">They shoot from ambush at the innocent man; they shoot at him suddenly, without fear.</ab>
          <ab n="5">They encourage each other in evil plans, they talk about hiding their snares; they say, "Who will see them?"</ab>
          <ab n="6">They plot injustice and say, "We have devised a perfect plan!" Surely the mind and heart of man are cunning.</ab>
          <ab n="7">But God will shoot them with arrows; suddenly they will be struck down.</ab>
          <ab n="8">He will turn their own tongues against them and bring them to ruin; all who see them will shake their heads in scorn.</ab>
          <ab n="9">All mankind will fear; they will proclaim the works of God and ponder what he has done.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Let the righteous rejoice in the LORD and take refuge in him; let all the upright in heart praise him!</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="65">
          <ab n="1">Praise awaits you, O God, in Zion; to you our vows will be fulfilled.</ab>
          <ab n="2">O you who hear prayer, to you all men will come.</ab>
          <ab n="3">When we were overwhelmed by sins, you forgave our transgressions.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Blessed are those you choose and bring near to live in your courts! We are filled with the good things of your house, of your holy temple.</ab>
          <ab n="5">You answer us with awesome deeds of righteousness, O God our Savior, the hope of all the ends of the earth and of the farthest seas,</ab>
          <ab n="6">who formed the mountains by your power, having armed yourself with strength,</ab>
          <ab n="7">who stilled the roaring of the seas, the roaring of their waves, and the turmoil of the nations.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Those living far away fear your wonders; where morning dawns and evening fades you call forth songs of joy.</ab>
          <ab n="9">You care for the land and water it; you enrich it abundantly. The streams of God are filled with water to provide the people with grain, for so you have ordained it.</ab>
          <ab n="10">You drench its furrows and level its ridges; you soften it with showers and bless its crops.</ab>
          <ab n="11">You crown the year with your bounty, and your carts overflow with abundance.</ab>
          <ab n="12">The grasslands of the desert overflow; the hills are clothed with gladness.</ab>
          <ab n="13">The meadows are covered with flocks and the valleys are mantled with grain; they shout for joy and sing.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="66">
          <ab n="1">Shout with joy to God, all the earth!</ab>
          <ab n="2">Sing the glory of his name; make his praise glorious!</ab>
          <ab n="3">Say to God, "How awesome are your deeds! So great is your power that your enemies cringe before you.</ab>
          <ab n="4">All the earth bows down to you; they sing praise to you, they sing praise to your name." Selah</ab>
          <ab n="5">Come and see what God has done, how awesome his works in man's behalf!</ab>
          <ab n="6">He turned the sea into dry land, they passed through the waters on foot- come, let us rejoice in him.</ab>
          <ab n="7">He rules forever by his power, his eyes watch the nations- let not the rebellious rise up against him. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="8">Praise our God, O peoples, let the sound of his praise be heard;</ab>
          <ab n="9">he has preserved our lives and kept our feet from slipping.</ab>
          <ab n="10">For you, O God, tested us; you refined us like silver.</ab>
          <ab n="11">You brought us into prison and laid burdens on our backs.</ab>
          <ab n="12">You let men ride over our heads; we went through fire and water, but you brought us to a place of abundance.</ab>
          <ab n="13">I will come to your temple with burnt offerings and fulfill my vows to you-</ab>
          <ab n="14">vows my lips promised and my mouth spoke when I was in trouble.</ab>
          <ab n="15">I will sacrifice fat animals to you and an offering of rams; I will offer bulls and goats. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="16">Come and listen, all you who fear God; let me tell you what he has done for me.</ab>
          <ab n="17">I cried out to him with my mouth; his praise was on my tongue.</ab>
          <ab n="18">If I had cherished sin in my heart, the Lord would not have listened;</ab>
          <ab n="19">but God has surely listened and heard my voice in prayer.</ab>
          <ab n="20">Praise be to God, who has not rejected my prayer or withheld his love from me!</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="67">
          <ab n="1">May God be gracious to us and bless us and make his face shine upon us, Selah</ab>
          <ab n="2">that your ways may be known on earth, your salvation among all nations.</ab>
          <ab n="3">May the peoples praise you, O God; may all the peoples praise you.</ab>
          <ab n="4">May the nations be glad and sing for joy, for you rule the peoples justly and guide the nations of the earth. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="5">May the peoples praise you, O God; may all the peoples praise you.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Then the land will yield its harvest, and God, our God, will bless us.</ab>
          <ab n="7">God will bless us, and all the ends of the earth will fear him.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="68">
          <ab n="1">May God arise, may his enemies be scattered; may his foes flee before him.</ab>
          <ab n="2">As smoke is blown away by the wind, may you blow them away; as wax melts before the fire, may the wicked perish before God.</ab>
          <ab n="3">But may the righteous be glad and rejoice before God; may they be happy and joyful.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Sing to God, sing praise to his name, extol him who rides on the clouds - his name is the LORD - and rejoice before him.</ab>
          <ab n="5">A father to the fatherless, a defender of widows, is God in his holy dwelling.</ab>
          <ab n="6">God sets the lonely in families, he leads forth the prisoners with singing; but the rebellious live in a sun-scorched land.</ab>
          <ab n="7">When you went out before your people, O God, when you marched through the wasteland, Selah</ab>
          <ab n="8">the earth shook, the heavens poured down rain, before God, the One of Sinai, before God, the God of Israel.</ab>
          <ab n="9">You gave abundant showers, O God; you refreshed your weary inheritance.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Your people settled in it, and from your bounty, O God, you provided for the poor.</ab>
          <ab n="11">The Lord announced the word, and great was the company of those who proclaimed it:</ab>
          <ab n="12">"Kings and armies flee in haste; in the camps men divide the plunder.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Even while you sleep among the campfires, the wings of my dove are sheathed with silver, its feathers with shining gold."</ab>
          <ab n="14">When the Almighty scattered the kings in the land, it was like snow fallen on Zalmon.</ab>
          <ab n="15">The mountains of Bashan are majestic mountains; rugged are the mountains of Bashan.</ab>
          <ab n="16">Why gaze in envy, O rugged mountains, at the mountain where God chooses to reign, where the LORD himself will dwell forever?</ab>
          <ab n="17">The chariots of God are tens of thousands and thousands of thousands; the Lord has come from Sinai into his sanctuary.</ab>
          <ab n="18">When you ascended on high, you led captives in your train; you received gifts from men, even from the rebellious- that you, O LORD God, might dwell there.</ab>
          <ab n="19">Praise be to the Lord, to God our Savior, who daily bears our burdens. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="20">Our God is a God who saves; from the Sovereign LORD comes escape from death.</ab>
          <ab n="21">Surely God will crush the heads of his enemies, the hairy crowns of those who go on in their sins.</ab>
          <ab n="22">The Lord says, "I will bring them from Bashan; I will bring them from the depths of the sea,</ab>
          <ab n="23">that you may plunge your feet in the blood of your foes, while the tongues of your dogs have their share."</ab>
          <ab n="24">Your procession has come into view, O God, the procession of my God and King into the sanctuary.</ab>
          <ab n="25">In front are the singers, after them the musicians; with them are the maidens playing tambourines.</ab>
          <ab n="26">Praise God in the great congregation; praise the LORD in the assembly of Israel.</ab>
          <ab n="27">There is the little tribe of Benjamin, leading them, there the great throng of Judah's princes, and there the princes of Zebulun and of Naphtali.</ab>
          <ab n="28">Summon your power, O God; show us your strength, O God, as you have done before.</ab>
          <ab n="29">Because of your temple at Jerusalem kings will bring you gifts.</ab>
          <ab n="30">Rebuke the beast among the reeds, the herd of bulls among the calves of the nations. Humbled, may it bring bars of silver. Scatter the nations who delight in war.</ab>
          <ab n="31">Envoys will come from Egypt; Cush will submit herself to God.</ab>
          <ab n="32">Sing to God, O kingdoms of the earth, sing praise to the Lord, Selah</ab>
          <ab n="33">to him who rides the ancient skies above, who thunders with mighty voice.</ab>
          <ab n="34">Proclaim the power of God, whose majesty is over Israel, whose power is in the skies.</ab>
          <ab n="35">You are awesome, O God, in your sanctuary; the God of Israel gives power and strength to his people. Praise be to God!</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="69">
          <ab n="1">Save me, O God, for the waters have come up to my neck.</ab>
          <ab n="2">I sink in the miry depths, where there is no foothold. I have come into the deep waters; the floods engulf me.</ab>
          <ab n="3">I am worn out calling for help; my throat is parched. My eyes fail, looking for my God.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Those who hate me without reason outnumber the hairs of my head; many are my enemies without cause, those who seek to destroy me. I am forced to restore what I did not steal.</ab>
          <ab n="5">You know my folly, O God; my guilt is not hidden from you.</ab>
          <ab n="6">May those who hope in you not be disgraced because of me, O Lord, the LORD Almighty; may those who seek you not be put to shame because of me, O God of Israel.</ab>
          <ab n="7">For I endure scorn for your sake, and shame covers my face.</ab>
          <ab n="8">I am a stranger to my brothers, an alien to my own mother's sons;</ab>
          <ab n="9">for zeal for your house consumes me, and the insults of those who insult you fall on me.</ab>
          <ab n="10">When I weep and fast, I must endure scorn;</ab>
          <ab n="11">when I put on sackcloth, people make sport of me.</ab>
          <ab n="12">Those who sit at the gate mock me, and I am the song of the drunkards.</ab>
          <ab n="13">But I pray to you, O LORD, in the time of your favor; in your great love, O God, answer me with your sure salvation.</ab>
          <ab n="14">Rescue me from the mire, do not let me sink; deliver me from those who hate me, from the deep waters.</ab>
          <ab n="15">Do not let the floodwaters engulf me or the depths swallow me up or the pit close its mouth over me.</ab>
          <ab n="16">Answer me, O LORD, out of the goodness of your love; in your great mercy turn to me.</ab>
          <ab n="17">Do not hide your face from your servant; answer me quickly, for I am in trouble.</ab>
          <ab n="18">Come near and rescue me; redeem me because of my foes.</ab>
          <ab n="19">You know how I am scorned, disgraced and shamed; all my enemies are before you.</ab>
          <ab n="20">Scorn has broken my heart and has left me helpless; I looked for sympathy, but there was none, for comforters, but I found none.</ab>
          <ab n="21">They put gall in my food and gave me vinegar for my thirst.</ab>
          <ab n="22">May the table set before them become a snare; may it become retribution and a trap.</ab>
          <ab n="23">May their eyes be darkened so they cannot see, and their backs be bent forever.</ab>
          <ab n="24">Pour out your wrath on them; let your fierce anger overtake them.</ab>
          <ab n="25">May their place be deserted; let there be no one to dwell in their tents.</ab>
          <ab n="26">For they persecute those you wound and talk about the pain of those you hurt.</ab>
          <ab n="27">Charge them with crime upon crime; do not let them share in your salvation.</ab>
          <ab n="28">May they be blotted out of the book of life and not be listed with the righteous.</ab>
          <ab n="29">I am in pain and distress; may your salvation, O God, protect me.</ab>
          <ab n="30">I will praise God's name in song and glorify him with thanksgiving.</ab>
          <ab n="31">This will please the LORD more than an ox, more than a bull with its horns and hoofs.</ab>
          <ab n="32">The poor will see and be glad- you who seek God, may your hearts live!</ab>
          <ab n="33">The LORD hears the needy and does not despise his captive people.</ab>
          <ab n="34">Let heaven and earth praise him, the seas and all that move in them,</ab>
          <ab n="35">for God will save Zion and rebuild the cities of Judah. Then people will settle there and possess it;</ab>
          <ab n="36">the children of his servants will inherit it, and those who love his name will dwell there.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="70">
          <ab n="1">Hasten, O God, to save me; O LORD, come quickly to help me.</ab>
          <ab n="2">May those who seek my life be put to shame and confusion; may all who desire my ruin be turned back in disgrace.</ab>
          <ab n="3">May those who say to me, "Aha! Aha!" turn back because of their shame.</ab>
          <ab n="4">But may all who seek you rejoice and be glad in you; may those who love your salvation always say, "Let God be exalted!"</ab>
          <ab n="5">Yet I am poor and needy; come quickly to me, O God. You are my help and my deliverer; O LORD, do not delay.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="71">
          <ab n="1">In you, O LORD, I have taken refuge; let me never be put to shame.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Rescue me and deliver me in your righteousness; turn your ear to me and save me.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Be my rock of refuge, to which I can always go; give the command to save me, for you are my rock and my fortress.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Deliver me, O my God, from the hand of the wicked, from the grasp of evil and cruel men.</ab>
          <ab n="5">For you have been my hope, O Sovereign LORD, my confidence since my youth.</ab>
          <ab n="6">From birth I have relied on you; you brought me forth from my mother's womb. I will ever praise you.</ab>
          <ab n="7">I have become like a portent to many, but you are my strong refuge.</ab>
          <ab n="8">My mouth is filled with your praise, declaring your splendor all day long.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Do not cast me away when I am old; do not forsake me when my strength is gone.</ab>
          <ab n="10">For my enemies speak against me; those who wait to kill me conspire together.</ab>
          <ab n="11">They say, "God has forsaken him; pursue him and seize him, for no one will rescue him."</ab>
          <ab n="12">Be not far from me, O God; come quickly, O my God, to help me.</ab>
          <ab n="13">May my accusers perish in shame; may those who want to harm me be covered with scorn and disgrace.</ab>
          <ab n="14">But as for me, I will always have hope; I will praise you more and more.</ab>
          <ab n="15">My mouth will tell of your righteousness, of your salvation all day long, though I know not its measure.</ab>
          <ab n="16">I will come and proclaim your mighty acts, O Sovereign LORD; I will proclaim your righteousness, yours alone.</ab>
          <ab n="17">Since my youth, O God, you have taught me, and to this day I declare your marvelous deeds.</ab>
          <ab n="18">Even when I am old and gray, do not forsake me, O God, till I declare your power to the next generation, your might to all who are to come.</ab>
          <ab n="19">Your righteousness reaches to the skies, O God, you who have done great things. Who, O God, is like you?</ab>
          <ab n="20">Though you have made me see troubles, many and bitter, you will restore my life again; from the depths of the earth you will again bring me up.</ab>
          <ab n="21">You will increase my honor and comfort me once again.</ab>
          <ab n="22">I will praise you with the harp for your faithfulness, O my God; I will sing praise to you with the lyre, O Holy One of Israel.</ab>
          <ab n="23">My lips will shout for joy when I sing praise to you- I, whom you have redeemed.</ab>
          <ab n="24">My tongue will tell of your righteous acts all day long, for those who wanted to harm me have been put to shame and confusion.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="72">
          <ab n="1">Endow the king with your justice, O God, the royal son with your righteousness.</ab>
          <ab n="2">He will judge your people in righteousness, your afflicted ones with justice.</ab>
          <ab n="3">The mountains will bring prosperity to the people, the hills the fruit of righteousness.</ab>
          <ab n="4">He will defend the afflicted among the people and save the children of the needy; he will crush the oppressor.</ab>
          <ab n="5">He will endure as long as the sun, as long as the moon, through all generations.</ab>
          <ab n="6">He will be like rain falling on a mown field, like showers watering the earth.</ab>
          <ab n="7">In his days the righteous will flourish; prosperity will abound till the moon is no more.</ab>
          <ab n="8">He will rule from sea to sea and from the River to the ends of the earth.</ab>
          <ab n="9">The desert tribes will bow before him and his enemies will lick the dust.</ab>
          <ab n="10">The kings of Tarshish and of distant shores will bring tribute to him; the kings of Sheba and Seba will present him gifts.</ab>
          <ab n="11">All kings will bow down to him and all nations will serve him.</ab>
          <ab n="12">For he will deliver the needy who cry out, the afflicted who have no one to help.</ab>
          <ab n="13">He will take pity on the weak and the needy and save the needy from death.</ab>
          <ab n="14">He will rescue them from oppression and violence, for precious is their blood in his sight.</ab>
          <ab n="15">Long may he live! May gold from Sheba be given him. May people ever pray for him and bless him all day long.</ab>
          <ab n="16">Let grain abound throughout the land; on the tops of the hills may it sway. Let its fruit flourish like Lebanon; let it thrive like the grass of the field.</ab>
          <ab n="17">May his name endure forever; may it continue as long as the sun. All nations will be blessed through him, and they will call him blessed.</ab>
          <ab n="18">Praise be to the LORD God, the God of Israel, who alone does marvelous deeds.</ab>
          <ab n="19">Praise be to his glorious name forever; may the whole earth be filled with his glory. Amen and Amen.</ab>
          <ab n="20">This concludes the prayers of David son of Jesse.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="73">
          <ab n="1">A psalm of Asaph. Surely God is good to Israel, to those who are pure in heart.</ab>
          <ab n="2">But as for me, my feet had almost slipped; I had nearly lost my foothold.</ab>
          <ab n="3">For I envied the arrogant when I saw the prosperity of the wicked.</ab>
          <ab n="4">They have no struggles; their bodies are healthy and strong.</ab>
          <ab n="5">They are free from the burdens common to man; they are not plagued by human ills.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Therefore pride is their necklace; they clothe themselves with violence.</ab>
          <ab n="7">From their callous hearts comes iniquity; the evil conceits of their minds know no limits.</ab>
          <ab n="8">They scoff, and speak with malice; in their arrogance they threaten oppression.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Their mouths lay claim to heaven, and their tongues take possession of the earth.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Therefore their people turn to them and drink up waters in abundance.</ab>
          <ab n="11">They say, "How can God know? Does the Most High have knowledge?"</ab>
          <ab n="12">This is what the wicked are like- always carefree, they increase in wealth.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Surely in vain have I kept my heart pure; in vain have I washed my hands in innocence.</ab>
          <ab n="14">All day long I have been plagued; I have been punished every morning.</ab>
          <ab n="15">If I had said, "I will speak thus," I would have betrayed your children.</ab>
          <ab n="16">When I tried to understand all this, it was oppressive to me</ab>
          <ab n="17">till I entered the sanctuary of God; then I understood their final destiny.</ab>
          <ab n="18">Surely you place them on slippery ground; you cast them down to ruin.</ab>
          <ab n="19">How suddenly are they destroyed, completely swept away by terrors!</ab>
          <ab n="20">As a dream when one awakes, so when you arise, O Lord, you will despise them as fantasies.</ab>
          <ab n="21">When my heart was grieved and my spirit embittered,</ab>
          <ab n="22">I was senseless and ignorant; I was a brute beast before you.</ab>
          <ab n="23">Yet I am always with you; you hold me by my right hand.</ab>
          <ab n="24">You guide me with your counsel, and afterward you will take me into glory.</ab>
          <ab n="25">Whom have I in heaven but you? And earth has nothing I desire besides you.</ab>
          <ab n="26">My flesh and my heart may fail, but God is the strength of my heart and my portion forever.</ab>
          <ab n="27">Those who are far from you will perish; you destroy all who are unfaithful to you.</ab>
          <ab n="28">But as for me, it is good to be near God. I have made the Sovereign LORD my refuge; I will tell of all your deeds.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="74">
          <ab n="1">Why have you rejected us forever, O God? Why does your anger smolder against the sheep of your pasture?</ab>
          <ab n="2">Remember the people you purchased of old, the tribe of your inheritance, whom you redeemed- Mount Zion, where you dwelt.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Turn your steps toward these everlasting ruins, all this destruction the enemy has brought on the sanctuary.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Your foes roared in the place where you met with us; they set up their standards as signs.</ab>
          <ab n="5">They behaved like men wielding axes to cut through a thicket of trees.</ab>
          <ab n="6">They smashed all the carved paneling with their axes and hatchets.</ab>
          <ab n="7">They burned your sanctuary to the ground; they defiled the dwelling place of your Name.</ab>
          <ab n="8">They said in their hearts, "We will crush them completely!" They burned every place where God was worshiped in the land.</ab>
          <ab n="9">We are given no miraculous signs; no prophets are left, and none of us knows how long this will be.</ab>
          <ab n="10">How long will the enemy mock you, O God? Will the foe revile your name forever?</ab>
          <ab n="11">Why do you hold back your hand, your right hand? Take it from the folds of your garment and destroy them!</ab>
          <ab n="12">But you, O God, are my king from of old; you bring salvation upon the earth.</ab>
          <ab n="13">It was you who split open the sea by your power; you broke the heads of the monster in the waters.</ab>
          <ab n="14">It was you who crushed the heads of Leviathan and gave him as food to the creatures of the desert.</ab>
          <ab n="15">It was you who opened up springs and streams; you dried up the ever flowing rivers.</ab>
          <ab n="16">The day is yours, and yours also the night; you established the sun and moon.</ab>
          <ab n="17">It was you who set all the boundaries of the earth; you made both summer and winter.</ab>
          <ab n="18">Remember how the enemy has mocked you, O LORD, how foolish people have reviled your name.</ab>
          <ab n="19">Do not hand over the life of your dove to wild beasts; do not forget the lives of your afflicted people forever.</ab>
          <ab n="20">Have regard for your covenant, because haunts of violence fill the dark places of the land.</ab>
          <ab n="21">Do not let the oppressed retreat in disgrace; may the poor and needy praise your name.</ab>
          <ab n="22">Rise up, O God, and defend your cause; remember how fools mock you all day long.</ab>
          <ab n="23">Do not ignore the clamor of your adversaries, the uproar of your enemies, which rises continually.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="75">
          <ab n="1">We give thanks to you, O God, we give thanks, for your Name is near; men tell of your wonderful deeds.</ab>
          <ab n="2">You say, "I choose the appointed time; it is I who judge uprightly.</ab>
          <ab n="3">When the earth and all its people quake, it is I who hold its pillars firm. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="4">To the arrogant I say, 'Boast no more,' and to the wicked, 'Do not lift up your horns.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Do not lift your horns against heaven; do not speak with outstretched neck.'"</ab>
          <ab n="6">No one from the east or the west or from the desert can exalt a man.</ab>
          <ab n="7">But it is God who judges: He brings one down, he exalts another.</ab>
          <ab n="8">In the hand of the LORD is a cup full of foaming wine mixed with spices; he pours it out, and all the wicked of the earth drink it down to its very dregs.</ab>
          <ab n="9">As for me, I will declare this forever; I will sing praise to the God of Jacob.</ab>
          <ab n="10">I will cut off the horns of all the wicked, but the horns of the righteous will be lifted up.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="76">
          <ab n="1">In Judah God is known; his name is great in Israel.</ab>
          <ab n="2">His tent is in Salem, his dwelling place in Zion.</ab>
          <ab n="3">There he broke the flashing arrows, the shields and the swords, the weapons of war. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="4">You are resplendent with light, more majestic than mountains rich with game.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Valiant men lie plundered, they sleep their last sleep; not one of the warriors can lift his hands.</ab>
          <ab n="6">At your rebuke, O God of Jacob, both horse and chariot lie still.</ab>
          <ab n="7">You alone are to be feared. Who can stand before you when you are angry?</ab>
          <ab n="8">From heaven you pronounced judgment, and the land feared and was quiet-</ab>
          <ab n="9">when you, O God, rose up to judge, to save all the afflicted of the land. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="10">Surely your wrath against men brings you praise, and the survivors of your wrath are restrained.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Make vows to the LORD your God and fulfill them; let all the neighboring lands bring gifts to the One to be feared.</ab>
          <ab n="12">He breaks the spirit of rulers; he is feared by the kings of the earth.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="77">
          <ab n="1">I cried out to God for help; I cried out to God to hear me.</ab>
          <ab n="2">When I was in distress, I sought the Lord; at night I stretched out untiring hands and my soul refused to be comforted.</ab>
          <ab n="3">I remembered you, O God, and I groaned; I mused, and my spirit grew faint. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="4">You kept my eyes from closing; I was too troubled to speak.</ab>
          <ab n="5">I thought about the former days, the years of long ago;</ab>
          <ab n="6">I remembered my songs in the night. My heart mused and my spirit inquired:</ab>
          <ab n="7">"Will the Lord reject forever? Will he never show his favor again?</ab>
          <ab n="8">Has his unfailing love vanished forever? Has his promise failed for all time?</ab>
          <ab n="9">Has God forgotten to be merciful? Has he in anger withheld his compassion?" Selah</ab>
          <ab n="10">Then I thought, "To this I will appeal: the years of the right hand of the Most High."</ab>
          <ab n="11">I will remember the deeds of the LORD; yes, I will remember your miracles of long ago.</ab>
          <ab n="12">I will meditate on all your works and consider all your mighty deeds.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Your ways, O God, are holy. What god is so great as our God?</ab>
          <ab n="14">You are the God who performs miracles; you display your power among the peoples.</ab>
          <ab n="15">With your mighty arm you redeemed your people, the descendants of Jacob and Joseph. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="16">The waters saw you, O God, the waters saw you and writhed; the very depths were convulsed.</ab>
          <ab n="17">The clouds poured down water, the skies resounded with thunder; your arrows flashed back and forth.</ab>
          <ab n="18">Your thunder was heard in the whirlwind, your lightning lit up the world; the earth trembled and quaked.</ab>
          <ab n="19">Your path led through the sea, your way through the mighty waters, though your footprints were not seen.</ab>
          <ab n="20">You led your people like a flock by the hand of Moses and Aaron.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="78">
          <ab n="1">O my people, hear my teaching; listen to the words of my mouth.</ab>
          <ab n="2">I will open my mouth in parables, I will utter hidden things, things from of old-</ab>
          <ab n="3">what we have heard and known, what our fathers have told us.</ab>
          <ab n="4">We will not hide them from their children; we will tell the next generation the praiseworthy deeds of the LORD, his power, and the wonders he has done.</ab>
          <ab n="5">He decreed statutes for Jacob and established the law in Israel, which he commanded our forefathers to teach their children,</ab>
          <ab n="6">so the next generation would know them, even the children yet to be born, and they in turn would tell their children.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Then they would put their trust in God and would not forget his deeds but would keep his commands.</ab>
          <ab n="8">They would not be like their forefathers- a stubborn and rebellious generation, whose hearts were not loyal to God, whose spirits were not faithful to him.</ab>
          <ab n="9">The men of Ephraim, though armed with bows, turned back on the day of battle;</ab>
          <ab n="10">they did not keep God's covenant and refused to live by his law.</ab>
          <ab n="11">They forgot what he had done, the wonders he had shown them.</ab>
          <ab n="12">He did miracles in the sight of their fathers in the land of Egypt, in the region of Zoan.</ab>
          <ab n="13">He divided the sea and led them through; he made the water stand firm like a wall.</ab>
          <ab n="14">He guided them with the cloud by day and with light from the fire all night.</ab>
          <ab n="15">He split the rocks in the desert and gave them water as abundant as the seas;</ab>
          <ab n="16">he brought streams out of a rocky crag and made water flow down like rivers.</ab>
          <ab n="17">But they continued to sin against him, rebelling in the desert against the Most High.</ab>
          <ab n="18">They willfully put God to the test by demanding the food they craved.</ab>
          <ab n="19">They spoke against God, saying, "Can God spread a table in the desert?</ab>
          <ab n="20">When he struck the rock, water gushed out, and streams flowed abundantly. But can he also give us food? Can he supply meat for his people?"</ab>
          <ab n="21">When the LORD heard them, he was very angry; his fire broke out against Jacob, and his wrath rose against Israel,</ab>
          <ab n="22">for they did not believe in God or trust in his deliverance.</ab>
          <ab n="23">Yet he gave a command to the skies above and opened the doors of the heavens;</ab>
          <ab n="24">he rained down manna for the people to eat, he gave them the grain of heaven.</ab>
          <ab n="25">Men ate the bread of angels; he sent them all the food they could eat.</ab>
          <ab n="26">He let loose the east wind from the heavens and led forth the south wind by his power.</ab>
          <ab n="27">He rained meat down on them like dust, flying birds like sand on the seashore.</ab>
          <ab n="28">He made them come down inside their camp, all around their tents.</ab>
          <ab n="29">They ate till they had more than enough, for he had given them what they craved.</ab>
          <ab n="30">But before they turned from the food they craved, even while it was still in their mouths,</ab>
          <ab n="31">God's anger rose against them; he put to death the sturdiest among them, cutting down the young men of Israel.</ab>
          <ab n="32">In spite of all this, they kept on sinning; in spite of his wonders, they did not believe.</ab>
          <ab n="33">So he ended their days in futility and their years in terror.</ab>
          <ab n="34">Whenever God slew them, they would seek him; they eagerly turned to him again.</ab>
          <ab n="35">They remembered that God was their Rock, that God Most High was their Redeemer.</ab>
          <ab n="36">But then they would flatter him with their mouths, lying to him with their tongues;</ab>
          <ab n="37">their hearts were not loyal to him, they were not faithful to his covenant.</ab>
          <ab n="38">Yet he was merciful; he forgave their iniquities and did not destroy them. Time after time he restrained his anger and did not stir up his full wrath.</ab>
          <ab n="39">He remembered that they were but flesh, a passing breeze that does not return.</ab>
          <ab n="40">How often they rebelled against him in the desert and grieved him in the wasteland!</ab>
          <ab n="41">Again and again they put God to the test; they vexed the Holy One of Israel.</ab>
          <ab n="42">They did not remember his power- the day he redeemed them from the oppressor,</ab>
          <ab n="43">the day he displayed his miraculous signs in Egypt, his wonders in the region of Zoan.</ab>
          <ab n="44">He turned their rivers to blood; they could not drink from their streams.</ab>
          <ab n="45">He sent swarms of flies that devoured them, and frogs that devastated them.</ab>
          <ab n="46">He gave their crops to the grasshopper, their produce to the locust.</ab>
          <ab n="47">He destroyed their vines with hail and their sycamore-figs with sleet.</ab>
          <ab n="48">He gave over their cattle to the hail, their livestock to bolts of lightning.</ab>
          <ab n="49">He unleashed against them his hot anger, his wrath, indignation and hostility- a band of destroying angels.</ab>
          <ab n="50">He prepared a path for his anger; he did not spare them from death but gave them over to the plague.</ab>
          <ab n="51">He struck down all the firstborn of Egypt, the firstfruits of manhood in the tents of Ham.</ab>
          <ab n="52">But he brought his people out like a flock; he led them like sheep through the desert.</ab>
          <ab n="53">He guided them safely, so they were unafraid; but the sea engulfed their enemies.</ab>
          <ab n="54">Thus he brought them to the border of his holy land, to the hill country his right hand had taken.</ab>
          <ab n="55">He drove out nations before them and allotted their lands to them as an inheritance; he settled the tribes of Israel in their homes.</ab>
          <ab n="56">But they put God to the test and rebelled against the Most High; they did not keep his statutes.</ab>
          <ab n="57">Like their fathers they were disloyal and faithless, as unreliable as a faulty bow.</ab>
          <ab n="58">They angered him with their high places; they aroused his jealousy with their idols.</ab>
          <ab n="59">When God heard them, he was very angry; he rejected Israel completely.</ab>
          <ab n="60">He abandoned the tabernacle of Shiloh, the tent he had set up among men.</ab>
          <ab n="61">He sent the ark of his might into captivity, his splendor into the hands of the enemy.</ab>
          <ab n="62">He gave his people over to the sword; he was very angry with his inheritance.</ab>
          <ab n="63">Fire consumed their young men, and their maidens had no wedding songs;</ab>
          <ab n="64">their priests were put to the sword, and their widows could not weep.</ab>
          <ab n="65">Then the Lord awoke as from sleep, as a man wakes from the stupor of wine.</ab>
          <ab n="66">He beat back his enemies; he put them to everlasting shame.</ab>
          <ab n="67">Then he rejected the tents of Joseph, he did not choose the tribe of Ephraim;</ab>
          <ab n="68">but he chose the tribe of Judah, Mount Zion, which he loved.</ab>
          <ab n="69">He built his sanctuary like the heights, like the earth that he established forever.</ab>
          <ab n="70">He chose David his servant and took him from the sheep pens;</ab>
          <ab n="71">from tending the sheep he brought him to be the shepherd of his people Jacob, of Israel his inheritance.</ab>
          <ab n="72">And David shepherded them with integrity of heart; with skillful hands he led them.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="79">
          <ab n="1">O God, the nations have invaded your inheritance; they have defiled your holy temple, they have reduced Jerusalem to rubble.</ab>
          <ab n="2">They have given the dead bodies of your servants as food to the birds of the air, the flesh of your saints to the beasts of the earth.</ab>
          <ab n="3">They have poured out blood like water all around Jerusalem, and there is no one to bury the dead.</ab>
          <ab n="4">We are objects of reproach to our neighbors, of scorn and derision to those around us.</ab>
          <ab n="5">How long, O LORD? Will you be angry forever? How long will your jealousy burn like fire?</ab>
          <ab n="6">Pour out your wrath on the nations that do not acknowledge you, on the kingdoms that do not call on your name;</ab>
          <ab n="7">for they have devoured Jacob and destroyed his homeland.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Do not hold against us the sins of the fathers; may your mercy come quickly to meet us, for we are in desperate need.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Help us, O God our Savior, for the glory of your name; deliver us and forgive our sins for your name's sake.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Why should the nations say, "Where is their God?" Before our eyes, make known among the nations that you avenge the outpoured blood of your servants.</ab>
          <ab n="11">May the groans of the prisoners come before you; by the strength of your arm preserve those condemned to die.</ab>
          <ab n="12">Pay back into the laps of our neighbors seven times the reproach they have hurled at you, O Lord.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Then we your people, the sheep of your pasture, will praise you forever; from generation to generation we will recount your praise.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="80">
          <ab n="1">Hear us, O Shepherd of Israel, you who lead Joseph like a flock; you who sit enthroned between the cherubim, shine forth</ab>
          <ab n="2">before Ephraim, Benjamin and Manasseh. Awaken your might; come and save us.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Restore us, O God; make your face shine upon us, that we may be saved.</ab>
          <ab n="4">O LORD God Almighty, how long will your anger smolder against the prayers of your people?</ab>
          <ab n="5">You have fed them with the bread of tears; you have made them drink tears by the bowlful.</ab>
          <ab n="6">You have made us a source of contention to our neighbors, and our enemies mock us.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Restore us, O God Almighty; make your face shine upon us, that we may be saved.</ab>
          <ab n="8">You brought a vine out of Egypt; you drove out the nations and planted it.</ab>
          <ab n="9">You cleared the ground for it, and it took root and filled the land.</ab>
          <ab n="10">The mountains were covered with its shade, the mighty cedars with its branches.</ab>
          <ab n="11">It sent out its boughs to the Sea, its shoots as far as the River.</ab>
          <ab n="12">Why have you broken down its walls so that all who pass by pick its grapes?</ab>
          <ab n="13">Boars from the forest ravage it and the creatures of the field feed on it.</ab>
          <ab n="14">Return to us, O God Almighty! Look down from heaven and see! Watch over this vine,</ab>
          <ab n="15">the root your right hand has planted, the son you have raised up for yourself.</ab>
          <ab n="16">Your vine is cut down, it is burned with fire; at your rebuke your people perish.</ab>
          <ab n="17">Let your hand rest on the man at your right hand, the son of man you have raised up for yourself.</ab>
          <ab n="18">Then we will not turn away from you; revive us, and we will call on your name.</ab>
          <ab n="19">Restore us, O LORD God Almighty; make your face shine upon us, that we may be saved.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="81">
          <ab n="1">Sing for joy to God our strength; shout aloud to the God of Jacob!</ab>
          <ab n="2">Begin the music, strike the tambourine, play the melodious harp and lyre.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Sound the ram's horn at the New Moon, and when the moon is full, on the day of our Feast;</ab>
          <ab n="4">this is a decree for Israel, an ordinance of the God of Jacob.</ab>
          <ab n="5">He established it as a statute for Joseph when he went out against Egypt, where we heard a language we did not understand.</ab>
          <ab n="6">He says, "I removed the burden from their shoulders; their hands were set free from the basket.</ab>
          <ab n="7">In your distress you called and I rescued you, I answered you out of a thundercloud; I tested you at the waters of Meribah. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="8">"Hear, O my people, and I will warn you- if you would but listen to me, O Israel!</ab>
          <ab n="9">You shall have no foreign god among you; you shall not bow down to an alien god.</ab>
          <ab n="10">I am the LORD your God, who brought you up out of Egypt. Open wide your mouth and I will fill it.</ab>
          <ab n="11">"But my people would not listen to me; Israel would not submit to me.</ab>
          <ab n="12">So I gave them over to their stubborn hearts to follow their own devices.</ab>
          <ab n="13">"If my people would but listen to me, if Israel would follow my ways,</ab>
          <ab n="14">how quickly would I subdue their enemies and turn my hand against their foes!</ab>
          <ab n="15">Those who hate the LORD would cringe before him, and their punishment would last forever.</ab>
          <ab n="16">But you would be fed with the finest of wheat; with honey from the rock I would satisfy you."</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="82">
          <ab n="1">God presides in the great assembly; he gives judgment among the "gods":</ab>
          <ab n="2">"How long will you defend the unjust and show partiality to the wicked? Selah</ab>
          <ab n="3">Defend the cause of the weak and fatherless; maintain the rights of the poor and oppressed.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Rescue the weak and needy; deliver them from the hand of the wicked.</ab>
          <ab n="5">"They know nothing, they understand nothing. They walk about in darkness; all the foundations of the earth are shaken.</ab>
          <ab n="6">"I said, 'You are "gods"; you are all sons of the Most High.'</ab>
          <ab n="7">But you will die like mere men; you will fall like every other ruler."</ab>
          <ab n="8">Rise up, O God, judge the earth, for all the nations are your inheritance.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="83">
          <ab n="1">O God, do not keep silent; be not quiet, O God, be not still.</ab>
          <ab n="2">See how your enemies are astir, how your foes rear their heads.</ab>
          <ab n="3">With cunning they conspire against your people; they plot against those you cherish.</ab>
          <ab n="4">"Come," they say, "let us destroy them as a nation, that the name of Israel be remembered no more."</ab>
          <ab n="5">With one mind they plot together; they form an alliance against you-</ab>
          <ab n="6">the tents of Edom and the Ishmaelites, of Moab and the Hagrites,</ab>
          <ab n="7">Gebal, Ammon and Amalek, Philistia, with the people of Tyre.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Even Assyria has joined them to lend strength to the descendants of Lot. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="9">Do to them as you did to Midian, as you did to Sisera and Jabin at the river Kishon,</ab>
          <ab n="10">who perished at Endor and became like refuse on the ground.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Make their nobles like Oreb and Zeeb, all their princes like Zebah and Zalmunna,</ab>
          <ab n="12">who said, "Let us take possession of the pasturelands of God."</ab>
          <ab n="13">Make them like tumbleweed, O my God, like chaff before the wind.</ab>
          <ab n="14">As fire consumes the forest or a flame sets the mountains ablaze,</ab>
          <ab n="15">so pursue them with your tempest and terrify them with your storm.</ab>
          <ab n="16">Cover their faces with shame so that men will seek your name, O LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="17">May they ever be ashamed and dismayed; may they perish in disgrace.</ab>
          <ab n="18">Let them know that you, whose name is the LORD - that you alone are the Most High over all the earth.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="84">
          <ab n="1">How lovely is your dwelling place, O LORD Almighty!</ab>
          <ab n="2">My soul yearns, even faints, for the courts of the LORD; my heart and my flesh cry out for the living God.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Even the sparrow has found a home, and the swallow a nest for herself, where she may have her young- a place near your altar, O LORD Almighty, my King and my God.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Blessed are those who dwell in your house; they are ever praising you. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="5">Blessed are those whose strength is in you, who have set their hearts on pilgrimage.</ab>
          <ab n="6">As they pass through the Valley of Baca, they make it a place of springs; the autumn rains also cover it with pools.</ab>
          <ab n="7">They go from strength to strength, till each appears before God in Zion.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Hear my prayer, O LORD God Almighty; listen to me, O God of Jacob. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="9">Look upon our shield, O God; look with favor on your anointed one.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Better is one day in your courts than a thousand elsewhere; I would rather be a doorkeeper in the house of my God than dwell in the tents of the wicked.</ab>
          <ab n="11">For the LORD God is a sun and shield; the LORD bestows favor and honor; no good thing does he withhold from those whose walk is blameless.</ab>
          <ab n="12">O LORD Almighty, blessed is the man who trusts in you.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="85">
          <ab n="1">You showed favor to your land, O LORD; you restored the fortunes of Jacob.</ab>
          <ab n="2">You forgave the iniquity of your people and covered all their sins. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="3">You set aside all your wrath and turned from your fierce anger.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Restore us again, O God our Savior, and put away your displeasure toward us.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Will you be angry with us forever? Will you prolong your anger through all generations?</ab>
          <ab n="6">Will you not revive us again, that your people may rejoice in you?</ab>
          <ab n="7">Show us your unfailing love, O LORD, and grant us your salvation.</ab>
          <ab n="8">I will listen to what God the LORD will say; he promises peace to his people, his saints- but let them not return to folly.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Surely his salvation is near those who fear him, that his glory may dwell in our land.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Love and faithfulness meet together; righteousness and peace kiss each other.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Faithfulness springs forth from the earth, and righteousness looks down from heaven.</ab>
          <ab n="12">The LORD will indeed give what is good, and our land will yield its harvest.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Righteousness goes before him and prepares the way for his steps.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="86">
          <ab n="1">Hear, O LORD, and answer me, for I am poor and needy.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Guard my life, for I am devoted to you. You are my God; save your servant who trusts in you.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Have mercy on me, O Lord, for I call to you all day long.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Bring joy to your servant, for to you, O Lord, I lift up my soul.</ab>
          <ab n="5">You are forgiving and good, O Lord, abounding in love to all who call to you.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Hear my prayer, O LORD; listen to my cry for mercy.</ab>
          <ab n="7">In the day of my trouble I will call to you, for you will answer me.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Among the gods there is none like you, O Lord; no deeds can compare with yours.</ab>
          <ab n="9">All the nations you have made will come and worship before you, O Lord; they will bring glory to your name.</ab>
          <ab n="10">For you are great and do marvelous deeds; you alone are God.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Teach me your way, O LORD, and I will walk in your truth; give me an undivided heart, that I may fear your name.</ab>
          <ab n="12">I will praise you, O Lord my God, with all my heart; I will glorify your name forever.</ab>
          <ab n="13">For great is your love toward me; you have delivered me from the depths of the grave.</ab>
          <ab n="14">The arrogant are attacking me, O God; a band of ruthless men seeks my life- men without regard for you.</ab>
          <ab n="15">But you, O Lord, are a compassionate and gracious God, slow to anger, abounding in love and faithfulness.</ab>
          <ab n="16">Turn to me and have mercy on me; grant your strength to your servant and save the son of your maidservant.</ab>
          <ab n="17">Give me a sign of your goodness, that my enemies may see it and be put to shame, for you, O LORD, have helped me and comforted me.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="87">
          <ab n="1">He has set his foundation on the holy mountain;</ab>
          <ab n="2">the LORD loves the gates of Zion more than all the dwellings of Jacob.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Glorious things are said of you, O city of God: Selah</ab>
          <ab n="4">"I will record Rahab and Babylon among those who acknowledge me- Philistia too, and Tyre, along with Cush - and will say, 'This one was born in Zion.'"</ab>
          <ab n="5">Indeed, of Zion it will be said, "This one and that one were born in her, and the Most High himself will establish her."</ab>
          <ab n="6">The LORD will write in the register of the peoples: "This one was born in Zion." Selah</ab>
          <ab n="7">As they make music they will sing, "All my fountains are in you."</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="88">
          <ab n="1">O LORD, the God who saves me, day and night I cry out before you.</ab>
          <ab n="2">May my prayer come before you; turn your ear to my cry.</ab>
          <ab n="3">For my soul is full of trouble and my life draws near the grave.</ab>
          <ab n="4">I am counted among those who go down to the pit; I am like a man without strength.</ab>
          <ab n="5">I am set apart with the dead, like the slain who lie in the grave, whom you remember no more, who are cut off from your care.</ab>
          <ab n="6">You have put me in the lowest pit, in the darkest depths.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Your wrath lies heavily upon me; you have overwhelmed me with all your waves. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="8">You have taken from me my closest friends and have made me repulsive to them. I am confined and cannot escape;</ab>
          <ab n="9">my eyes are dim with grief. I call to you, O LORD, every day; I spread out my hands to you.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Do you show your wonders to the dead? Do those who are dead rise up and praise you? Selah</ab>
          <ab n="11">Is your love declared in the grave, your faithfulness in Destruction?</ab>
          <ab n="12">Are your wonders known in the place of darkness, or your righteous deeds in the land of oblivion?</ab>
          <ab n="13">But I cry to you for help, O LORD; in the morning my prayer comes before you.</ab>
          <ab n="14">Why, O LORD, do you reject me and hide your face from me?</ab>
          <ab n="15">From my youth I have been afflicted and close to death; I have suffered your terrors and am in despair.</ab>
          <ab n="16">Your wrath has swept over me; your terrors have destroyed me.</ab>
          <ab n="17">All day long they surround me like a flood; they have completely engulfed me.</ab>
          <ab n="18">You have taken my companions and loved ones from me; the darkness is my closest friend.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="89">
          <ab n="1">I will sing of the LORD's great love forever; with my mouth I will make your faithfulness known through all generations.</ab>
          <ab n="2">I will declare that your love stands firm forever, that you established your faithfulness in heaven itself.</ab>
          <ab n="3">You said, "I have made a covenant with my chosen one, I have sworn to David my servant,</ab>
          <ab n="4">'I will establish your line forever and make your throne firm through all generations.'" Selah</ab>
          <ab n="5">The heavens praise your wonders, O LORD, your faithfulness too, in the assembly of the holy ones.</ab>
          <ab n="6">For who in the skies above can compare with the LORD? Who is like the LORD among the heavenly beings?</ab>
          <ab n="7">In the council of the holy ones God is greatly feared; he is more awesome than all who surround him.</ab>
          <ab n="8">O LORD God Almighty, who is like you? You are mighty, O LORD, and your faithfulness surrounds you.</ab>
          <ab n="9">You rule over the surging sea; when its waves mount up, you still them.</ab>
          <ab n="10">You crushed Rahab like one of the slain; with your strong arm you scattered your enemies.</ab>
          <ab n="11">The heavens are yours, and yours also the earth; you founded the world and all that is in it.</ab>
          <ab n="12">You created the north and the south; Tabor and Hermon sing for joy at your name.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Your arm is endued with power; your hand is strong, your right hand exalted.</ab>
          <ab n="14">Righteousness and justice are the foundation of your throne; love and faithfulness go before you.</ab>
          <ab n="15">Blessed are those who have learned to acclaim you, who walk in the light of your presence, O LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="16">They rejoice in your name all day long; they exult in your righteousness.</ab>
          <ab n="17">For you are their glory and strength, and by your favor you exalt our horn.</ab>
          <ab n="18">Indeed, our shield belongs to the LORD, our king to the Holy One of Israel.</ab>
          <ab n="19">Once you spoke in a vision, to your faithful people you said: "I have bestowed strength on a warrior; I have exalted a young man from among the people.</ab>
          <ab n="20">I have found David my servant; with my sacred oil I have anointed him.</ab>
          <ab n="21">My hand will sustain him; surely my arm will strengthen him.</ab>
          <ab n="22">No enemy will subject him to tribute; no wicked man will oppress him.</ab>
          <ab n="23">I will crush his foes before him and strike down his adversaries.</ab>
          <ab n="24">My faithful love will be with him, and through my name his horn will be exalted.</ab>
          <ab n="25">I will set his hand over the sea, his right hand over the rivers.</ab>
          <ab n="26">He will call out to me, 'You are my Father, my God, the Rock my Savior.'</ab>
          <ab n="27">I will also appoint him my firstborn, the most exalted of the kings of the earth.</ab>
          <ab n="28">I will maintain my love to him forever, and my covenant with him will never fail.</ab>
          <ab n="29">I will establish his line forever, his throne as long as the heavens endure.</ab>
          <ab n="30">"If his sons forsake my law and do not follow my statutes,</ab>
          <ab n="31">if they violate my decrees and fail to keep my commands,</ab>
          <ab n="32">I will punish their sin with the rod, their iniquity with flogging;</ab>
          <ab n="33">but I will not take my love from him, nor will I ever betray my faithfulness.</ab>
          <ab n="34">I will not violate my covenant or alter what my lips have uttered.</ab>
          <ab n="35">Once for all, I have sworn by my holiness- and I will not lie to David-</ab>
          <ab n="36">that his line will continue forever and his throne endure before me like the sun;</ab>
          <ab n="37">it will be established forever like the moon, the faithful witness in the sky." Selah</ab>
          <ab n="38">But you have rejected, you have spurned, you have been very angry with your anointed one.</ab>
          <ab n="39">You have renounced the covenant with your servant and have defiled his crown in the dust.</ab>
          <ab n="40">You have broken through all his walls and reduced his strongholds to ruins.</ab>
          <ab n="41">All who pass by have plundered him; he has become the scorn of his neighbors.</ab>
          <ab n="42">You have exalted the right hand of his foes; you have made all his enemies rejoice.</ab>
          <ab n="43">You have turned back the edge of his sword and have not supported him in battle.</ab>
          <ab n="44">You have put an end to his splendor and cast his throne to the ground.</ab>
          <ab n="45">You have cut short the days of his youth; you have covered him with a mantle of shame. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="46">How long, O LORD? Will you hide yourself forever? How long will your wrath burn like fire?</ab>
          <ab n="47">Remember how fleeting is my life. For what futility you have created all men!</ab>
          <ab n="48">What man can live and not see death, or save himself from the power of the grave? Selah</ab>
          <ab n="49">O Lord, where is your former great love, which in your faithfulness you swore to David?</ab>
          <ab n="50">Remember, Lord, how your servant has been mocked, how I bear in my heart the taunts of all the nations,</ab>
          <ab n="51">the taunts with which your enemies have mocked, O LORD, with which they have mocked every step of your anointed one.</ab>
          <ab n="52">Praise be to the LORD forever! Amen and Amen. BOOK IV Psalms 90-106</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="90">
          <ab n="1">Lord, you have been our dwelling place throughout all generations.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Before the mountains were born or you brought forth the earth and the world, from everlasting to everlasting you are God.</ab>
          <ab n="3">You turn men back to dust, saying, "Return to dust, O sons of men."</ab>
          <ab n="4">For a thousand years in your sight are like a day that has just gone by, or like a watch in the night.</ab>
          <ab n="5">You sweep men away in the sleep of death; they are like the new grass of the morning-</ab>
          <ab n="6">though in the morning it springs up new, by evening it is dry and withered.</ab>
          <ab n="7">We are consumed by your anger and terrified by your indignation.</ab>
          <ab n="8">You have set our iniquities before you, our secret sins in the light of your presence.</ab>
          <ab n="9">All our days pass away under your wrath; we finish our years with a moan.</ab>
          <ab n="10">The length of our days is seventy years- or eighty, if we have the strength; yet their span is but trouble and sorrow, for they quickly pass, and we fly away.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Who knows the power of your anger? For your wrath is as great as the fear that is due you.</ab>
          <ab n="12">Teach us to number our days aright, that we may gain a heart of wisdom.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Relent, O LORD! How long will it be? Have compassion on your servants.</ab>
          <ab n="14">Satisfy us in the morning with your unfailing love, that we may sing for joy and be glad all our days.</ab>
          <ab n="15">Make us glad for as many days as you have afflicted us, for as many years as we have seen trouble.</ab>
          <ab n="16">May your deeds be shown to your servants, your splendor to their children.</ab>
          <ab n="17">May the favor of the Lord our God rest upon us; establish the work of our hands for us- yes, establish the work of our hands.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="91">
          <ab n="1">He who dwells in the shelter of the Most High will rest in the shadow of the Almighty.</ab>
          <ab n="2">I will say of the LORD, "He is my refuge and my fortress, my God, in whom I trust."</ab>
          <ab n="3">Surely he will save you from the fowler's snare and from the deadly pestilence.</ab>
          <ab n="4">He will cover you with his feathers, and under his wings you will find refuge; his faithfulness will be your shield and rampart.</ab>
          <ab n="5">You will not fear the terror of night, nor the arrow that flies by day,</ab>
          <ab n="6">nor the pestilence that stalks in the darkness, nor the plague that destroys at midday.</ab>
          <ab n="7">A thousand may fall at your side, ten thousand at your right hand, but it will not come near you.</ab>
          <ab n="8">You will only observe with your eyes and see the punishment of the wicked.</ab>
          <ab n="9">If you make the Most High your dwelling- even the LORD, who is my refuge-</ab>
          <ab n="10">then no harm will befall you, no disaster will come near your tent.</ab>
          <ab n="11">For he will command his angels concerning you to guard you in all your ways;</ab>
          <ab n="12">they will lift you up in their hands, so that you will not strike your foot against a stone.</ab>
          <ab n="13">You will tread upon the lion and the cobra; you will trample the great lion and the serpent.</ab>
          <ab n="14">"Because he loves me," says the LORD, "I will rescue him; I will protect him, for he acknowledges my name.</ab>
          <ab n="15">He will call upon me, and I will answer him; I will be with him in trouble, I will deliver him and honor him.</ab>
          <ab n="16">With long life will I satisfy him and show him my salvation."</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="92">
          <ab n="1">It is good to praise the LORD and make music to your name, O Most High,</ab>
          <ab n="2">to proclaim your love in the morning and your faithfulness at night,</ab>
          <ab n="3">to the music of the ten-stringed lyre and the melody of the harp.</ab>
          <ab n="4">For you make me glad by your deeds, O LORD; I sing for joy at the works of your hands.</ab>
          <ab n="5">How great are your works, O LORD, how profound your thoughts!</ab>
          <ab n="6">The senseless man does not know, fools do not understand,</ab>
          <ab n="7">that though the wicked spring up like grass and all evildoers flourish, they will be forever destroyed.</ab>
          <ab n="8">But you, O LORD, are exalted forever.</ab>
          <ab n="9">For surely your enemies, O LORD, surely your enemies will perish; all evildoers will be scattered.</ab>
          <ab n="10">You have exalted my horn like that of a wild ox; fine oils have been poured upon me.</ab>
          <ab n="11">My eyes have seen the defeat of my adversaries; my ears have heard the rout of my wicked foes.</ab>
          <ab n="12">The righteous will flourish like a palm tree, they will grow like a cedar of Lebanon;</ab>
          <ab n="13">planted in the house of the LORD, they will flourish in the courts of our God.</ab>
          <ab n="14">They will still bear fruit in old age, they will stay fresh and green,</ab>
          <ab n="15">proclaiming, "The LORD is upright; he is my Rock, and there is no wickedness in him."</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="93">
          <ab n="1">The LORD reigns, he is robed in majesty; the LORD is robed in majesty and is armed with strength. The world is firmly established; it cannot be moved.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Your throne was established long ago; you are from all eternity.</ab>
          <ab n="3">The seas have lifted up, O LORD, the seas have lifted up their voice; the seas have lifted up their pounding waves.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Mightier than the thunder of the great waters, mightier than the breakers of the sea- the LORD on high is mighty.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Your statutes stand firm; holiness adorns your house for endless days, O LORD.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="94">
          <ab n="1">O LORD, the God who avenges, O God who avenges, shine forth.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Rise up, O Judge of the earth; pay back to the proud what they deserve.</ab>
          <ab n="3">How long will the wicked, O LORD, how long will the wicked be jubilant?</ab>
          <ab n="4">They pour out arrogant words; all the evildoers are full of boasting.</ab>
          <ab n="5">They crush your people, O LORD; they oppress your inheritance.</ab>
          <ab n="6">They slay the widow and the alien; they murder the fatherless.</ab>
          <ab n="7">They say, "The LORD does not see; the God of Jacob pays no heed."</ab>
          <ab n="8">Take heed, you senseless ones among the people; you fools, when will you become wise?</ab>
          <ab n="9">Does he who implanted the ear not hear? Does he who formed the eye not see?</ab>
          <ab n="10">Does he who disciplines nations not punish? Does he who teaches man lack knowledge?</ab>
          <ab n="11">The LORD knows the thoughts of man; he knows that they are futile.</ab>
          <ab n="12">Blessed is the man you discipline, O LORD, the man you teach from your law;</ab>
          <ab n="13">you grant him relief from days of trouble, till a pit is dug for the wicked.</ab>
          <ab n="14">For the LORD will not reject his people; he will never forsake his inheritance.</ab>
          <ab n="15">Judgment will again be founded on righteousness, and all the upright in heart will follow it.</ab>
          <ab n="16">Who will rise up for me against the wicked? Who will take a stand for me against evildoers?</ab>
          <ab n="17">Unless the LORD had given me help, I would soon have dwelt in the silence of death.</ab>
          <ab n="18">When I said, "My foot is slipping," your love, O LORD, supported me.</ab>
          <ab n="19">When anxiety was great within me, your consolation brought joy to my soul.</ab>
          <ab n="20">Can a corrupt throne be allied with you- one that brings on misery by its decrees?</ab>
          <ab n="21">They band together against the righteous and condemn the innocent to death.</ab>
          <ab n="22">But the LORD has become my fortress, and my God the rock in whom I take refuge.</ab>
          <ab n="23">He will repay them for their sins and destroy them for their wickedness; the LORD our God will destroy them.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="95">
          <ab n="1">Come, let us sing for joy to the LORD; let us shout aloud to the Rock of our salvation.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Let us come before him with thanksgiving and extol him with music and song.</ab>
          <ab n="3">For the LORD is the great God, the great King above all gods.</ab>
          <ab n="4">In his hand are the depths of the earth, and the mountain peaks belong to him.</ab>
          <ab n="5">The sea is his, for he made it, and his hands formed the dry land.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Come, let us bow down in worship, let us kneel before the LORD our Maker;</ab>
          <ab n="7">for he is our God and we are the people of his pasture, the flock under his care. Today, if you hear his voice,</ab>
          <ab n="8">do not harden your hearts as you did at Meribah, as you did that day at Massah in the desert,</ab>
          <ab n="9">where your fathers tested and tried me, though they had seen what I did.</ab>
          <ab n="10">For forty years I was angry with that generation; I said, "They are a people whose hearts go astray, and they have not known my ways."</ab>
          <ab n="11">So I declared on oath in my anger, "They shall never enter my rest."</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="96">
          <ab n="1">Sing to the LORD a new song; sing to the LORD, all the earth.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Sing to the LORD, praise his name; proclaim his salvation day after day.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Declare his glory among the nations, his marvelous deeds among all peoples.</ab>
          <ab n="4">For great is the LORD and most worthy of praise; he is to be feared above all gods.</ab>
          <ab n="5">For all the gods of the nations are idols, but the LORD made the heavens.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Splendor and majesty are before him; strength and glory are in his sanctuary.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Ascribe to the LORD, O families of nations, ascribe to the LORD glory and strength.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Ascribe to the LORD the glory due his name; bring an offering and come into his courts.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Worship the LORD in the splendor of his holiness; tremble before him, all the earth.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Say among the nations, "The LORD reigns." The world is firmly established, it cannot be moved; he will judge the peoples with equity.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Let the heavens rejoice, let the earth be glad; let the sea resound, and all that is in it;</ab>
          <ab n="12">let the fields be jubilant, and everything in them. Then all the trees of the forest will sing for joy;</ab>
          <ab n="13">they will sing before the LORD, for he comes, he comes to judge the earth. He will judge the world in righteousness and the peoples in his truth.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="97">
          <ab n="1">The LORD reigns, let the earth be glad; let the distant shores rejoice.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Clouds and thick darkness surround him; righteousness and justice are the foundation of his throne.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Fire goes before him and consumes his foes on every side.</ab>
          <ab n="4">His lightning lights up the world; the earth sees and trembles.</ab>
          <ab n="5">The mountains melt like wax before the LORD, before the Lord of all the earth.</ab>
          <ab n="6">The heavens proclaim his righteousness, and all the peoples see his glory.</ab>
          <ab n="7">All who worship images are put to shame, those who boast in idols- worship him, all you gods!</ab>
          <ab n="8">Zion hears and rejoices and the villages of Judah are glad because of your judgments, O LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="9">For you, O LORD, are the Most High over all the earth; you are exalted far above all gods.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Let those who love the LORD hate evil, for he guards the lives of his faithful ones and delivers them from the hand of the wicked.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Light is shed upon the righteous and joy on the upright in heart.</ab>
          <ab n="12">Rejoice in the LORD, you who are righteous, and praise his holy name.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="98">
          <ab n="1">Sing to the LORD a new song, for he has done marvelous things; his right hand and his holy arm have worked salvation for him.</ab>
          <ab n="2">The LORD has made his salvation known and revealed his righteousness to the nations.</ab>
          <ab n="3">He has remembered his love and his faithfulness to the house of Israel; all the ends of the earth have seen the salvation of our God.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Shout for joy to the LORD, all the earth, burst into jubilant song with music;</ab>
          <ab n="5">make music to the LORD with the harp, with the harp and the sound of singing,</ab>
          <ab n="6">with trumpets and the blast of the ram's horn- shout for joy before the LORD, the King.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Let the sea resound, and everything in it, the world, and all who live in it.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Let the rivers clap their hands, Let the mountains sing together for joy;</ab>
          <ab n="9">let them sing before the LORD, for he comes to judge the earth. He will judge the world in righteousness and the peoples with equity.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="99">
          <ab n="1">The LORD reigns, let the nations tremble; he sits enthroned between the cherubim, let the earth shake.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Great is the LORD in Zion; he is exalted over all the nations.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Let them praise your great and awesome name- he is holy.</ab>
          <ab n="4">The King is mighty, he loves justice- you have established equity; in Jacob you have done what is just and right.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Exalt the LORD our God and worship at his footstool; he is holy.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Moses and Aaron were among his priests, Samuel was among those who called on his name; they called on the LORD and he answered them.</ab>
          <ab n="7">He spoke to them from the pillar of cloud; they kept his statutes and the decrees he gave them.</ab>
          <ab n="8">O LORD our God, you answered them; you were to Israel a forgiving God, though you punished their misdeeds.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Exalt the LORD our God and worship at his holy mountain, for the LORD our God is holy.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="100">
          <ab n="1">Shout for joy to the LORD, all the earth.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Worship the LORD with gladness; come before him with joyful songs.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Know that the LORD is God. It is he who made us, and we are his; we are his people, the sheep of his pasture.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Enter his gates with thanksgiving and his courts with praise; give thanks to him and praise his name.</ab>
          <ab n="5">For the LORD is good and his love endures forever; his faithfulness continues through all generations.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="101">
          <ab n="1">I will sing of your love and justice; to you, O LORD, I will sing praise.</ab>
          <ab n="2">I will be careful to lead a blameless life- when will you come to me? I will walk in my house with blameless heart.</ab>
          <ab n="3">I will set before my eyes no vile thing. The deeds of faithless men I hate; they will not cling to me.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Men of perverse heart shall be far from me; I will have nothing to do with evil.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Whoever slanders his neighbor in secret, him will I put to silence; whoever has haughty eyes and a proud heart, him will I not endure.</ab>
          <ab n="6">My eyes will be on the faithful in the land, that they may dwell with me; he whose walk is blameless will minister to me.</ab>
          <ab n="7">No one who practices deceit will dwell in my house; no one who speaks falsely will stand in my presence.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Every morning I will put to silence all the wicked in the land; I will cut off every evildoer from the city of the LORD.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="102">
          <ab n="1">Hear my prayer, O LORD; let my cry for help come to you.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Do not hide your face from me when I am in distress. Turn your ear to me; when I call, answer me quickly.</ab>
          <ab n="3">For my days vanish like smoke; my bones burn like glowing embers.</ab>
          <ab n="4">My heart is blighted and withered like grass; I forget to eat my food.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Because of my loud groaning I am reduced to skin and bones.</ab>
          <ab n="6">I am like a desert owl, like an owl among the ruins.</ab>
          <ab n="7">I lie awake; I have become like a bird alone on a roof.</ab>
          <ab n="8">All day long my enemies taunt me; those who rail against me use my name as a curse.</ab>
          <ab n="9">For I eat ashes as my food and mingle my drink with tears</ab>
          <ab n="10">because of your great wrath, for you have taken me up and thrown me aside.</ab>
          <ab n="11">My days are like the evening shadow; I wither away like grass.</ab>
          <ab n="12">But you, O LORD, sit enthroned forever; your renown endures through all generations.</ab>
          <ab n="13">You will arise and have compassion on Zion, for it is time to show favor to her; the appointed time has come.</ab>
          <ab n="14">For her stones are dear to your servants; her very dust moves them to pity.</ab>
          <ab n="15">The nations will fear the name of the LORD, all the kings of the earth will revere your glory.</ab>
          <ab n="16">For the LORD will rebuild Zion and appear in his glory.</ab>
          <ab n="17">He will respond to the prayer of the destitute; he will not despise their plea.</ab>
          <ab n="18">Let this be written for a future generation, that a people not yet created may praise the LORD:</ab>
          <ab n="19">"The LORD looked down from his sanctuary on high, from heaven he viewed the earth,</ab>
          <ab n="20">to hear the groans of the prisoners and release those condemned to death."</ab>
          <ab n="21">So the name of the LORD will be declared in Zion and his praise in Jerusalem</ab>
          <ab n="22">when the peoples and the kingdoms assemble to worship the LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="23">In the course of my life he broke my strength; he cut short my days.</ab>
          <ab n="24">So I said: "Do not take me away, O my God, in the midst of my days; your years go on through all generations.</ab>
          <ab n="25">In the beginning you laid the foundations of the earth, and the heavens are the work of your hands.</ab>
          <ab n="26">They will perish, but you remain; they will all wear out like a garment. Like clothing you will change them and they will be discarded.</ab>
          <ab n="27">But you remain the same, and your years will never end.</ab>
          <ab n="28">The children of your servants will live in your presence; their descendants will be established before you."</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="103">
          <ab n="1">Praise the LORD, O my soul; all my inmost being, praise his holy name.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Praise the LORD, O my soul, and forget not all his benefits-</ab>
          <ab n="3">who forgives all your sins and heals all your diseases,</ab>
          <ab n="4">who redeems your life from the pit and crowns you with love and compassion,</ab>
          <ab n="5">who satisfies your desires with good things so that your youth is renewed like the eagle's.</ab>
          <ab n="6">The LORD works righteousness and justice for all the oppressed.</ab>
          <ab n="7">He made known his ways to Moses, his deeds to the people of Israel:</ab>
          <ab n="8">The LORD is compassionate and gracious, slow to anger, abounding in love.</ab>
          <ab n="9">He will not always accuse, nor will he harbor his anger forever;</ab>
          <ab n="10">he does not treat us as our sins deserve or repay us according to our iniquities.</ab>
          <ab n="11">For as high as the heavens are above the earth, so great is his love for those who fear him;</ab>
          <ab n="12">as far as the east is from the west, so far has he removed our transgressions from us.</ab>
          <ab n="13">As a father has compassion on his children, so the LORD has compassion on those who fear him;</ab>
          <ab n="14">for he knows how we are formed, he remembers that we are dust.</ab>
          <ab n="15">As for man, his days are like grass, he flourishes like a flower of the field;</ab>
          <ab n="16">the wind blows over it and it is gone, and its place remembers it no more.</ab>
          <ab n="17">But from everlasting to everlasting the LORD's love is with those who fear him, and his righteousness with their children's children-</ab>
          <ab n="18">with those who keep his covenant and remember to obey his precepts.</ab>
          <ab n="19">The LORD has established his throne in heaven, and his kingdom rules over all.</ab>
          <ab n="20">Praise the LORD, you his angels, you mighty ones who do his bidding, who obey his word.</ab>
          <ab n="21">Praise the LORD, all his heavenly hosts, you his servants who do his will.</ab>
          <ab n="22">Praise the LORD, all his works everywhere in his dominion. Praise the LORD, O my soul.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="104">
          <ab n="1">Praise the LORD, O my soul. O LORD my God, you are very great; you are clothed with splendor and majesty.</ab>
          <ab n="2">He wraps himself in light as with a garment; he stretches out the heavens like a tent</ab>
          <ab n="3">and lays the beams of his upper chambers on their waters. He makes the clouds his chariot and rides on the wings of the wind.</ab>
          <ab n="4">He makes winds his messengers, flames of fire his servants.</ab>
          <ab n="5">He set the earth on its foundations; it can never be moved.</ab>
          <ab n="6">You covered it with the deep as with a garment; the waters stood above the mountains.</ab>
          <ab n="7">But at your rebuke the waters fled, at the sound of your thunder they took to flight;</ab>
          <ab n="8">they flowed over the mountains, they went down into the valleys, to the place you assigned for them.</ab>
          <ab n="9">You set a boundary they cannot cross; never again will they cover the earth.</ab>
          <ab n="10">He makes springs pour water into the ravines; it flows between the mountains.</ab>
          <ab n="11">They give water to all the beasts of the field; the wild donkeys quench their thirst.</ab>
          <ab n="12">The birds of the air nest by the waters; they sing among the branches.</ab>
          <ab n="13">He waters the mountains from his upper chambers; the earth is satisfied by the fruit of his work.</ab>
          <ab n="14">He makes grass grow for the cattle, and plants for man to cultivate- bringing forth food from the earth:</ab>
          <ab n="15">wine that gladdens the heart of man, oil to make his face shine, and bread that sustains his heart.</ab>
          <ab n="16">The trees of the LORD are well watered, the cedars of Lebanon that he planted.</ab>
          <ab n="17">There the birds make their nests; the stork has its home in the pine trees.</ab>
          <ab n="18">The high mountains belong to the wild goats; the crags are a refuge for the coneys.</ab>
          <ab n="19">The moon marks off the seasons, and the sun knows when to go down.</ab>
          <ab n="20">You bring darkness, it becomes night, and all the beasts of the forest prowl.</ab>
          <ab n="21">The lions roar for their prey and seek their food from God.</ab>
          <ab n="22">The sun rises, and they steal away; they return and lie down in their dens.</ab>
          <ab n="23">Then man goes out to his work, to his labor until evening.</ab>
          <ab n="24">How many are your works, O LORD! In wisdom you made them all; the earth is full of your creatures.</ab>
          <ab n="25">There is the sea, vast and spacious, teeming with creatures beyond number- living things both large and small.</ab>
          <ab n="26">There the ships go to and fro, and the leviathan, which you formed to frolic there.</ab>
          <ab n="27">These all look to you to give them their food at the proper time.</ab>
          <ab n="28">When you give it to them, they gather it up; when you open your hand, they are satisfied with good things.</ab>
          <ab n="29">When you hide your face, they are terrified; when you take away their breath, they die and return to the dust.</ab>
          <ab n="30">When you send your Spirit, they are created, and you renew the face of the earth.</ab>
          <ab n="31">May the glory of the LORD endure forever; may the LORD rejoice in his works-</ab>
          <ab n="32">he who looks at the earth, and it trembles, who touches the mountains, and they smoke.</ab>
          <ab n="33">I will sing to the LORD all my life; I will sing praise to my God as long as I live.</ab>
          <ab n="34">May my meditation be pleasing to him, as I rejoice in the LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="35">But may sinners vanish from the earth and the wicked be no more. Praise the LORD, O my soul. Praise the LORD.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="105">
          <ab n="1">Give thanks to the LORD, call on his name; make known among the nations what he has done.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Sing to him, sing praise to him; tell of all his wonderful acts.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Glory in his holy name; let the hearts of those who seek the LORD rejoice.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Look to the LORD and his strength; seek his face always.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Remember the wonders he has done, his miracles, and the judgments he pronounced,</ab>
          <ab n="6">O descendants of Abraham his servant, O sons of Jacob, his chosen ones.</ab>
          <ab n="7">He is the LORD our God; his judgments are in all the earth.</ab>
          <ab n="8">He remembers his covenant forever, the word he commanded, for a thousand generations,</ab>
          <ab n="9">the covenant he made with Abraham, the oath he swore to Isaac.</ab>
          <ab n="10">He confirmed it to Jacob as a decree, to Israel as an everlasting covenant:</ab>
          <ab n="11">"To you I will give the land of Canaan as the portion you will inherit."</ab>
          <ab n="12">When they were but few in number, few indeed, and strangers in it,</ab>
          <ab n="13">they wandered from nation to nation, from one kingdom to another.</ab>
          <ab n="14">He allowed no one to oppress them; for their sake he rebuked kings:</ab>
          <ab n="15">"Do not touch my anointed ones; do my prophets no harm."</ab>
          <ab n="16">He called down famine on the land and destroyed all their supplies of food;</ab>
          <ab n="17">and he sent a man before them- Joseph, sold as a slave.</ab>
          <ab n="18">They bruised his feet with shackles, his neck was put in irons,</ab>
          <ab n="19">till what he foretold came to pass, till the word of the LORD proved him true.</ab>
          <ab n="20">The king sent and released him, the ruler of peoples set him free.</ab>
          <ab n="21">He made him master of his household, ruler over all he possessed,</ab>
          <ab n="22">to instruct his princes as he pleased and teach his elders wisdom.</ab>
          <ab n="23">Then Israel entered Egypt; Jacob lived as an alien in the land of Ham.</ab>
          <ab n="24">The LORD made his people very fruitful; he made them too numerous for their foes,</ab>
          <ab n="25">whose hearts he turned to hate his people, to conspire against his servants.</ab>
          <ab n="26">He sent Moses his servant, and Aaron, whom he had chosen.</ab>
          <ab n="27">They performed his miraculous signs among them, his wonders in the land of Ham.</ab>
          <ab n="28">He sent darkness and made the land dark- for had they not rebelled against his words?</ab>
          <ab n="29">He turned their waters into blood, causing their fish to die.</ab>
          <ab n="30">Their land teemed with frogs, which went up into the bedrooms of their rulers.</ab>
          <ab n="31">He spoke, and there came swarms of flies, and gnats throughout their country.</ab>
          <ab n="32">He turned their rain into hail, with lightning throughout their land;</ab>
          <ab n="33">he struck down their vines and fig trees and shattered the trees of their country.</ab>
          <ab n="34">He spoke, and the locusts came, grasshoppers without number;</ab>
          <ab n="35">they ate up every green thing in their land, ate up the produce of their soil.</ab>
          <ab n="36">Then he struck down all the firstborn in their land, the firstfruits of all their manhood.</ab>
          <ab n="37">He brought out Israel, laden with silver and gold, and from among their tribes no one faltered.</ab>
          <ab n="38">Egypt was glad when they left, because dread of Israel had fallen on them.</ab>
          <ab n="39">He spread out a cloud as a covering, and a fire to give light at night.</ab>
          <ab n="40">They asked, and he brought them quail and satisfied them with the bread of heaven.</ab>
          <ab n="41">He opened the rock, and water gushed out; like a river it flowed in the desert.</ab>
          <ab n="42">For he remembered his holy promise given to his servant Abraham.</ab>
          <ab n="43">He brought out his people with rejoicing, his chosen ones with shouts of joy;</ab>
          <ab n="44">he gave them the lands of the nations, and they fell heir to what others had toiled for-</ab>
          <ab n="45">that they might keep his precepts and observe his laws. Praise the LORD.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="106">
          <ab n="1">Praise the LORD. Give thanks to the LORD, for he is good; his love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Who can proclaim the mighty acts of the LORD or fully declare his praise?</ab>
          <ab n="3">Blessed are they who maintain justice, who constantly do what is right.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Remember me, O LORD, when you show favor to your people, come to my aid when you save them,</ab>
          <ab n="5">that I may enjoy the prosperity of your chosen ones, that I may share in the joy of your nation and join your inheritance in giving praise.</ab>
          <ab n="6">We have sinned, even as our fathers did; we have done wrong and acted wickedly.</ab>
          <ab n="7">When our fathers were in Egypt, they gave no thought to your miracles; they did not remember your many kindnesses, and they rebelled by the sea, the Red Sea.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Yet he saved them for his name's sake, to make his mighty power known.</ab>
          <ab n="9">He rebuked the Red Sea, and it dried up; he led them through the depths as through a desert.</ab>
          <ab n="10">He saved them from the hand of the foe; from the hand of the enemy he redeemed them.</ab>
          <ab n="11">The waters covered their adversaries; not one of them survived.</ab>
          <ab n="12">Then they believed his promises and sang his praise.</ab>
          <ab n="13">But they soon forgot what he had done and did not wait for his counsel.</ab>
          <ab n="14">In the desert they gave in to their craving; in the wasteland they put God to the test.</ab>
          <ab n="15">So he gave them what they asked for, but sent a wasting disease upon them.</ab>
          <ab n="16">In the camp they grew envious of Moses and of Aaron, who was consecrated to the LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="17">The earth opened up and swallowed Dathan; it buried the company of Abiram.</ab>
          <ab n="18">Fire blazed among their followers; a flame consumed the wicked.</ab>
          <ab n="19">At Horeb they made a calf and worshiped an idol cast from metal.</ab>
          <ab n="20">They exchanged their Glory for an image of a bull, which eats grass.</ab>
          <ab n="21">They forgot the God who saved them, who had done great things in Egypt,</ab>
          <ab n="22">miracles in the land of Ham and awesome deeds by the Red Sea.</ab>
          <ab n="23">So he said he would destroy them- had not Moses, his chosen one, stood in the breach before him to keep his wrath from destroying them.</ab>
          <ab n="24">Then they despised the pleasant land; they did not believe his promise.</ab>
          <ab n="25">They grumbled in their tents and did not obey the LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="26">So he swore to them with uplifted hand that he would make them fall in the desert,</ab>
          <ab n="27">make their descendants fall among the nations and scatter them throughout the lands.</ab>
          <ab n="28">They yoked themselves to the Baal of Peor and ate sacrifices offered to lifeless gods;</ab>
          <ab n="29">they provoked the LORD to anger by their wicked deeds, and a plague broke out among them.</ab>
          <ab n="30">But Phinehas stood up and intervened, and the plague was checked.</ab>
          <ab n="31">This was credited to him as righteousness for endless generations to come.</ab>
          <ab n="32">By the waters of Meribah they angered the LORD, and trouble came to Moses because of them;</ab>
          <ab n="33">for they rebelled against the Spirit of God, and rash words came from Moses' lips.</ab>
          <ab n="34">They did not destroy the peoples as the LORD had commanded them,</ab>
          <ab n="35">but they mingled with the nations and adopted their customs.</ab>
          <ab n="36">They worshiped their idols, which became a snare to them.</ab>
          <ab n="37">They sacrificed their sons and their daughters to demons.</ab>
          <ab n="38">They shed innocent blood, the blood of their sons and daughters, whom they sacrificed to the idols of Canaan, and the land was desecrated by their blood.</ab>
          <ab n="39">They defiled themselves by what they did; by their deeds they prostituted themselves.</ab>
          <ab n="40">Therefore the LORD was angry with his people and abhorred his inheritance.</ab>
          <ab n="41">He handed them over to the nations, and their foes ruled over them.</ab>
          <ab n="42">Their enemies oppressed them and subjected them to their power.</ab>
          <ab n="43">Many times he delivered them, but they were bent on rebellion and they wasted away in their sin.</ab>
          <ab n="44">But he took note of their distress when he heard their cry;</ab>
          <ab n="45">for their sake he remembered his covenant and out of his great love he relented.</ab>
          <ab n="46">He caused them to be pitied by all who held them captive.</ab>
          <ab n="47">Save us, O LORD our God, and gather us from the nations, that we may give thanks to your holy name and glory in your praise.</ab>
          <ab n="48">Praise be to the LORD, the God of Israel, from everlasting to everlasting. Let all the people say, "Amen!" Praise the LORD.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="107">
          <ab n="1">Give thanks to the LORD, for he is good; his love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Let the redeemed of the LORD say this- those he redeemed from the hand of the foe,</ab>
          <ab n="3">those he gathered from the lands, from east and west, from north and south.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Some wandered in desert wastelands, finding no way to a city where they could settle.</ab>
          <ab n="5">They were hungry and thirsty, and their lives ebbed away.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Then they cried out to the LORD in their trouble, and he delivered them from their distress.</ab>
          <ab n="7">He led them by a straight way to a city where they could settle.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Let them give thanks to the LORD for his unfailing love and his wonderful deeds for men,</ab>
          <ab n="9">for he satisfies the thirsty and fills the hungry with good things.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Some sat in darkness and the deepest gloom, prisoners suffering in iron chains,</ab>
          <ab n="11">for they had rebelled against the words of God and despised the counsel of the Most High.</ab>
          <ab n="12">So he subjected them to bitter labor; they stumbled, and there was no one to help.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Then they cried to the LORD in their trouble, and he saved them from their distress.</ab>
          <ab n="14">He brought them out of darkness and the deepest gloom and broke away their chains.</ab>
          <ab n="15">Let them give thanks to the LORD for his unfailing love and his wonderful deeds for men,</ab>
          <ab n="16">for he breaks down gates of bronze and cuts through bars of iron.</ab>
          <ab n="17">Some became fools through their rebellious ways and suffered affliction because of their iniquities.</ab>
          <ab n="18">They loathed all food and drew near the gates of death.</ab>
          <ab n="19">Then they cried to the LORD in their trouble, and he saved them from their distress.</ab>
          <ab n="20">He sent forth his word and healed them; he rescued them from the grave.</ab>
          <ab n="21">Let them give thanks to the LORD for his unfailing love and his wonderful deeds for men.</ab>
          <ab n="22">Let them sacrifice thank offerings and tell of his works with songs of joy.</ab>
          <ab n="23">Others went out on the sea in ships; they were merchants on the mighty waters.</ab>
          <ab n="24">They saw the works of the LORD, his wonderful deeds in the deep.</ab>
          <ab n="25">For he spoke and stirred up a tempest that lifted high the waves.</ab>
          <ab n="26">They mounted up to the heavens and went down to the depths; in their peril their courage melted away.</ab>
          <ab n="27">They reeled and staggered like drunken men; they were at their wits' end.</ab>
          <ab n="28">Then they cried out to the LORD in their trouble, and he brought them out of their distress.</ab>
          <ab n="29">He stilled the storm to a whisper; the waves of the sea were hushed.</ab>
          <ab n="30">They were glad when it grew calm, and he guided them to their desired haven.</ab>
          <ab n="31">Let them give thanks to the LORD for his unfailing love and his wonderful deeds for men.</ab>
          <ab n="32">Let them exalt him in the assembly of the people and praise him in the council of the elders.</ab>
          <ab n="33">He turned rivers into a desert, flowing springs into thirsty ground,</ab>
          <ab n="34">and fruitful land into a salt waste, because of the wickedness of those who lived there.</ab>
          <ab n="35">He turned the desert into pools of water and the parched ground into flowing springs;</ab>
          <ab n="36">there he brought the hungry to live, and they founded a city where they could settle.</ab>
          <ab n="37">They sowed fields and planted vineyards that yielded a fruitful harvest;</ab>
          <ab n="38">he blessed them, and their numbers greatly increased, and he did not let their herds diminish.</ab>
          <ab n="39">Then their numbers decreased, and they were humbled by oppression, calamity and sorrow;</ab>
          <ab n="40">he who pours contempt on nobles made them wander in a trackless waste.</ab>
          <ab n="41">But he lifted the needy out of their affliction and increased their families like flocks.</ab>
          <ab n="42">The upright see and rejoice, but all the wicked shut their mouths.</ab>
          <ab n="43">Whoever is wise, let him heed these things and consider the great love of the LORD.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="108">
          <ab n="1">My heart is steadfast, O God; I will sing and make music with all my soul.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Awake, harp and lyre! I will awaken the dawn.</ab>
          <ab n="3">I will praise you, O LORD, among the nations; I will sing of you among the peoples.</ab>
          <ab n="4">For great is your love, higher than the heavens; your faithfulness reaches to the skies.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Be exalted, O God, above the heavens, and let your glory be over all the earth.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Save us and help us with your right hand, that those you love may be delivered.</ab>
          <ab n="7">God has spoken from his sanctuary: "In triumph I will parcel out Shechem and measure off the Valley of Succoth.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Gilead is mine, Manasseh is mine; Ephraim is my helmet, Judah my scepter.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Moab is my washbasin, upon Edom I toss my sandal; over Philistia I shout in triumph."</ab>
          <ab n="10">Who will bring me to the fortified city? Who will lead me to Edom?</ab>
          <ab n="11">Is it not you, O God, you who have rejected us and no longer go out with our armies?</ab>
          <ab n="12">Give us aid against the enemy, for the help of man is worthless.</ab>
          <ab n="13">With God we will gain the victory, and he will trample down our enemies.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="109">
          <ab n="1">O God, whom I praise, do not remain silent,</ab>
          <ab n="2">for wicked and deceitful men have opened their mouths against me; they have spoken against me with lying tongues.</ab>
          <ab n="3">With words of hatred they surround me; they attack me without cause.</ab>
          <ab n="4">In return for my friendship they accuse me, but I am a man of prayer.</ab>
          <ab n="5">They repay me evil for good, and hatred for my friendship.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Appoint an evil man to oppose him; let an accuser stand at his right hand.</ab>
          <ab n="7">When he is tried, let him be found guilty, and may his prayers condemn him.</ab>
          <ab n="8">May his days be few; may another take his place of leadership.</ab>
          <ab n="9">May his children be fatherless and his wife a widow.</ab>
          <ab n="10">May his children be wandering beggars; may they be driven from their ruined homes.</ab>
          <ab n="11">May a creditor seize all he has; may strangers plunder the fruits of his labor.</ab>
          <ab n="12">May no one extend kindness to him or take pity on his fatherless children.</ab>
          <ab n="13">May his descendants be cut off, their names blotted out from the next generation.</ab>
          <ab n="14">May the iniquity of his fathers be remembered before the LORD; may the sin of his mother never be blotted out.</ab>
          <ab n="15">May their sins always remain before the LORD, that he may cut off the memory of them from the earth.</ab>
          <ab n="16">For he never thought of doing a kindness, but hounded to death the poor and the needy and the brokenhearted.</ab>
          <ab n="17">He loved to pronounce a curse- may it come on him; he found no pleasure in blessing- may it be far from him.</ab>
          <ab n="18">He wore cursing as his garment; it entered into his body like water, into his bones like oil.</ab>
          <ab n="19">May it be like a cloak wrapped about him, like a belt tied forever around him.</ab>
          <ab n="20">May this be the LORD's payment to my accusers, to those who speak evil of me.</ab>
          <ab n="21">But you, O Sovereign LORD, deal well with me for your name's sake; out of the goodness of your love, deliver me.</ab>
          <ab n="22">For I am poor and needy, and my heart is wounded within me.</ab>
          <ab n="23">I fade away like an evening shadow; I am shaken off like a locust.</ab>
          <ab n="24">My knees give way from fasting; my body is thin and gaunt.</ab>
          <ab n="25">I am an object of scorn to my accusers; when they see me, they shake their heads.</ab>
          <ab n="26">Help me, O LORD my God; save me in accordance with your love.</ab>
          <ab n="27">Let them know that it is your hand, that you, O LORD, have done it.</ab>
          <ab n="28">They may curse, but you will bless; when they attack they will be put to shame, but your servant will rejoice.</ab>
          <ab n="29">My accusers will be clothed with disgrace and wrapped in shame as in a cloak.</ab>
          <ab n="30">With my mouth I will greatly extol the LORD; in the great throng I will praise him.</ab>
          <ab n="31">For he stands at the right hand of the needy one, to save his life from those who condemn him.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="110">
          <ab n="1">The LORD says to my Lord: "Sit at my right hand until I make your enemies a footstool for your feet."</ab>
          <ab n="2">The LORD will extend your mighty scepter from Zion; you will rule in the midst of your enemies.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Your troops will be willing on your day of battle. Arrayed in holy majesty, from the womb of the dawn you will receive the dew of your youth.</ab>
          <ab n="4">The LORD has sworn and will not change his mind: "You are a priest forever, in the order of Melchizedek."</ab>
          <ab n="5">The Lord is at your right hand; he will crush kings on the day of his wrath.</ab>
          <ab n="6">He will judge the nations, heaping up the dead and crushing the rulers of the whole earth.</ab>
          <ab n="7">He will drink from a brook beside the way; therefore he will lift up his head.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="111">
          <ab n="1">Praise the LORD. I will extol the LORD with all my heart in the council of the upright and in the assembly.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Great are the works of the LORD; they are pondered by all who delight in them.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Glorious and majestic are his deeds, and his righteousness endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="4">He has caused his wonders to be remembered; the LORD is gracious and compassionate.</ab>
          <ab n="5">He provides food for those who fear him; he remembers his covenant forever.</ab>
          <ab n="6">He has shown his people the power of his works, giving them the lands of other nations.</ab>
          <ab n="7">The works of his hands are faithful and just; all his precepts are trustworthy.</ab>
          <ab n="8">They are steadfast for ever and ever, done in faithfulness and uprightness.</ab>
          <ab n="9">He provided redemption for his people; he ordained his covenant forever- holy and awesome is his name.</ab>
          <ab n="10">The fear of the LORD is the beginning of wisdom; all who follow his precepts have good understanding. To him belongs eternal praise.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="112">
          <ab n="1">Praise the LORD. Blessed is the man who fears the LORD, who finds great delight in his commands.</ab>
          <ab n="2">His children will be mighty in the land; the generation of the upright will be blessed.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Wealth and riches are in his house, and his righteousness endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Even in darkness light dawns for the upright, for the gracious and compassionate and righteous man.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Good will come to him who is generous and lends freely, who conducts his affairs with justice.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Surely he will never be shaken; a righteous man will be remembered forever.</ab>
          <ab n="7">He will have no fear of bad news; his heart is steadfast, trusting in the LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="8">His heart is secure, he will have no fear; in the end he will look in triumph on his foes.</ab>
          <ab n="9">He has scattered abroad his gifts to the poor, his righteousness endures forever; his horn will be lifted high in honor.</ab>
          <ab n="10">The wicked man will see and be vexed, he will gnash his teeth and waste away; the longings of the wicked will come to nothing.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="113">
          <ab n="1">Praise the LORD. Praise, O servants of the LORD, praise the name of the LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Let the name of the LORD be praised, both now and forevermore.</ab>
          <ab n="3">From the rising of the sun to the place where it sets, the name of the LORD is to be praised.</ab>
          <ab n="4">The LORD is exalted over all the nations, his glory above the heavens.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Who is like the LORD our God, the One who sits enthroned on high,</ab>
          <ab n="6">who stoops down to look on the heavens and the earth?</ab>
          <ab n="7">He raises the poor from the dust and lifts the needy from the ash heap;</ab>
          <ab n="8">he seats them with princes, with the princes of their people.</ab>
          <ab n="9">He settles the barren woman in her home as a happy mother of children. Praise the LORD.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="114">
          <ab n="1">When Israel came out of Egypt, the house of Jacob from a people of foreign tongue,</ab>
          <ab n="2">Judah became God's sanctuary, Israel his dominion.</ab>
          <ab n="3">The sea looked and fled, the Jordan turned back;</ab>
          <ab n="4">the mountains skipped like rams, the hills like lambs.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Why was it, O sea, that you fled, O Jordan, that you turned back,</ab>
          <ab n="6">you mountains, that you skipped like rams, you hills, like lambs?</ab>
          <ab n="7">Tremble, O earth, at the presence of the Lord, at the presence of the God of Jacob,</ab>
          <ab n="8">who turned the rock into a pool, the hard rock into springs of water.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="115">
          <ab n="1">Not to us, O LORD, not to us but to your name be the glory, because of your love and faithfulness.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Why do the nations say, "Where is their God?"</ab>
          <ab n="3">Our God is in heaven; he does whatever pleases him.</ab>
          <ab n="4">But their idols are silver and gold, made by the hands of men.</ab>
          <ab n="5">They have mouths, but cannot speak, eyes, but they cannot see;</ab>
          <ab n="6">they have ears, but cannot hear, noses, but they cannot smell;</ab>
          <ab n="7">they have hands, but cannot feel, feet, but they cannot walk; nor can they utter a sound with their throats.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Those who make them will be like them, and so will all who trust in them.</ab>
          <ab n="9">O house of Israel, trust in the LORD - he is their help and shield.</ab>
          <ab n="10">O house of Aaron, trust in the LORD - he is their help and shield.</ab>
          <ab n="11">You who fear him, trust in the LORD - he is their help and shield.</ab>
          <ab n="12">The LORD remembers us and will bless us: He will bless the house of Israel, he will bless the house of Aaron,</ab>
          <ab n="13">he will bless those who fear the LORD - small and great alike.</ab>
          <ab n="14">May the LORD make you increase, both you and your children.</ab>
          <ab n="15">May you be blessed by the LORD, the Maker of heaven and earth.</ab>
          <ab n="16">The highest heavens belong to the LORD, but the earth he has given to man.</ab>
          <ab n="17">It is not the dead who praise the LORD, those who go down to silence;</ab>
          <ab n="18">it is we who extol the LORD, both now and forevermore. Praise the LORD.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="116">
          <ab n="1">I love the LORD, for he heard my voice; he heard my cry for mercy.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Because he turned his ear to me, I will call on him as long as I live.</ab>
          <ab n="3">The cords of death entangled me, the anguish of the grave came upon me; I was overcome by trouble and sorrow.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Then I called on the name of the LORD: "O LORD, save me!"</ab>
          <ab n="5">The LORD is gracious and righteous; our God is full of compassion.</ab>
          <ab n="6">The LORD protects the simplehearted; when I was in great need, he saved me.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Be at rest once more, O my soul, for the LORD has been good to you.</ab>
          <ab n="8">For you, O LORD, have delivered my soul from death, my eyes from tears, my feet from stumbling,</ab>
          <ab n="9">that I may walk before the LORD in the land of the living.</ab>
          <ab n="10">I believed; therefore I said, "I am greatly afflicted."</ab>
          <ab n="11">And in my dismay I said, "All men are liars."</ab>
          <ab n="12">How can I repay the LORD for all his goodness to me?</ab>
          <ab n="13">I will lift up the cup of salvation and call on the name of the LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="14">I will fulfill my vows to the LORD in the presence of all his people.</ab>
          <ab n="15">Precious in the sight of the LORD is the death of his saints.</ab>
          <ab n="16">O LORD, truly I am your servant; I am your servant, the son of your maidservant; you have freed me from my chains.</ab>
          <ab n="17">I will sacrifice a thank offering to you and call on the name of the LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="18">I will fulfill my vows to the LORD in the presence of all his people,</ab>
          <ab n="19">in the courts of the house of the LORD - in your midst, O Jerusalem. Praise the LORD.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="117">
          <ab n="1">Praise the LORD, all you nations; extol him, all you peoples.</ab>
          <ab n="2">For great is his love toward us, and the faithfulness of the LORD endures forever. Praise the LORD.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="118">
          <ab n="1">Give thanks to the LORD, for he is good; his love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Let Israel say: "His love endures forever."</ab>
          <ab n="3">Let the house of Aaron say: "His love endures forever."</ab>
          <ab n="4">Let those who fear the LORD say: "His love endures forever."</ab>
          <ab n="5">In my anguish I cried to the LORD, and he answered by setting me free.</ab>
          <ab n="6">The LORD is with me; I will not be afraid. What can man do to me?</ab>
          <ab n="7">The LORD is with me; he is my helper. I will look in triumph on my enemies.</ab>
          <ab n="8">It is better to take refuge in the LORD than to trust in man.</ab>
          <ab n="9">It is better to take refuge in the LORD than to trust in princes.</ab>
          <ab n="10">All the nations surrounded me, but in the name of the LORD I cut them off.</ab>
          <ab n="11">They surrounded me on every side, but in the name of the LORD I cut them off.</ab>
          <ab n="12">They swarmed around me like bees, but they died out as quickly as burning thorns; in the name of the LORD I cut them off.</ab>
          <ab n="13">I was pushed back and about to fall, but the LORD helped me.</ab>
          <ab n="14">The LORD is my strength and my song; he has become my salvation.</ab>
          <ab n="15">Shouts of joy and victory resound in the tents of the righteous: "The LORD's right hand has done mighty things!</ab>
          <ab n="16">The LORD's right hand is lifted high; the LORD's right hand has done mighty things!"</ab>
          <ab n="17">I will not die but live, and will proclaim what the LORD has done.</ab>
          <ab n="18">The LORD has chastened me severely, but he has not given me over to death.</ab>
          <ab n="19">Open for me the gates of righteousness; I will enter and give thanks to the LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="20">This is the gate of the LORD through which the righteous may enter.</ab>
          <ab n="21">I will give you thanks, for you answered me; you have become my salvation.</ab>
          <ab n="22">The stone the builders rejected has become the capstone;</ab>
          <ab n="23">the LORD has done this, and it is marvelous in our eyes.</ab>
          <ab n="24">This is the day the LORD has made; let us rejoice and be glad in it.</ab>
          <ab n="25">O LORD, save us; O LORD, grant us success.</ab>
          <ab n="26">Blessed is he who comes in the name of the LORD. From the house of the LORD we bless you.</ab>
          <ab n="27">The LORD is God, and he has made his light shine upon us. With boughs in hand, join in the festal procession up to the horns of the altar.</ab>
          <ab n="28">You are my God, and I will give you thanks; you are my God, and I will exalt you.</ab>
          <ab n="29">Give thanks to the LORD, for he is good; his love endures forever.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="119">
          <ab n="1">Blessed are they whose ways are blameless, who walk according to the law of the LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Blessed are they who keep his statutes and seek him with all their heart.</ab>
          <ab n="3">They do nothing wrong; they walk in his ways.</ab>
          <ab n="4">You have laid down precepts that are to be fully obeyed.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Oh, that my ways were steadfast in obeying your decrees!</ab>
          <ab n="6">Then I would not be put to shame when I consider all your commands.</ab>
          <ab n="7">I will praise you with an upright heart as I learn your righteous laws.</ab>
          <ab n="8">I will obey your decrees; do not utterly forsake me.</ab>
          <ab n="9">How can a young man keep his way pure? By living according to your word.</ab>
          <ab n="10">I seek you with all my heart; do not let me stray from your commands.</ab>
          <ab n="11">I have hidden your word in my heart that I might not sin against you.</ab>
          <ab n="12">Praise be to you, O LORD; teach me your decrees.</ab>
          <ab n="13">With my lips I recount all the laws that come from your mouth.</ab>
          <ab n="14">I rejoice in following your statutes as one rejoices in great riches.</ab>
          <ab n="15">I meditate on your precepts and consider your ways.</ab>
          <ab n="16">I delight in your decrees; I will not neglect your word.</ab>
          <ab n="17">Do good to your servant, and I will live; I will obey your word.</ab>
          <ab n="18">Open my eyes that I may see wonderful things in your law.</ab>
          <ab n="19">I am a stranger on earth; do not hide your commands from me.</ab>
          <ab n="20">My soul is consumed with longing for your laws at all times.</ab>
          <ab n="21">You rebuke the arrogant, who are cursed and who stray from your commands.</ab>
          <ab n="22">Remove from me scorn and contempt, for I keep your statutes.</ab>
          <ab n="23">Though rulers sit together and slander me, your servant will meditate on your decrees.</ab>
          <ab n="24">Your statutes are my delight; they are my counselors.</ab>
          <ab n="25">I am laid low in the dust; preserve my life according to your word.</ab>
          <ab n="26">I recounted my ways and you answered me; teach me your decrees.</ab>
          <ab n="27">Let me understand the teaching of your precepts; then I will meditate on your wonders.</ab>
          <ab n="28">My soul is weary with sorrow; strengthen me according to your word.</ab>
          <ab n="29">Keep me from deceitful ways; be gracious to me through your law.</ab>
          <ab n="30">I have chosen the way of truth; I have set my heart on your laws.</ab>
          <ab n="31">I hold fast to your statutes, O LORD; do not let me be put to shame.</ab>
          <ab n="32">I run in the path of your commands, for you have set my heart free.</ab>
          <ab n="33">Teach me, O LORD, to follow your decrees; then I will keep them to the end.</ab>
          <ab n="34">Give me understanding, and I will keep your law and obey it with all my heart.</ab>
          <ab n="35">Direct me in the path of your commands, for there I find delight.</ab>
          <ab n="36">Turn my heart toward your statutes and not toward selfish gain.</ab>
          <ab n="37">Turn my eyes away from worthless things; preserve my life according to your word.</ab>
          <ab n="38">Fulfill your promise to your servant, so that you may be feared.</ab>
          <ab n="39">Take away the disgrace I dread, for your laws are good.</ab>
          <ab n="40">How I long for your precepts! Preserve my life in your righteousness.</ab>
          <ab n="41">May your unfailing love come to me, O LORD, your salvation according to your promise;</ab>
          <ab n="42">then I will answer the one who taunts me, for I trust in your word.</ab>
          <ab n="43">Do not snatch the word of truth from my mouth, for I have put my hope in your laws.</ab>
          <ab n="44">I will always obey your law, for ever and ever.</ab>
          <ab n="45">I will walk about in freedom, for I have sought out your precepts.</ab>
          <ab n="46">I will speak of your statutes before kings and will not be put to shame,</ab>
          <ab n="47">for I delight in your commands because I love them.</ab>
          <ab n="48">I lift up my hands to your commands, which I love, and I meditate on your decrees.</ab>
          <ab n="49">Remember your word to your servant, for you have given me hope.</ab>
          <ab n="50">My comfort in my suffering is this: Your promise preserves my life.</ab>
          <ab n="51">The arrogant mock me without restraint, but I do not turn from your law.</ab>
          <ab n="52">I remember your ancient laws, O LORD, and I find comfort in them.</ab>
          <ab n="53">Indignation grips me because of the wicked, who have forsaken your law.</ab>
          <ab n="54">Your decrees are the theme of my song wherever I lodge.</ab>
          <ab n="55">In the night I remember your name, O LORD, and I will keep your law.</ab>
          <ab n="56">This has been my practice: I obey your precepts.</ab>
          <ab n="57">You are my portion, O LORD; I have promised to obey your words.</ab>
          <ab n="58">I have sought your face with all my heart; be gracious to me according to your promise.</ab>
          <ab n="59">I have considered my ways and have turned my steps to your statutes.</ab>
          <ab n="60">I will hasten and not delay to obey your commands.</ab>
          <ab n="61">Though the wicked bind me with ropes, I will not forget your law.</ab>
          <ab n="62">At midnight I rise to give you thanks for your righteous laws.</ab>
          <ab n="63">I am a friend to all who fear you, to all who follow your precepts.</ab>
          <ab n="64">The earth is filled with your love, O LORD; teach me your decrees.</ab>
          <ab n="65">Do good to your servant according to your word, O LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="66">Teach me knowledge and good judgment, for I believe in your commands.</ab>
          <ab n="67">Before I was afflicted I went astray, but now I obey your word.</ab>
          <ab n="68">You are good, and what you do is good; teach me your decrees.</ab>
          <ab n="69">Though the arrogant have smeared me with lies, I keep your precepts with all my heart.</ab>
          <ab n="70">Their hearts are callous and unfeeling, but I delight in your law.</ab>
          <ab n="71">It was good for me to be afflicted so that I might learn your decrees.</ab>
          <ab n="72">The law from your mouth is more precious to me than thousands of pieces of silver and gold.</ab>
          <ab n="73">Your hands made me and formed me; give me understanding to learn your commands.</ab>
          <ab n="74">May those who fear you rejoice when they see me, for I have put my hope in your word.</ab>
          <ab n="75">I know, O LORD, that your laws are righteous, and in faithfulness you have afflicted me.</ab>
          <ab n="76">May your unfailing love be my comfort, according to your promise to your servant.</ab>
          <ab n="77">Let your compassion come to me that I may live, for your law is my delight.</ab>
          <ab n="78">May the arrogant be put to shame for wronging me without cause; but I will meditate on your precepts.</ab>
          <ab n="79">May those who fear you turn to me, those who understand your statutes.</ab>
          <ab n="80">May my heart be blameless toward your decrees, that I may not be put to shame.</ab>
          <ab n="81">My soul faints with longing for your salvation, but I have put my hope in your word.</ab>
          <ab n="82">My eyes fail, looking for your promise; I say, "When will you comfort me?"</ab>
          <ab n="83">Though I am like a wineskin in the smoke, I do not forget your decrees.</ab>
          <ab n="84">How long must your servant wait? When will you punish my persecutors?</ab>
          <ab n="85">The arrogant dig pitfalls for me, contrary to your law.</ab>
          <ab n="86">All your commands are trustworthy; help me, for men persecute me without cause.</ab>
          <ab n="87">They almost wiped me from the earth, but I have not forsaken your precepts.</ab>
          <ab n="88">Preserve my life according to your love, and I will obey the statutes of your mouth.</ab>
          <ab n="89">Your word, O LORD, is eternal; it stands firm in the heavens.</ab>
          <ab n="90">Your faithfulness continues through all generations; you established the earth, and it endures.</ab>
          <ab n="91">Your laws endure to this day, for all things serve you.</ab>
          <ab n="92">If your law had not been my delight, I would have perished in my affliction.</ab>
          <ab n="93">I will never forget your precepts, for by them you have preserved my life.</ab>
          <ab n="94">Save me, for I am yours; I have sought out your precepts.</ab>
          <ab n="95">The wicked are waiting to destroy me, but I will ponder your statutes.</ab>
          <ab n="96">To all perfection I see a limit; but your commands are boundless.</ab>
          <ab n="97">Oh, how I love your law! I meditate on it all day long.</ab>
          <ab n="98">Your commands make me wiser than my enemies, for they are ever with me.</ab>
          <ab n="99">I have more insight than all my teachers, for I meditate on your statutes.</ab>
          <ab n="100">I have more understanding than the elders, for I obey your precepts.</ab>
          <ab n="101">I have kept my feet from every evil path so that I might obey your word.</ab>
          <ab n="102">I have not departed from your laws, for you yourself have taught me.</ab>
          <ab n="103">How sweet are your words to my taste, sweeter than honey to my mouth!</ab>
          <ab n="104">I gain understanding from your precepts; therefore I hate every wrong path.</ab>
          <ab n="105">Your word is a lamp to my feet and a light for my path.</ab>
          <ab n="106">I have taken an oath and confirmed it, that I will follow your righteous laws.</ab>
          <ab n="107">I have suffered much; preserve my life, O LORD, according to your word.</ab>
          <ab n="108">Accept, O LORD, the willing praise of my mouth, and teach me your laws.</ab>
          <ab n="109">Though I constantly take my life in my hands, I will not forget your law.</ab>
          <ab n="110">The wicked have set a snare for me, but I have not strayed from your precepts.</ab>
          <ab n="111">Your statutes are my heritage forever; they are the joy of my heart.</ab>
          <ab n="112">My heart is set on keeping your decrees to the very end.</ab>
          <ab n="113">I hate double-minded men, but I love your law.</ab>
          <ab n="114">You are my refuge and my shield; I have put my hope in your word.</ab>
          <ab n="115">Away from me, you evildoers, that I may keep the commands of my God!</ab>
          <ab n="116">Sustain me according to your promise, and I will live; do not let my hopes be dashed.</ab>
          <ab n="117">Uphold me, and I will be delivered; I will always have regard for your decrees.</ab>
          <ab n="118">You reject all who stray from your decrees, for their deceitfulness is in vain.</ab>
          <ab n="119">All the wicked of the earth you discard like dross; therefore I love your statutes.</ab>
          <ab n="120">My flesh trembles in fear of you; I stand in awe of your laws.</ab>
          <ab n="121">I have done what is righteous and just; do not leave me to my oppressors.</ab>
          <ab n="122">Ensure your servant's well-being; let not the arrogant oppress me.</ab>
          <ab n="123">My eyes fail, looking for your salvation, looking for your righteous promise.</ab>
          <ab n="124">Deal with your servant according to your love and teach me your decrees.</ab>
          <ab n="125">I am your servant; give me discernment that I may understand your statutes.</ab>
          <ab n="126">It is time for you to act, O LORD; your law is being broken.</ab>
          <ab n="127">Because I love your commands more than gold, more than pure gold,</ab>
          <ab n="128">and because I consider all your precepts right, I hate every wrong path.</ab>
          <ab n="129">Your statutes are wonderful; therefore I obey them.</ab>
          <ab n="130">The unfolding of your words gives light; it gives understanding to the simple.</ab>
          <ab n="131">I open my mouth and pant, longing for your commands.</ab>
          <ab n="132">Turn to me and have mercy on me, as you always do to those who love your name.</ab>
          <ab n="133">Direct my footsteps according to your word; let no sin rule over me.</ab>
          <ab n="134">Redeem me from the oppression of men, that I may obey your precepts.</ab>
          <ab n="135">Make your face shine upon your servant and teach me your decrees.</ab>
          <ab n="136">Streams of tears flow from my eyes, for your law is not obeyed.</ab>
          <ab n="137">Righteous are you, O LORD, and your laws are right.</ab>
          <ab n="138">The statutes you have laid down are righteous; they are fully trustworthy.</ab>
          <ab n="139">My zeal wears me out, for my enemies ignore your words.</ab>
          <ab n="140">Your promises have been thoroughly tested, and your servant loves them.</ab>
          <ab n="141">Though I am lowly and despised, I do not forget your precepts.</ab>
          <ab n="142">Your righteousness is everlasting and your law is true.</ab>
          <ab n="143">Trouble and distress have come upon me, but your commands are my delight.</ab>
          <ab n="144">Your statutes are forever right; give me understanding that I may live.</ab>
          <ab n="145">I call with all my heart; answer me, O LORD, and I will obey your decrees.</ab>
          <ab n="146">I call out to you; save me and I will keep your statutes.</ab>
          <ab n="147">I rise before dawn and cry for help; I have put my hope in your word.</ab>
          <ab n="148">My eyes stay open through the watches of the night, that I may meditate on your promises.</ab>
          <ab n="149">Hear my voice in accordance with your love; preserve my life, O LORD, according to your laws.</ab>
          <ab n="150">Those who devise wicked schemes are near, but they are far from your law.</ab>
          <ab n="151">Yet you are near, O LORD, and all your commands are true.</ab>
          <ab n="152">Long ago I learned from your statutes that you established them to last forever.</ab>
          <ab n="153">Look upon my suffering and deliver me, for I have not forgotten your law.</ab>
          <ab n="154">Defend my cause and redeem me; preserve my life according to your promise.</ab>
          <ab n="155">Salvation is far from the wicked, for they do not seek out your decrees.</ab>
          <ab n="156">Your compassion is great, O LORD; preserve my life according to your laws.</ab>
          <ab n="157">Many are the foes who persecute me, but I have not turned from your statutes.</ab>
          <ab n="158">I look on the faithless with loathing, for they do not obey your word.</ab>
          <ab n="159">See how I love your precepts; preserve my life, O LORD, according to your love.</ab>
          <ab n="160">All your words are true; all your righteous laws are eternal.</ab>
          <ab n="161">Rulers persecute me without cause, but my heart trembles at your word.</ab>
          <ab n="162">I rejoice in your promise like one who finds great spoil.</ab>
          <ab n="163">I hate and abhor falsehood but I love your law.</ab>
          <ab n="164">Seven times a day I praise you for your righteous laws.</ab>
          <ab n="165">Great peace have they who love your law, and nothing can make them stumble.</ab>
          <ab n="166">I wait for your salvation, O LORD, and I follow your commands.</ab>
          <ab n="167">I obey your statutes, for I love them greatly.</ab>
          <ab n="168">I obey your precepts and your statutes, for all my ways are known to you.</ab>
          <ab n="169">May my cry come before you, O LORD; give me understanding according to your word.</ab>
          <ab n="170">May my supplication come before you; deliver me according to your promise.</ab>
          <ab n="171">May my lips overflow with praise, for you teach me your decrees.</ab>
          <ab n="172">May my tongue sing of your word, for all your commands are righteous.</ab>
          <ab n="173">May your hand be ready to help me, for I have chosen your precepts.</ab>
          <ab n="174">I long for your salvation, O LORD, and your law is my delight.</ab>
          <ab n="175">Let me live that I may praise you, and may your laws sustain me.</ab>
          <ab n="176">I have strayed like a lost sheep. Seek your servant, for I have not forgotten your commands.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="120">
          <ab n="1">I call on the LORD in my distress, and he answers me.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Save me, O LORD, from lying lips and from deceitful tongues.</ab>
          <ab n="3">What will he do to you, and what more besides, O deceitful tongue?</ab>
          <ab n="4">He will punish you with a warrior's sharp arrows, with burning coals of the broom tree.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Woe to me that I dwell in Meshech, that I live among the tents of Kedar!</ab>
          <ab n="6">Too long have I lived among those who hate peace.</ab>
          <ab n="7">I am a man of peace; but when I speak, they are for war.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="121">
          <ab n="1">I lift up my eyes to the hills- where does my help come from?</ab>
          <ab n="2">My help comes from the LORD, the Maker of heaven and earth.</ab>
          <ab n="3">He will not let your foot slip- he who watches over you will not slumber;</ab>
          <ab n="4">indeed, he who watches over Israel will neither slumber nor sleep.</ab>
          <ab n="5">The LORD watches over you- the LORD is your shade at your right hand;</ab>
          <ab n="6">the sun will not harm you by day, nor the moon by night.</ab>
          <ab n="7">The LORD will keep you from all harm- he will watch over your life;</ab>
          <ab n="8">the LORD will watch over your coming and going both now and forevermore.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="122">
          <ab n="1">I rejoiced with those who said to me, "Let us go to the house of the LORD."</ab>
          <ab n="2">Our feet are standing in your gates, O Jerusalem.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Jerusalem is built like a city that is closely compacted together.</ab>
          <ab n="4">That is where the tribes go up, the tribes of the LORD, to praise the name of the LORD according to the statute given to Israel.</ab>
          <ab n="5">There the thrones for judgment stand, the thrones of the house of David.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Pray for the peace of Jerusalem: "May those who love you be secure.</ab>
          <ab n="7">May there be peace within your walls and security within your citadels."</ab>
          <ab n="8">For the sake of my brothers and friends, I will say, "Peace be within you."</ab>
          <ab n="9">For the sake of the house of the LORD our God, I will seek your prosperity.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="123">
          <ab n="1">I lift up my eyes to you, to you whose throne is in heaven.</ab>
          <ab n="2">As the eyes of slaves look to the hand of their master, as the eyes of a maid look to the hand of her mistress, so our eyes look to the LORD our God, till he shows us his mercy.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Have mercy on us, O LORD, have mercy on us, for we have endured much contempt.</ab>
          <ab n="4">We have endured much ridicule from the proud, much contempt from the arrogant.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="124">
          <ab n="1">If the LORD had not been on our side- let Israel say-</ab>
          <ab n="2">if the LORD had not been on our side when men attacked us,</ab>
          <ab n="3">when their anger flared against us, they would have swallowed us alive;</ab>
          <ab n="4">the flood would have engulfed us, the torrent would have swept over us,</ab>
          <ab n="5">the raging waters would have swept us away.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Praise be to the LORD, who has not let us be torn by their teeth.</ab>
          <ab n="7">We have escaped like a bird out of the fowler's snare; the snare has been broken, and we have escaped.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Our help is in the name of the LORD, the Maker of heaven and earth.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="125">
          <ab n="1">Those who trust in the LORD are like Mount Zion, which cannot be shaken but endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="2">As the mountains surround Jerusalem, so the LORD surrounds his people both now and forevermore.</ab>
          <ab n="3">The scepter of the wicked will not remain over the land allotted to the righteous, for then the righteous might use their hands to do evil.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Do good, O LORD, to those who are good, to those who are upright in heart.</ab>
          <ab n="5">But those who turn to crooked ways the LORD will banish with the evildoers. Peace be upon Israel.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="126">
          <ab n="1">When the LORD brought back the captives to Zion, we were like men who dreamed.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Our mouths were filled with laughter, our tongues with songs of joy. Then it was said among the nations, "The LORD has done great things for them."</ab>
          <ab n="3">The LORD has done great things for us, and we are filled with joy.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Restore our fortunes, O LORD, like streams in the Negev.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Those who sow in tears will reap with songs of joy.</ab>
          <ab n="6">He who goes out weeping, carrying seed to sow, will return with songs of joy, carrying sheaves with him.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="127">
          <ab n="1">Unless the LORD builds the house, its builders labor in vain. Unless the LORD watches over the city, the watchmen stand guard in vain.</ab>
          <ab n="2">In vain you rise early and stay up late, toiling for food to eat- for he grants sleep to those he loves.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Sons are a heritage from the LORD, children a reward from him.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Like arrows in the hands of a warrior are sons born in one's youth.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Blessed is the man whose quiver is full of them. They will not be put to shame when they contend with their enemies in the gate.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="128">
          <ab n="1">Blessed are all who fear the LORD, who walk in his ways.</ab>
          <ab n="2">You will eat the fruit of your labor; blessings and prosperity will be yours.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Your wife will be like a fruitful vine within your house; your sons will be like olive shoots around your table.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Thus is the man blessed who fears the LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="5">May the LORD bless you from Zion all the days of your life; may you see the prosperity of Jerusalem,</ab>
          <ab n="6">and may you live to see your children's children. Peace be upon Israel.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="129">
          <ab n="1">They have greatly oppressed me from my youth- let Israel say-</ab>
          <ab n="2">they have greatly oppressed me from my youth, but they have not gained the victory over me.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Plowmen have plowed my back and made their furrows long.</ab>
          <ab n="4">But the LORD is righteous; he has cut me free from the cords of the wicked.</ab>
          <ab n="5">May all who hate Zion be turned back in shame.</ab>
          <ab n="6">May they be like grass on the roof, which withers before it can grow;</ab>
          <ab n="7">with it the reaper cannot fill his hands, nor the one who gathers fill his arms.</ab>
          <ab n="8">May those who pass by not say, "The blessing of the LORD be upon you; we bless you in the name of the LORD."</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="130">
          <ab n="1">Out of the depths I cry to you, O LORD;</ab>
          <ab n="2">O Lord, hear my voice. Let your ears be attentive to my cry for mercy.</ab>
          <ab n="3">If you, O LORD, kept a record of sins, O Lord, who could stand?</ab>
          <ab n="4">But with you there is forgiveness; therefore you are feared.</ab>
          <ab n="5">I wait for the LORD, my soul waits, and in his word I put my hope.</ab>
          <ab n="6">My soul waits for the Lord more than watchmen wait for the morning, more than watchmen wait for the morning.</ab>
          <ab n="7">O Israel, put your hope in the LORD, for with the LORD is unfailing love and with him is full redemption.</ab>
          <ab n="8">He himself will redeem Israel from all their sins.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="131">
          <ab n="1">My heart is not proud, O LORD, my eyes are not haughty; I do not concern myself with great matters or things too wonderful for me.</ab>
          <ab n="2">But I have stilled and quieted my soul; like a weaned child with its mother, like a weaned child is my soul within me.</ab>
          <ab n="3">O Israel, put your hope in the LORD both now and forevermore.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="132">
          <ab n="1">O LORD, remember David and all the hardships he endured.</ab>
          <ab n="2">He swore an oath to the LORD and made a vow to the Mighty One of Jacob:</ab>
          <ab n="3">"I will not enter my house or go to my bed-</ab>
          <ab n="4">I will allow no sleep to my eyes, no slumber to my eyelids,</ab>
          <ab n="5">till I find a place for the LORD, a dwelling for the Mighty One of Jacob."</ab>
          <ab n="6">We heard it in Ephrathah, we came upon it in the fields of Jaar:</ab>
          <ab n="7">"Let us go to his dwelling place; let us worship at his footstool-</ab>
          <ab n="8">arise, O LORD, and come to your resting place, you and the ark of your might.</ab>
          <ab n="9">May your priests be clothed with righteousness; may your saints sing for joy."</ab>
          <ab n="10">For the sake of David your servant, do not reject your anointed one.</ab>
          <ab n="11">The LORD swore an oath to David, a sure oath that he will not revoke: "One of your own descendants I will place on your throne-</ab>
          <ab n="12">if your sons keep my covenant and the statutes I teach them, then their sons will sit on your throne for ever and ever."</ab>
          <ab n="13">For the LORD has chosen Zion, he has desired it for his dwelling:</ab>
          <ab n="14">"This is my resting place for ever and ever; here I will sit enthroned, for I have desired it-</ab>
          <ab n="15">I will bless her with abundant provisions; her poor will I satisfy with food.</ab>
          <ab n="16">I will clothe her priests with salvation, and her saints will ever sing for joy.</ab>
          <ab n="17">"Here I will make a horn grow for David and set up a lamp for my anointed one.</ab>
          <ab n="18">I will clothe his enemies with shame, but the crown on his head will be resplendent."</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="133">
          <ab n="1">How good and pleasant it is when brothers live together in unity!</ab>
          <ab n="2">It is like precious oil poured on the head, running down on the beard, running down on Aaron's beard, down upon the collar of his robes.</ab>
          <ab n="3">It is as if the dew of Hermon were falling on Mount Zion. For there the LORD bestows his blessing, even life forevermore.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="134">
          <ab n="1">Praise the LORD, all you servants of the LORD who minister by night in the house of the LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Lift up your hands in the sanctuary and praise the LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="3">May the LORD, the Maker of heaven and earth, bless you from Zion.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="135">
          <ab n="1">Praise the LORD. Praise the name of the LORD; praise him, you servants of the LORD,</ab>
          <ab n="2">you who minister in the house of the LORD, in the courts of the house of our God.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Praise the LORD, for the LORD is good; sing praise to his name, for that is pleasant.</ab>
          <ab n="4">For the LORD has chosen Jacob to be his own, Israel to be his treasured possession.</ab>
          <ab n="5">I know that the LORD is great, that our Lord is greater than all gods.</ab>
          <ab n="6">The LORD does whatever pleases him, in the heavens and on the earth, in the seas and all their depths.</ab>
          <ab n="7">He makes clouds rise from the ends of the earth; he sends lightning with the rain and brings out the wind from his storehouses.</ab>
          <ab n="8">He struck down the firstborn of Egypt, the firstborn of men and animals.</ab>
          <ab n="9">He sent his signs and wonders into your midst, O Egypt, against Pharaoh and all his servants.</ab>
          <ab n="10">He struck down many nations and killed mighty kings-</ab>
          <ab n="11">Sihon king of the Amorites, Og king of Bashan and all the kings of Canaan-</ab>
          <ab n="12">and he gave their land as an inheritance, an inheritance to his people Israel.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Your name, O LORD, endures forever, your renown, O LORD, through all generations.</ab>
          <ab n="14">For the LORD will vindicate his people and have compassion on his servants.</ab>
          <ab n="15">The idols of the nations are silver and gold, made by the hands of men.</ab>
          <ab n="16">They have mouths, but cannot speak, eyes, but they cannot see;</ab>
          <ab n="17">they have ears, but cannot hear, nor is there breath in their mouths.</ab>
          <ab n="18">Those who make them will be like them, and so will all who trust in them.</ab>
          <ab n="19">O house of Israel, praise the LORD; O house of Aaron, praise the LORD;</ab>
          <ab n="20">O house of Levi, praise the LORD; you who fear him, praise the LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="21">Praise be to the LORD from Zion, to him who dwells in Jerusalem. Praise the LORD.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="136">
          <ab n="1">Give thanks to the LORD, for he is good. His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Give thanks to the God of gods. His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Give thanks to the Lord of lords: His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="4">to him who alone does great wonders, His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="5">who by his understanding made the heavens, His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="6">who spread out the earth upon the waters, His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="7">who made the great lights- His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="8">the sun to govern the day, His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="9">the moon and stars to govern the night; His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="10">to him who struck down the firstborn of Egypt His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="11">and brought Israel out from among them His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="12">with a mighty hand and outstretched arm; His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="13">to him who divided the Red Sea asunder His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="14">and brought Israel through the midst of it, His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="15">but swept Pharaoh and his army into the Red Sea; His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="16">to him who led his people through the desert, His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="17">who struck down great kings, His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="18">and killed mighty kings- His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="19">Sihon king of the Amorites His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="20">and Og king of Bashan- His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="21">and gave their land as an inheritance, His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="22">an inheritance to his servant Israel; His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="23">to the One who remembered us in our low estate His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="24">and freed us from our enemies, His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="25">and who gives food to every creature. His love endures forever.</ab>
          <ab n="26">Give thanks to the God of heaven. His love endures forever.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="137">
          <ab n="1">By the rivers of Babylon we sat and wept when we remembered Zion.</ab>
          <ab n="2">There on the poplars we hung our harps,</ab>
          <ab n="3">for there our captors asked us for songs, our tormentors demanded songs of joy; they said, "Sing us one of the songs of Zion!"</ab>
          <ab n="4">How can we sing the songs of the LORD while in a foreign land?</ab>
          <ab n="5">If I forget you, O Jerusalem, may my right hand forget its skill.</ab>
          <ab n="6">May my tongue cling to the roof of my mouth if I do not remember you, if I do not consider Jerusalem my highest joy.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Remember, O LORD, what the Edomites did on the day Jerusalem fell. "Tear it down," they cried, "tear it down to its foundations!"</ab>
          <ab n="8">O Daughter of Babylon, doomed to destruction, happy is he who repays you for what you have done to us-</ab>
          <ab n="9">he who seizes your infants and dashes them against the rocks.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="138">
          <ab n="1">I will praise you, O LORD, with all my heart; before the "gods" I will sing your praise.</ab>
          <ab n="2">I will bow down toward your holy temple and will praise your name for your love and your faithfulness, for you have exalted above all things your name and your word.</ab>
          <ab n="3">When I called, you answered me; you made me bold and stouthearted.</ab>
          <ab n="4">May all the kings of the earth praise you, O LORD, when they hear the words of your mouth.</ab>
          <ab n="5">May they sing of the ways of the LORD, for the glory of the LORD is great.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Though the LORD is on high, he looks upon the lowly, but the proud he knows from afar.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Though I walk in the midst of trouble, you preserve my life; you stretch out your hand against the anger of my foes, with your right hand you save me.</ab>
          <ab n="8">The LORD will fulfill his purpose for me; your love, O LORD, endures forever- do not abandon the works of your hands.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="139">
          <ab n="1">O LORD, you have searched me and you know me.</ab>
          <ab n="2">You know when I sit and when I rise; you perceive my thoughts from afar.</ab>
          <ab n="3">You discern my going out and my lying down; you are familiar with all my ways.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Before a word is on my tongue you know it completely, O LORD.</ab>
          <ab n="5">You hem me in-behind and before; you have laid your hand upon me.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Such knowledge is too wonderful for me, too lofty for me to attain.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Where can I go from your Spirit? Where can I flee from your presence?</ab>
          <ab n="8">If I go up to the heavens, you are there; if I make my bed in the depths, you are there.</ab>
          <ab n="9">If I rise on the wings of the dawn, if I settle on the far side of the sea,</ab>
          <ab n="10">even there your hand will guide me, your right hand will hold me fast.</ab>
          <ab n="11">If I say, "Surely the darkness will hide me and the light become night around me,"</ab>
          <ab n="12">even the darkness will not be dark to you; the night will shine like the day, for darkness is as light to you.</ab>
          <ab n="13">For you created my inmost being; you knit me together in my mother's womb.</ab>
          <ab n="14">I praise you because I am fearfully and wonderfully made; your works are wonderful, I know that full well.</ab>
          <ab n="15">My frame was not hidden from you when I was made in the secret place. When I was woven together in the depths of the earth,</ab>
          <ab n="16">your eyes saw my unformed body. All the days ordained for me were written in your book before one of them came to be.</ab>
          <ab n="17">How precious to me are your thoughts, O God! How vast is the sum of them!</ab>
          <ab n="18">Were I to count them, they would outnumber the grains of sand. When I awake, I am still with you.</ab>
          <ab n="19">If only you would slay the wicked, O God! Away from me, you bloodthirsty men!</ab>
          <ab n="20">They speak of you with evil intent; your adversaries misuse your name.</ab>
          <ab n="21">Do I not hate those who hate you, O LORD, and abhor those who rise up against you?</ab>
          <ab n="22">I have nothing but hatred for them; I count them my enemies.</ab>
          <ab n="23">Search me, O God, and know my heart; test me and know my anxious thoughts.</ab>
          <ab n="24">See if there is any offensive way in me, and lead me in the way everlasting.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="140">
          <ab n="1">Rescue me, O LORD, from evil men; protect me from men of violence,</ab>
          <ab n="2">who devise evil plans in their hearts and stir up war every day.</ab>
          <ab n="3">They make their tongues as sharp as a serpent's; the poison of vipers is on their lips. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="4">Keep me, O LORD, from the hands of the wicked; protect me from men of violence who plan to trip my feet.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Proud men have hidden a snare for me; they have spread out the cords of their net and have set traps for me along my path. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="6">O LORD, I say to you, "You are my God." Hear, O LORD, my cry for mercy.</ab>
          <ab n="7">O Sovereign LORD, my strong deliverer, who shields my head in the day of battle-</ab>
          <ab n="8">do not grant the wicked their desires, O LORD; do not let their plans succeed, or they will become proud. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="9">Let the heads of those who surround me be covered with the trouble their lips have caused.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Let burning coals fall upon them; may they be thrown into the fire, into miry pits, never to rise.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Let slanderers not be established in the land; may disaster hunt down men of violence.</ab>
          <ab n="12">I know that the LORD secures justice for the poor and upholds the cause of the needy.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Surely the righteous will praise your name and the upright will live before you.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="141">
          <ab n="1">O LORD, I call to you; come quickly to me. Hear my voice when I call to you.</ab>
          <ab n="2">May my prayer be set before you like incense; may the lifting up of my hands be like the evening sacrifice.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Set a guard over my mouth, O LORD; keep watch over the door of my lips.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Let not my heart be drawn to what is evil, to take part in wicked deeds with men who are evildoers; let me not eat of their delicacies.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Let a righteous man strike me-it is a kindness; let him rebuke me-it is oil on my head. My head will not refuse it. Yet my prayer is ever against the deeds of evildoers;</ab>
          <ab n="6">their rulers will be thrown down from the cliffs, and the wicked will learn that my words were well spoken.</ab>
          <ab n="7">They will say, "As one plows and breaks up the earth, so our bones have been scattered at the mouth of the grave. "</ab>
          <ab n="8">But my eyes are fixed on you, O Sovereign LORD; in you I take refuge-do not give me over to death.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Keep me from the snares they have laid for me, from the traps set by evildoers.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Let the wicked fall into their own nets, while I pass by in safety.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="142">
          <ab n="1">I cry aloud to the LORD; I lift up my voice to the LORD for mercy.</ab>
          <ab n="2">I pour out my complaint before him; before him I tell my trouble.</ab>
          <ab n="3">When my spirit grows faint within me, it is you who know my way. In the path where I walk men have hidden a snare for me.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Look to my right and see; no one is concerned for me. I have no refuge; no one cares for my life.</ab>
          <ab n="5">I cry to you, O LORD; I say, "You are my refuge, my portion in the land of the living."</ab>
          <ab n="6">Listen to my cry, for I am in desperate need; rescue me from those who pursue me, for they are too strong for me.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Set me free from my prison, that I may praise your name. Then the righteous will gather about me because of your goodness to me.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="143">
          <ab n="1">O LORD, hear my prayer, listen to my cry for mercy; in your faithfulness and righteousness come to my relief.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Do not bring your servant into judgment, for no one living is righteous before you.</ab>
          <ab n="3">The enemy pursues me, he crushes me to the ground; he makes me dwell in darkness like those long dead.</ab>
          <ab n="4">So my spirit grows faint within me; my heart within me is dismayed.</ab>
          <ab n="5">I remember the days of long ago; I meditate on all your works and consider what your hands have done.</ab>
          <ab n="6">I spread out my hands to you; my soul thirsts for you like a parched land. Selah</ab>
          <ab n="7">Answer me quickly, O LORD; my spirit fails. Do not hide your face from me or I will be like those who go down to the pit.</ab>
          <ab n="8">Let the morning bring me word of your unfailing love, for I have put my trust in you. Show me the way I should go, for to you I lift up my soul.</ab>
          <ab n="9">Rescue me from my enemies, O LORD, for I hide myself in you.</ab>
          <ab n="10">Teach me to do your will, for you are my God; may your good Spirit lead me on level ground.</ab>
          <ab n="11">For your name's sake, O LORD, preserve my life; in your righteousness, bring me out of trouble.</ab>
          <ab n="12">In your unfailing love, silence my enemies; destroy all my foes, for I am your servant.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="144">
          <ab n="1">Praise be to the LORD my Rock, who trains my hands for war, my fingers for battle.</ab>
          <ab n="2">He is my loving God and my fortress, my stronghold and my deliverer, my shield, in whom I take refuge, who subdues peoples under me.</ab>
          <ab n="3">O LORD, what is man that you care for him, the son of man that you think of him?</ab>
          <ab n="4">Man is like a breath; his days are like a fleeting shadow.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Part your heavens, O LORD, and come down; touch the mountains, so that they smoke.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Send forth lightning and scatter {the enemies}; shoot your arrows and rout them.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Reach down your hand from on high; deliver me and rescue me from the mighty waters, from the hands of foreigners</ab>
          <ab n="8">whose mouths are full of lies, whose right hands are deceitful.</ab>
          <ab n="9">I will sing a new song to you, O God; on the ten-stringed lyre I will make music to you,</ab>
          <ab n="10">to the One who gives victory to kings, who delivers his servant David from the deadly sword.</ab>
          <ab n="11">Deliver me and rescue me from the hands of foreigners whose mouths are full of lies, whose right hands are deceitful.</ab>
          <ab n="12">Then our sons in their youth will be like well-nurtured plants, and our daughters will be like pillars carved to adorn a palace.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Our barns will be filled with every kind of provision. Our sheep will increase by thousands, by tens of thousands in our fields;</ab>
          <ab n="14">our oxen will draw heavy loads. There will be no breaching of walls, no going into captivity, no cry of distress in our streets.</ab>
          <ab n="15">Blessed are the people of whom this is true; blessed are the people whose God is the LORD.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="145">
          <ab n="1">I will exalt you, my God the King; I will praise your name for ever and ever.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Every day I will praise you and extol your name for ever and ever.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Great is the LORD and most worthy of praise; his greatness no one can fathom.</ab>
          <ab n="4">One generation will commend your works to another; they will tell of your mighty acts.</ab>
          <ab n="5">They will speak of the glorious splendor of your majesty, and I will meditate on your wonderful works.</ab>
          <ab n="6">They will tell of the power of your awesome works, and I will proclaim your great deeds.</ab>
          <ab n="7">They will celebrate your abundant goodness and joyfully sing of your righteousness.</ab>
          <ab n="8">The LORD is gracious and compassionate, slow to anger and rich in love.</ab>
          <ab n="9">The LORD is good to all; he has compassion on all he has made.</ab>
          <ab n="10">All you have made will praise you, O LORD; your saints will extol you.</ab>
          <ab n="11">They will tell of the glory of your kingdom and speak of your might,</ab>
          <ab n="12">so that all men may know of your mighty acts and the glorious splendor of your kingdom.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Your kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and your dominion endures through all generations. The LORD is faithful to all his promises and loving toward all he has made.</ab>
          <ab n="14">The LORD upholds all those who fall and lifts up all who are bowed down.</ab>
          <ab n="15">The eyes of all look to you, and you give them their food at the proper time.</ab>
          <ab n="16">You open your hand and satisfy the desires of every living thing.</ab>
          <ab n="17">The LORD is righteous in all his ways and loving toward all he has made.</ab>
          <ab n="18">The LORD is near to all who call on him, to all who call on him in truth.</ab>
          <ab n="19">He fulfills the desires of those who fear him; he hears their cry and saves them.</ab>
          <ab n="20">The LORD watches over all who love him, but all the wicked he will destroy.</ab>
          <ab n="21">My mouth will speak in praise of the LORD. Let every creature praise his holy name for ever and ever.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="146">
          <ab n="1">Praise the LORD. Praise the LORD, O my soul.</ab>
          <ab n="2">I will praise the LORD all my life; I will sing praise to my God as long as I live.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Do not put your trust in princes, in mortal men, who cannot save.</ab>
          <ab n="4">When their spirit departs, they return to the ground; on that very day their plans come to nothing.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Blessed is he whose help is the God of Jacob, whose hope is in the LORD his God,</ab>
          <ab n="6">the Maker of heaven and earth, the sea, and everything in them- the LORD, who remains faithful forever.</ab>
          <ab n="7">He upholds the cause of the oppressed and gives food to the hungry. The LORD sets prisoners free,</ab>
          <ab n="8">the LORD gives sight to the blind, the LORD lifts up those who are bowed down, the LORD loves the righteous.</ab>
          <ab n="9">The LORD watches over the alien and sustains the fatherless and the widow, but he frustrates the ways of the wicked.</ab>
          <ab n="10">The LORD reigns forever, your God, O Zion, for all generations. Praise the LORD.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="147">
          <ab n="1">Praise the LORD. How good it is to sing praises to our God, how pleasant and fitting to praise him!</ab>
          <ab n="2">The LORD builds up Jerusalem; he gathers the exiles of Israel.</ab>
          <ab n="3">He heals the brokenhearted and binds up their wounds.</ab>
          <ab n="4">He determines the number of the stars and calls them each by name.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Great is our Lord and mighty in power; his understanding has no limit.</ab>
          <ab n="6">The LORD sustains the humble but casts the wicked to the ground.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Sing to the LORD with thanksgiving; make music to our God on the harp.</ab>
          <ab n="8">He covers the sky with clouds; he supplies the earth with rain and makes grass grow on the hills.</ab>
          <ab n="9">He provides food for the cattle and for the young ravens when they call.</ab>
          <ab n="10">His pleasure is not in the strength of the horse, nor his delight in the legs of a man;</ab>
          <ab n="11">the LORD delights in those who fear him, who put their hope in his unfailing love.</ab>
          <ab n="12">Extol the LORD, O Jerusalem; praise your God, O Zion,</ab>
          <ab n="13">for he strengthens the bars of your gates and blesses your people within you.</ab>
          <ab n="14">He grants peace to your borders and satisfies you with the finest of wheat.</ab>
          <ab n="15">He sends his command to the earth; his word runs swiftly.</ab>
          <ab n="16">He spreads the snow like wool and scatters the frost like ashes.</ab>
          <ab n="17">He hurls down his hail like pebbles. Who can withstand his icy blast?</ab>
          <ab n="18">He sends his word and melts them; he stirs up his breezes, and the waters flow.</ab>
          <ab n="19">He has revealed his word to Jacob, his laws and decrees to Israel.</ab>
          <ab n="20">He has done this for no other nation; they do not know his laws. Praise the LORD.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="148">
          <ab n="1">Praise the LORD. Praise the LORD from the heavens, praise him in the heights above.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Praise him, all his angels, praise him, all his heavenly hosts.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Praise him, sun and moon, praise him, all you shining stars.</ab>
          <ab n="4">Praise him, you highest heavens and you waters above the skies.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Let them praise the name of the LORD, for he commanded and they were created.</ab>
          <ab n="6">He set them in place for ever and ever; he gave a decree that will never pass away.</ab>
          <ab n="7">Praise the LORD from the earth, you great sea creatures and all ocean depths,</ab>
          <ab n="8">lightning and hail, snow and clouds, stormy winds that do his bidding,</ab>
          <ab n="9">you mountains and all hills, fruit trees and all cedars,</ab>
          <ab n="10">wild animals and all cattle, small creatures and flying birds,</ab>
          <ab n="11">kings of the earth and all nations, you princes and all rulers on earth,</ab>
          <ab n="12">young men and maidens, old men and children.</ab>
          <ab n="13">Let them praise the name of the LORD, for his name alone is exalted; his splendor is above the earth and the heavens.</ab>
          <ab n="14">He has raised up for his people a horn, the praise of all his saints, of Israel, the people close to his heart. Praise the LORD.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="149">
          <ab n="1">Praise the LORD. Sing to the LORD a new song, his praise in the assembly of the saints.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Let Israel rejoice in their Maker; let the people of Zion be glad in their King.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Let them praise his name with dancing and make music to him with tambourine and harp.</ab>
          <ab n="4">For the LORD takes delight in his people; he crowns the humble with salvation.</ab>
          <ab n="5">Let the saints rejoice in this honor and sing for joy on their beds.</ab>
          <ab n="6">May the praise of God be in their mouths and a double-edged sword in their hands,</ab>
          <ab n="7">to inflict vengeance on the nations and punishment on the peoples,</ab>
          <ab n="8">to bind their kings with fetters, their nobles with shackles of iron,</ab>
          <ab n="9">to carry out the sentence written against them. This is the glory of all his saints. Praise the LORD.</ab>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="150">
          <ab n="1">Praise the LORD. Praise God in his sanctuary; praise him in his mighty heavens.</ab>
          <ab n="2">Praise him for his acts of power; praise him for his surpassing greatness.</ab>
          <ab n="3">Praise him with the sounding of the trumpet, praise him with the harp and lyre,</ab>
          <ab n="4">praise him with tambourine and dancing, praise him with the strings and flute,</ab>
          <ab n="5">praise him with the clash of cymbals, praise him with resounding cymbals.</ab>
          <ab n="6">Let everything that has breath praise the LORD. Praise the LORD.</ab>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
