<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="PROV" style="id"/>
  <chapter number="1" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>The proverbs of Solomon, son of David, king of Israel:
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>To know wisdom and instruction, to understand words of insight,
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>to receive instruction in wise dealing, in righteousness, justice, and equity;
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>to give prudence to the simple, knowledge and discretion to the youth-
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>Let the wise hear and increase in learning, and the one who understands obtain guidance,
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>to understand a proverb and a saying, the words of the wise and their riddles.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>The fear of the LORD is the beginning of knowledge; fools despise wisdom and instruction.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>Hear, my son, your father's instruction, and forsake not your mother's teaching,
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>for they are a graceful garland for your head and pendants for your neck.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>My son, if sinners entice you, do not consent.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>If they say, "Come with us, let us lie in wait for blood; let us ambush the innocent without reason;
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>like Sheol let us swallow them alive, and whole, like those who go down to the pit;
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>we shall find all precious goods, we shall fill our houses with plunder;
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>throw in your lot among us; we will all have one purse"-
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>my son, do not walk in the way with them; hold back your foot from their paths,
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>for their feet run to evil, and they make haste to shed blood.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>For in vain is a net spread in the sight of any bird,
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>but these men lie in wait for their own blood; they set an ambush for their own lives.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>Such are the ways of everyone who is greedy for unjust gain; it takes away the life of its possessors.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>Wisdom cries aloud in the street, in the markets she raises her voice;
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>at the head of the noisy streets she cries out; at the entrance of the city gates she speaks:
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>"How long, O simple ones, will you love being simple? How long will scoffers delight in their scoffing and fools hate knowledge?
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>If you turn at my reproof, behold, I will pour out my spirit to you; I will make my words known to you.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>Because I have called and you refused to listen, have stretched out my hand and no one has heeded,
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>because you have ignored all my counsel and would have none of my reproof,
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>I also will laugh at your calamity; I will mock when terror strikes you,
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>when terror strikes you like a storm and your calamity comes like a whirlwind, when distress and anguish come upon you.
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>Then they will call upon me, but I will not answer; they will seek me diligently but will not find me.
    <verse number="29" style="v"/>Because they hated knowledge and did not choose the fear of the LORD,
    <verse number="30" style="v"/>would have none of my counsel and despised all my reproof,
    <verse number="31" style="v"/>therefore they shall eat the fruit of their way, and have their fill of their own devices.
    <verse number="32" style="v"/>For the simple are killed by their turning away, and the complacency of fools destroys them;
    <verse number="33" style="v"/>but whoever listens to me will dwell secure and will be at ease, without dread of disaster."
  </para>
  <chapter number="2" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>My son, if you receive my words and treasure up my commandments with you,
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>making your ear attentive to wisdom and inclining your heart to understanding;
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>yes, if you call out for insight and raise your voice for understanding,
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>if you seek it like silver and search for it as for hidden treasures,
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>then you will understand the fear of the LORD and find the knowledge of God.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>For the LORD gives wisdom; from his mouth come knowledge and understanding;
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>he stores up sound wisdom for the upright; he is a shield to those who walk in integrity,
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>guarding the paths of justice and watching over the way of his saints.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>Then you will understand righteousness and justice and equity, every good path;
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>for wisdom will come into your heart, and knowledge will be pleasant to your soul;
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>discretion will watch over you, understanding will guard you,
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>delivering you from the way of evil, from men of perverted speech,
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>who forsake the paths of uprightness to walk in the ways of darkness,
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>who rejoice in doing evil and delight in the perverseness of evil,
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>men whose paths are crooked, and who are devious in their ways.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>So you will be delivered from the forbidden woman, from the adulteress with her smooth words,
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>who forsakes the companion of her youth and forgets the covenant of her God;
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>for her house sinks down to death, and her paths to the departed;
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>none who go to her come back, nor do they regain the paths of life.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>So you will walk in the way of the good and keep to the paths of the righteous.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>For the upright will inhabit the land, and those with integrity will remain in it,
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>but the wicked will be cut off from the land, and the treacherous will be rooted out of it.
  </para>
  <chapter number="3" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>My son, do not forget my teaching, but let your heart keep my commandments,
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>for length of days and years of life and peace they will add to you.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>Let not steadfast love and faithfulness forsake you; bind them around your neck; write them on the tablet of your heart.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>So you will find favor and good success in the sight of God and man.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>Trust in the LORD with all your heart, and do not lean on your own understanding.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>In all your ways acknowledge him, and he will make straight your paths.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>Be not wise in your own eyes; fear the LORD, and turn away from evil.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>It will be healing to your flesh and refreshment to your bones.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>Honor the LORD with your wealth and with the firstfruits of all your produce;
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>then your barns will be filled with plenty, and your vats will be bursting with wine.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>My son, do not despise the LORD's discipline or be weary of his reproof,
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>for the LORD reproves him whom he loves, as a father the son in whom he delights.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>Blessed is the one who finds wisdom, and the one who gets understanding,
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>for the gain from her is better than gain from silver and her profit better than gold.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>She is more precious than jewels, and nothing you desire can compare with her.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>Long life is in her right hand; in her left hand are riches and honor.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>Her ways are ways of pleasantness, and all her paths are peace.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>She is a tree of life to those who lay hold of her; those who hold her fast are called blessed.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>The LORD by wisdom founded the earth; by understanding he established the heavens;
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>by his knowledge the deeps broke open, and the clouds drop down the dew.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>My son, do not lose sight of these- keep sound wisdom and discretion,
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>and they will be life for your soul and adornment for your neck.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>Then you will walk on your way securely, and your foot will not stumble.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>If you lie down, you will not be afraid; when you lie down, your sleep will be sweet.
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>Do not be afraid of sudden terror or of the ruin of the wicked, when it comes,
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>for the LORD will be your confidence and will keep your foot from being caught.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>Do not withhold good from those to whom it is due, when it is in your power to do it.
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>Do not say to your neighbor, "Go, and come again, tomorrow I will give it"- when you have it with you.
    <verse number="29" style="v"/>Do not plan evil against your neighbor, who dwells trustingly beside you.
    <verse number="30" style="v"/>Do not contend with a man for no reason, when he has done you no harm.
    <verse number="31" style="v"/>Do not envy a man of violence and do not choose any of his ways,
    <verse number="32" style="v"/>for the devious person is an abomination to the LORD, but the upright are in his confidence.
    <verse number="33" style="v"/>The LORD's curse is on the house of the wicked, but he blesses the dwelling of the righteous.
    <verse number="34" style="v"/>Toward the scorners he is scornful, but to the humble he gives favor.
    <verse number="35" style="v"/>The wise will inherit honor, but fools get disgrace.
  </para>
  <chapter number="4" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>Hear, O sons, a father's instruction, and be attentive, that you may gain insight,
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>for I give you good precepts; do not forsake my teaching.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>When I was a son with my father, tender, the only one in the sight of my mother,
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>he taught me and said to me, "Let your heart hold fast my words; keep my commandments, and live.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>Get wisdom; get insight; do not forget, and do not turn away from the words of my mouth.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>Do not forsake her, and she will keep you; love her, and she will guard you.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>The beginning of wisdom is this: Get wisdom, and whatever you get, get insight.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>Prize her highly, and she will exalt you; she will honor you if you embrace her.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>She will place on your head a graceful garland; she will bestow on you a beautiful crown."
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>Hear, my son, and accept my words, that the years of your life may be many.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>I have taught you the way of wisdom; I have led you in the paths of uprightness.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>When you walk, your step will not be hampered, and if you run, you will not stumble.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>Keep hold of instruction; do not let go; guard her, for she is your life.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>Do not enter the path of the wicked, and do not walk in the way of the evil.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>Avoid it; do not go on it; turn away from it and pass on.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>For they cannot sleep unless they have done wrong; they are robbed of sleep unless they have made someone stumble.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>For they eat the bread of wickedness and drink the wine of violence.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>But the path of the righteous is like the light of dawn, which shines brighter and brighter until full day.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>The way of the wicked is like deep darkness; they do not know over what they stumble.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>My son, be attentive to my words; incline your ear to my sayings.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>Let them not escape from your sight; keep them within your heart.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>For they are life to those who find them, and healing to all their flesh.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>Keep your heart with all vigilance, for from it flow the springs of life.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>Put away from you crooked speech, and put devious talk far from you.
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>Let your eyes look directly forward, and your gaze be straight before you.
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>Ponder the path of your feet; then all your ways will be sure.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>Do not swerve to the right or to the left; turn your foot away from evil.
  </para>
  <chapter number="5" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>My son, be attentive to my wisdom; incline your ear to my understanding,
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>that you may keep discretion, and your lips may guard knowledge.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>For the lips of a forbidden woman drip honey, and her speech is smoother than oil,
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>but in the end she is bitter as wormwood, sharp as a two-edged sword.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>Her feet go down to death; her steps follow the path to Sheol;
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>she does not ponder the path of life; her ways wander, and she does not know it.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>And now, O sons, listen to me, and do not depart from the words of my mouth.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>Keep your way far from her, and do not go near the door of her house,
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>lest you give your honor to others and your years to the merciless,
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>lest strangers take their fill of your strength, and your labors go to the house of a foreigner,
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>and at the end of your life you groan, when your flesh and body are consumed,
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>and you say, "How I hated discipline, and my heart despised reproof!
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>I did not listen to the voice of my teachers or incline my ear to my instructors.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>I am at the brink of utter ruin in the assembled congregation."
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>Drink water from your own cistern, flowing water from your own well.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>Should your springs be scattered abroad, streams of water in the streets?
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>Let them be for yourself alone, and not for strangers with you.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>Let your fountain be blessed, and rejoice in the wife of your youth,
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>a lovely deer, a graceful doe. Let her breasts fill you at all times with delight; be intoxicated always in her love.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>Why should you be intoxicated, my son, with a forbidden woman and embrace the bosom of an adulteress?
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>For a man's ways are before the eyes of the LORD, and he ponders all his paths.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>The iniquities of the wicked ensnare him, and he is held fast in the cords of his sin.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>He dies for lack of discipline, and because of his great folly he is led astray.
  </para>
  <chapter number="6" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>My son, if you have put up security for your neighbor, have given your pledge for a stranger,
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>if you are snared in the words of your mouth, caught in the words of your mouth,
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>then do this, my son, and save yourself, for you have come into the hand of your neighbor: go, hasten, and plead urgently with your neighbor.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>Give your eyes no sleep and your eyelids no slumber;
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>save yourself like a gazelle from the hand of the hunter, like a bird from the hand of the fowler.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>Go to the ant, O sluggard; consider her ways, and be wise.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>Without having any chief, officer, or ruler,
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>she prepares her bread in summer and gathers her food in harvest.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>How long will you lie there, O sluggard? When will you arise from your sleep?
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>A little sleep, a little slumber, a little folding of the hands to rest,
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>and poverty will come upon you like a robber, and want like an armed man.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>A worthless person, a wicked man, goes about with crooked speech,
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>winks with his eyes, signals with his feet, points with his finger,
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>with perverted heart devises evil, continually sowing discord;
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>therefore calamity will come upon him suddenly; in a moment he will be broken beyond healing.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>There are six things that the LORD hates, seven that are an abomination to him:
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>haughty eyes, a lying tongue, and hands that shed innocent blood,
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>a heart that devises wicked plans, feet that make haste to run to evil,
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>a false witness who breathes out lies, and one who sows discord among brothers.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>My son, keep your father's commandment, and forsake not your mother's teaching.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>Bind them on your heart always; tie them around your neck.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>When you walk, they will lead you; when you lie down, they will watch over you; and when you awake, they will talk with you.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>For the commandment is a lamp and the teaching a light, and the reproofs of discipline are the way of life,
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>to preserve you from the evil woman, from the smooth tongue of the adulteress.
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>Do not desire her beauty in your heart, and do not let her capture you with her eyelashes;
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>for the price of a prostitute is only a loaf of bread, but a married woman hunts down a precious life.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>Can a man carry fire next to his chest and his clothes not be burned?
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>Or can one walk on hot coals and his feet not be scorched?
    <verse number="29" style="v"/>So is he who goes in to his neighbor's wife; none who touches her will go unpunished.
    <verse number="30" style="v"/>People do not despise a thief if he steals to satisfy his appetite when he is hungry,
    <verse number="31" style="v"/>but if he is caught, he will pay sevenfold; he will give all the goods of his house.
    <verse number="32" style="v"/>He who commits adultery lacks sense; he who does it destroys himself.
    <verse number="33" style="v"/>Wounds and dishonor will he get, and his disgrace will not be wiped away.
    <verse number="34" style="v"/>For jealousy makes a man furious, and he will not spare when he takes revenge.
    <verse number="35" style="v"/>He will accept no compensation; he will refuse though you multiply gifts.
  </para>
  <chapter number="7" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>My son, keep my wordsand treasure up my commandments with you;
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>keep my commandments and live; keep my teaching as the apple of your eye;
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>bind them on your fingers; write them on the tablet of your heart.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>Say to wisdom, "You are my sister," and call insight your intimate friend,
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>to keep you from the forbidden woman, from the adulteress with her smooth words.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>For at the window of my house I have looked out through my lattice,
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>and I have seen among the simple, I have perceived among the youths, a young man lacking sense,
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>passing along the street near her corner, taking the road to her house
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>in the twilight, in the evening, at the time of night and darkness.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>And behold, the woman meets him, dressed as a prostitute, wily of heart.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>She is loud and wayward; her feet do not stay at home;
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>now in the street, now in the market, and at every corner she lies in wait.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>She seizes him and kisses him, and with bold face she says to him,
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>"I had to offer sacrifices, and today I have paid my vows;
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>so now I have come out to meet you, to seek you eagerly, and I have found you.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>I have spread my couch with coverings, colored linens from Egyptian linen;
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>I have perfumed my bed with myrrh, aloes, and cinnamon.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>Come, let us take our fill of love till morning; let us delight ourselves with love.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>For my husband is not at home; he has gone on a long journey;
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>he took a bag of money with him; at full moon he will come home."
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>With much seductive speech she persuades him; with her smooth talk she compels him.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>All at once he follows her, as an ox goes to the slaughter, or as a stag is caught fast
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>till an arrow pierces its liver; as a bird rushes into a snare; he does not know that it will cost him his life.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>And now, O sons, listen to me, and be attentive to the words of my mouth.
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>Let not your heart turn aside to her ways; do not stray into her paths,
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>for many a victim has she laid low, and all her slain are a mighty throng.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>Her house is the way to Sheol, going down to the chambers of death.
  </para>
  <chapter number="8" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>Does not wisdom call?Does not understanding raise her voice?
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>On the heights beside the way, at the crossroads she takes her stand;
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>beside the gates in front of the town, at the entrance of the portals she cries aloud:
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>"To you, O men, I call, and my cry is to the children of man.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>O simple ones, learn prudence; O fools, learn sense.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>Hear, for I will speak noble things, and from my lips will come what is right,
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>for my mouth will utter truth; wickedness is an abomination to my lips.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>All the words of my mouth are righteous; there is nothing twisted or crooked in them.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>They are all straight to him who understands, and right to those who find knowledge.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>Take my instruction instead of silver, and knowledge rather than choice gold,
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>for wisdom is better than jewels, and all that you may desire cannot compare with her.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>"I, wisdom, dwell with prudence, and I find knowledge and discretion.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>The fear of the LORD is hatred of evil. Pride and arrogance and the way of evil and perverted speech I hate.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>I have counsel and sound wisdom; I have insight; I have strength.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>By me kings reign, and rulers decree what is just;
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>by me princes rule, and nobles, all who govern justly.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>I love those who love me, and those who seek me diligently find me.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>Riches and honor are with me, enduring wealth and righteousness.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>My fruit is better than gold, even fine gold, and my yield than choice silver.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>I walk in the way of righteousness, in the paths of justice,
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>granting an inheritance to those who love me, and filling their treasuries.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>"The LORD possessed me at the beginning of his work, the first of his acts of old.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>Ages ago I was set up, at the first, before the beginning of the earth.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>When there were no depths I was brought forth, when there were no springs abounding with water.
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>Before the mountains had been shaped, before the hills, I was brought forth,
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>before he had made the earth with its fields, or the first of the dust of the world.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>When he established the heavens, I was there; when he drew a circle on the face of the deep,
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>when he made firm the skies above, when he established the fountains of the deep,
    <verse number="29" style="v"/>when he assigned to the sea its limit, so that the waters might not transgress his command, when he marked out the foundations of the earth,
    <verse number="30" style="v"/>then I was beside him, like a master workman, and I was daily his delight, rejoicing before him always,
    <verse number="31" style="v"/>rejoicing in his inhabited world and delighting in the children of man.
    <verse number="32" style="v"/>"And now, O sons, listen to me: blessed are those who keep my ways.
    <verse number="33" style="v"/>Hear instruction and be wise, and do not neglect it.
    <verse number="34" style="v"/>Blessed is the one who listens to me, watching daily at my gates, waiting beside my doors.
    <verse number="35" style="v"/>For whoever finds me finds life and obtains favor from the LORD,
    <verse number="36" style="v"/>but he who fails to find me injures himself; all who hate me love death."
  </para>
  <chapter number="9" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>Wisdom has built her house;she has hewn her seven pillars.
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>She has slaughtered her beasts; she has mixed her wine; she has also set her table.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>She has sent out her young women to call from the highest places in the town,
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>"Whoever is simple, let him turn in here!" To him who lacks sense she says,
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>"Come, eat of my bread and drink of the wine I have mixed.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>Leave your simple ways, and live, and walk in the way of insight."
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>Whoever corrects a scoffer gets himself abuse, and he who reproves a wicked man incurs injury.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>Do not reprove a scoffer, or he will hate you; reprove a wise man, and he will love you.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>Give instruction to a wise man, and he will be still wiser; teach a righteous man, and he will increase in learning.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>The fear of the LORD is the beginning of wisdom, and the knowledge of the Holy One is insight.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>For by me your days will be multiplied, and years will be added to your life.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>If you are wise, you are wise for yourself; if you scoff, you alone will bear it.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>The woman Folly is loud; she is seductive and knows nothing.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>She sits at the door of her house; she takes a seat on the highest places of the town,
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>calling to those who pass by, who are going straight on their way,
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>"Whoever is simple, let him turn in here!" And to him who lacks sense she says,
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>"Stolen water is sweet, and bread eaten in secret is pleasant."
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>But he does not know that the dead are there, that her guests are in the depths of Sheol.
  </para>
  <chapter number="10" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>The proverbs of Solomon. A wise son makes a glad father, but a foolish son is a sorrow to his mother.
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>Treasures gained by wickedness do not profit, but righteousness delivers from death.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>The LORD does not let the righteous go hungry, but he thwarts the craving of the wicked.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>A slack hand causes poverty, but the hand of the diligent makes rich.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>He who gathers in summer is a prudent son, but he who sleeps in harvest is a son who brings shame.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>Blessings are on the head of the righteous, but the mouth of the wicked conceals violence.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>The memory of the righteous is a blessing, but the name of the wicked will rot.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>The wise of heart will receive commandments, but a babbling fool will come to ruin.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>Whoever walks in integrity walks securely, but he who makes his ways crooked will be found out.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>Whoever winks the eye causes trouble, but a babbling fool will come to ruin.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>The mouth of the righteous is a fountain of life, but the mouth of the wicked conceals violence.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>Hatred stirs up strife, but love covers all offenses.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>On the lips of him who has understanding, wisdom is found, but a rod is for the back of him who lacks sense.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>The wise lay up knowledge, but the mouth of a fool brings ruin near.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>A rich man's wealth is his strong city; the poverty of the poor is their ruin.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>The wage of the righteous leads to life, the gain of the wicked to sin.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>Whoever heeds instruction is on the path to life, but he who rejects reproof leads others astray.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>The one who conceals hatred has lying lips, and whoever utters slander is a fool.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>When words are many, transgression is not lacking, but whoever restrains his lips is prudent.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>The tongue of the righteous is choice silver; the heart of the wicked is of little worth.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>The lips of the righteous feed many, but fools die for lack of sense.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>The blessing of the LORD makes rich, and he adds no sorrow with it.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>Doing wrong is like a joke to a fool, but wisdom is pleasure to a man of understanding.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>What the wicked dreads will come upon him, but the desire of the righteous will be granted.
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>When the tempest passes, the wicked is no more, but the righteous is established forever.
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>Like vinegar to the teeth and smoke to the eyes, so is the sluggard to those who send him.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>The fear of the LORD prolongs life, but the years of the wicked will be short.
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>The hope of the righteous brings joy, but the expectation of the wicked will perish.
    <verse number="29" style="v"/>The way of the LORD is a stronghold to the blameless, but destruction to evildoers.
    <verse number="30" style="v"/>The righteous will never be removed, but the wicked will not dwell in the land.
    <verse number="31" style="v"/>The mouth of the righteous brings forth wisdom, but the perverse tongue will be cut off.
    <verse number="32" style="v"/>The lips of the righteous know what is acceptable, but the mouth of the wicked, what is perverse.
  </para>
  <chapter number="11" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>A false balance is an abomination to the LORD, but a just weight is his delight.
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>When pride comes, then comes disgrace, but with the humble is wisdom.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>The integrity of the upright guides them, but the crookedness of the treacherous destroys them.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>Riches do not profit in the day of wrath, but righteousness delivers from death.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>The righteousness of the blameless keeps his way straight, but the wicked falls by his own wickedness.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>The righteousness of the upright delivers them, but the treacherous are taken captive by their lust.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>When the wicked dies, his hope will perish, and the expectation of wealth perishes too.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>The righteous is delivered from trouble, and the wicked walks into it instead.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>With his mouth the godless man would destroy his neighbor, but by knowledge the righteous are delivered.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>When it goes well with the righteous, the city rejoices, and when the wicked perish there are shouts of gladness.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>By the blessing of the upright a city is exalted, but by the mouth of the wicked it is overthrown.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>Whoever belittles his neighbor lacks sense, but a man of understanding remains silent.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>Whoever goes about slandering reveals secrets, but he who is trustworthy in spirit keeps a thing covered.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>Where there is no guidance, a people falls, but in an abundance of counselors there is safety.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>Whoever puts up security for a stranger will surely suffer harm, but he who hates striking hands in pledge is secure.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>A gracious woman gets honor, and violent men get riches.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>A man who is kind benefits himself, but a cruel man hurts himself.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>The wicked earns deceptive wages, but one who sows righteousness gets a sure reward.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>Whoever is steadfast in righteousness will live, but he who pursues evil will die.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>Those of crooked heart are an abomination to the LORD, but those of blameless ways are his delight.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>Be assured, an evil person will not go unpunished, but the offspring of the righteous will be delivered.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>Like a gold ring in a pig's snout is a beautiful woman without discretion.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>The desire of the righteous ends only in good; the expectation of the wicked in wrath.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>One gives freely, yet grows all the richer; another withholds what he should give, and only suffers want.
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>Whoever brings blessing will be enriched, and one who waters will himself be watered.
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>The people curse him who holds back grain, but a blessing is on the head of him who sells it.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>Whoever diligently seeks good seeks favor, but evil comes to him who searches for it.
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>Whoever trusts in his riches will fall, but the righteous will flourish like a green leaf.
    <verse number="29" style="v"/>Whoever troubles his own household will inherit the wind, and the fool will be servant to the wise of heart.
    <verse number="30" style="v"/>The fruit of the righteous is a tree of life, and whoever captures souls is wise.
    <verse number="31" style="v"/>If the righteous is repaid on earth, how much more the wicked and the sinner!
  </para>
  <chapter number="12" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>Whoever loves discipline loves knowledge, but he who hates reproof is stupid.
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>A good man obtains favor from the LORD, but a man of evil devices he condemns.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>No one is established by wickedness, but the root of the righteous will never be moved.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>An excellent wife is the crown of her husband, but she who brings shame is like rottenness in his bones.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>The thoughts of the righteous are just; the counsels of the wicked are deceitful.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>The words of the wicked lie in wait for blood, but the mouth of the upright delivers them.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>The wicked are overthrown and are no more, but the house of the righteous will stand.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>A man is commended according to his good sense, but one of twisted mind is despised.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>Better to be lowly and have a servant than to play the great man and lack bread.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>Whoever is righteous has regard for the life of his beast, but the mercy of the wicked is cruel.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>Whoever works his land will have plenty of bread, but he who follows worthless pursuits lacks sense.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>Whoever is wicked covets the spoil of evildoers, but the root of the righteous bears fruit.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>An evil man is ensnared by the transgression of his lips, but the righteous escapes from trouble.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>From the fruit of his mouth a man is satisfied with good, and the work of a man's hand comes back to him.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>The way of a fool is right in his own eyes, but a wise man listens to advice.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>The vexation of a fool is known at once, but the prudent ignores an insult.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>Whoever speaks the truth gives honest evidence, but a false witness utters deceit.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>There is one whose rash words are like sword thrusts, but the tongue of the wise brings healing.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>Truthful lips endure forever, but a lying tongue is but for a moment.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>Deceit is in the heart of those who devise evil, but those who plan peace have joy.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>No ill befalls the righteous, but the wicked are filled with trouble.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>Lying lips are an abomination to the LORD, but those who act faithfully are his delight.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>A prudent man conceals knowledge, but the heart of fools proclaims folly.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>The hand of the diligent will rule, while the slothful will be put to forced labor.
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>Anxiety in a man's heart weighs him down, but a good word makes him glad.
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>One who is righteous is a guide to his neighbor, but the way of the wicked leads them astray.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>Whoever is slothful will not roast his game, but the diligent man will get precious wealth.
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>In the path of righteousness is life, and in its pathway there is no death.
  </para>
  <chapter number="13" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>A wise son hears his father's instruction, but a scoffer does not listen to rebuke.
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>From the fruit of his mouth a man eats what is good, but the desire of the treacherous is for violence.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>Whoever guards his mouth preserves his life; he who opens wide his lips comes to ruin.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>The soul of the sluggard craves and gets nothing, while the soul of the diligent is richly supplied.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>The righteous hates falsehood, but the wicked brings shame and disgrace.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>Righteousness guards him whose way is blameless, but sin overthrows the wicked.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>One pretends to be rich, yet has nothing; another pretends to be poor, yet has great wealth.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>The ransom of a man's life is his wealth, but a poor man hears no threat.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>The light of the righteous rejoices, but the lamp of the wicked will be put out.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>By insolence comes nothing but strife, but with those who take advice is wisdom.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>Wealth gained hastily will dwindle, but whoever gathers little by little will increase it.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>Hope deferred makes the heart sick, but a desire fulfilled is a tree of life.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>Whoever despises the word brings destruction on himself, but he who reveres the commandment will be rewarded.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>The teaching of the wise is a fountain of life, that one may turn away from the snares of death.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>Good sense wins favor, but the way of the treacherous is their ruin.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>In everything the prudent acts with knowledge, but a fool flaunts his folly.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>A wicked messenger falls into trouble, but a faithful envoy brings healing.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>Poverty and disgrace come to him who ignores instruction, but whoever heeds reproof is honored.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>A desire fulfilled is sweet to the soul, but to turn away from evil is an abomination to fools.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>Whoever walks with the wise becomes wise, but the companion of fools will suffer harm.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>Disaster pursues sinners, but the righteous are rewarded with good.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>A good man leaves an inheritance to his children's children, but the sinner's wealth is laid up for the righteous.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>The fallow ground of the poor would yield much food, but it is swept away through injustice.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>Whoever spares the rod hates his son, but he who loves him is diligent to discipline him.
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>The righteous has enough to satisfy his appetite, but the belly of the wicked suffers want.
  </para>
  <chapter number="14" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>The wisest of women builds her house, but folly with her own hands tears it down.
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>Whoever walks in uprightness fears the LORD, but he who is devious in his ways despises him.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>By the mouth of a fool comes a rod for his back, but the lips of the wise will preserve them.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>Where there are no oxen, the manger is clean, but abundant crops come by the strength of the ox.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>A faithful witness does not lie, but a false witness breathes out lies.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>A scoffer seeks wisdom in vain, but knowledge is easy for a man of understanding.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>Leave the presence of a fool, for there you do not meet words of knowledge.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>The wisdom of the prudent is to discern his way, but the folly of fools is deceiving.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>Fools mock at the guilt offering, but the upright enjoy acceptance.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>The heart knows its own bitterness, and no stranger shares its joy.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>The house of the wicked will be destroyed, but the tent of the upright will flourish.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>There is a way that seems right to a man, but its end is the way to death.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>Even in laughter the heart may ache, and the end of joy may be grief.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>The backslider in heart will be filled with the fruit of his ways, and a good man will be filled with the fruit of his ways.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>The simple believes everything, but the prudent gives thought to his steps.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>One who is wise is cautious and turns away from evil, but a fool is reckless and careless.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>A man of quick temper acts foolishly, and a man of evil devices is hated.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>The simple inherit folly, but the prudent are crowned with knowledge.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>The evil bow down before the good, the wicked at the gates of the righteous.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>The poor is disliked even by his neighbor, but the rich has many friends.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>Whoever despises his neighbor is a sinner, but blessed is he who is generous to the poor.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>Do they not go astray who devise evil? Those who devise good meet steadfast love and faithfulness.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>In all toil there is profit, but mere talk tends only to poverty.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>The crown of the wise is their wealth, but the folly of fools brings folly.
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>A truthful witness saves lives, but one who breathes out lies is deceitful.
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>In the fear of the LORD one has strong confidence, and his children will have a refuge.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>The fear of the LORD is a fountain of life, that one may turn away from the snares of death.
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>In a multitude of people is the glory of a king, but without people a prince is ruined.
    <verse number="29" style="v"/>Whoever is slow to anger has great understanding, but he who has a hasty temper exalts folly.
    <verse number="30" style="v"/>A tranquil heart gives life to the flesh, but envy makes the bones rot.
    <verse number="31" style="v"/>Whoever oppresses a poor man insults his Maker, but he who is generous to the needy honors him.
    <verse number="32" style="v"/>The wicked is overthrown through his evildoing, but the righteous finds refuge in his death.
    <verse number="33" style="v"/>Wisdom rests in the heart of a man of understanding, but it makes itself known even in the midst of fools.
    <verse number="34" style="v"/>Righteousness exalts a nation, but sin is a reproach to any people.
    <verse number="35" style="v"/>A servant who deals wisely has the king's favor, but his wrath falls on one who acts shamefully.
  </para>
  <chapter number="15" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>A soft answer turns away wrath, but a harsh word stirs up anger.
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>The tongue of the wise commends knowledge, but the mouths of fools pour out folly.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>The eyes of the LORD are in every place, keeping watch on the evil and the good.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>A gentle tongue is a tree of life, but perverseness in it breaks the spirit.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>A fool despises his father's instruction, but whoever heeds reproof is prudent.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>In the house of the righteous there is much treasure, but trouble befalls the income of the wicked.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>The lips of the wise spread knowledge; not so the hearts of fools.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>The sacrifice of the wicked is an abomination to the LORD, but the prayer of the upright is acceptable to him.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>The way of the wicked is an abomination to the LORD, but he loves him who pursues righteousness.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>There is severe discipline for him who forsakes the way; whoever hates reproof will die.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>Sheol and Abaddon lie open before the LORD; how much more the hearts of the children of man!
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>A scoffer does not like to be reproved; he will not go to the wise.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>A glad heart makes a cheerful face, but by sorrow of heart the spirit is crushed.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>The heart of him who has understanding seeks knowledge, but the mouths of fools feed on folly.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>All the days of the afflicted are evil, but the cheerful of heart has a continual feast.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>Better is a little with the fear of the LORD than great treasure and trouble with it.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>Better is a dinner of herbs where love is than a fattened ox and hatred with it.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>A hot-tempered man stirs up strife, but he who is slow to anger quiets contention.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>The way of a sluggard is like a hedge of thorns, but the path of the upright is a level highway.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>A wise son makes a glad father, but a foolish man despises his mother.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>Folly is a joy to him who lacks sense, but a man of understanding walks straight ahead.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>Without counsel plans fail, but with many advisers they succeed.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>To make an apt answer is a joy to a man, and a word in season, how good it is!
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>The path of life leads upward for the prudent, that he may turn away from Sheol beneath.
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>The LORD tears down the house of the proud but maintains the widow's boundaries.
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>The thoughts of the wicked are an abomination to the LORD, but gracious words are pure.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>Whoever is greedy for unjust gain troubles his own household, but he who hates bribes will live.
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>The heart of the righteous ponders how to answer, but the mouth of the wicked pours out evil things.
    <verse number="29" style="v"/>The LORD is far from the wicked, but he hears the prayer of the righteous.
    <verse number="30" style="v"/>The light of the eyes rejoices the heart, and good news refreshes the bones.
    <verse number="31" style="v"/>The ear that listens to life-giving reproof will dwell among the wise.
    <verse number="32" style="v"/>Whoever ignores instruction despises himself, but he who listens to reproof gains intelligence.
    <verse number="33" style="v"/>The fear of the LORD is instruction in wisdom, and humility comes before honor.
  </para>
  <chapter number="16" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>The plans of the heart belong to man, but the answer of the tongue is from the LORD.
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>All the ways of a man are pure in his own eyes, but the LORD weighs the spirit.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>Commit your work to the LORD, and your plans will be established.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>The LORD has made everything for its purpose, even the wicked for the day of trouble.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>Everyone who is arrogant in heart is an abomination to the LORD; be assured, he will not go unpunished.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>By steadfast love and faithfulness iniquity is atoned for, and by the fear of the LORD one turns away from evil.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>When a man's ways please the LORD, he makes even his enemies to be at peace with him.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>Better is a little with righteousness than great revenues with injustice.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>The heart of man plans his way, but the LORD establishes his steps.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>An oracle is on the lips of a king; his mouth does not sin in judgment.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>A just balance and scales are the LORD's; all the weights in the bag are his work.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>It is an abomination to kings to do evil, for the throne is established by righteousness.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>Righteous lips are the delight of a king, and he loves him who speaks what is right.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>A king's wrath is a messenger of death, and a wise man will appease it.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>In the light of a king's face there is life, and his favor is like the clouds that bring the spring rain.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>How much better to get wisdom than gold! To get understanding is to be chosen rather than silver.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>The highway of the upright turns aside from evil; whoever guards his way preserves his life.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>Pride goes before destruction, and a haughty spirit before a fall.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>It is better to be of a lowly spirit with the poor than to divide the spoil with the proud.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>Whoever gives thought to the word will discover good, and blessed is he who trusts in the LORD.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>The wise of heart is called discerning, and sweetness of speech increases persuasiveness.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>Good sense is a fountain of life to him who has it, but the instruction of fools is folly.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>The heart of the wise makes his speech judicious and adds persuasiveness to his lips.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>Gracious words are like a honeycomb, sweetness to the soul and health to the body.
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>There is a way that seems right to a man, but its end is the way to death.
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>A worker's appetite works for him; his mouth urges him on.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>A worthless man plots evil, and his speech is like a scorching fire.
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>A dishonest man spreads strife, and a whisperer separates close friends.
    <verse number="29" style="v"/>A man of violence entices his neighbor and leads him in a way that is not good.
    <verse number="30" style="v"/>Whoever winks his eyes plans dishonest things; he who purses his lips brings evil to pass.
    <verse number="31" style="v"/>Gray hair is a crown of glory; it is gained in a righteous life.
    <verse number="32" style="v"/>Whoever is slow to anger is better than the mighty, and he who rules his spirit than he who takes a city.
    <verse number="33" style="v"/>The lot is cast into the lap, but its every decision is from the LORD.
  </para>
  <chapter number="17" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>Better is a dry morsel with quiet than a house full of feasting with strife.
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>A servant who deals wisely will rule over a son who acts shamefully and will share the inheritance as one of the brothers.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>The crucible is for silver, and the furnace is for gold, and the LORD tests hearts.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>An evildoer listens to wicked lips, and a liar gives ear to a mischievous tongue.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>Whoever mocks the poor insults his Maker; he who is glad at calamity will not go unpunished.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>Grandchildren are the crown of the aged, and the glory of children is their fathers.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>Fine speech is not becoming to a fool; still less is false speech to a prince.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>A bribe is like a magic stone in the eyes of the one who gives it; wherever he turns he prospers.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>Whoever covers an offense seeks love, but he who repeats a matter separates close friends.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>A rebuke goes deeper into a man of understanding than a hundred blows into a fool.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>An evil man seeks only rebellion, and a cruel messenger will be sent against him.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>Let a man meet a she-bear robbed of her cubs rather than a fool in his folly.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>If anyone returns evil for good, evil will not depart from his house.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>The beginning of strife is like letting out water, so quit before the quarrel breaks out.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>He who justifies the wicked and he who condemns the righteous are both alike an abomination to the LORD.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>Why should a fool have money in his hand to buy wisdom when he has no sense?
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>A friend loves at all times, and a brother is born for adversity.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>One who lacks sense gives a pledge and puts up security in the presence of his neighbor.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>Whoever loves transgression loves strife; he who makes his door high seeks destruction.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>A man of crooked heart does not discover good, and one with a dishonest tongue falls into calamity.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>He who sires a fool gets himself sorrow, and the father of a fool has no joy.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>A joyful heart is good medicine, but a crushed spirit dries up the bones.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>The wicked accepts a bribe in secret to pervert the ways of justice.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>The discerning sets his face toward wisdom, but the eyes of a fool are on the ends of the earth.
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>A foolish son is a grief to his father and bitterness to her who bore him.
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>To impose a fine on a righteous man is not good, nor to strike the noble for their uprightness.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>Whoever restrains his words has knowledge, and he who has a cool spirit is a man of understanding.
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>Even a fool who keeps silent is considered wise; when he closes his lips, he is deemed intelligent.
  </para>
  <chapter number="18" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>Whoever isolates himself seeks his own desire; he breaks out against all sound judgment.
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>A fool takes no pleasure in understanding, but only in expressing his opinion.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>When wickedness comes, contempt comes also, and with dishonor comes disgrace.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>The words of a man's mouth are deep waters; the fountain of wisdom is a bubbling brook.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>It is not good to be partial to the wicked or to deprive the righteous of justice.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>A fool's lips walk into a fight, and his mouth invites a beating.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>A fool's mouth is his ruin, and his lips are a snare to his soul.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>The words of a whisperer are like delicious morsels; they go down into the inner parts of the body.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>Whoever is slack in his work is a brother to him who destroys.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>The name of the LORD is a strong tower; the righteous man runs into it and is safe.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>A rich man's wealth is his strong city, and like a high wall in his imagination.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>Before destruction a man's heart is haughty, but humility comes before honor.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>If one gives an answer before he hears, it is his folly and shame.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>A man's spirit will endure sickness, but a crushed spirit who can bear?
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>An intelligent heart acquires knowledge, and the ear of the wise seeks knowledge.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>A man's gift makes room for him and brings him before the great.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>The one who states his case first seems right, until the other comes and examines him.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>The lot puts an end to quarrels and decides between powerful contenders.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>A brother offended is more unyielding than a strong city, and quarreling is like the bars of a castle.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>From the fruit of a man's mouth his stomach is satisfied; he is satisfied by the yield of his lips.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>Death and life are in the power of the tongue, and those who love it will eat its fruits.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>He who finds a wife finds a good thing and obtains favor from the LORD.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>The poor use entreaties, but the rich answer roughly.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>A man of many companions may come to ruin, but there is a friend who sticks closer than a brother.
  </para>
  <chapter number="19" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>Better is a poor person who walks in his integrity than one who is crooked in speech and is a fool.
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>Desire without knowledge is not good, and whoever makes haste with his feet misses his way.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>When a man's folly brings his way to ruin, his heart rages against the LORD.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>Wealth brings many new friends, but a poor man is deserted by his friend.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>A false witness will not go unpunished, and he who breathes out lies will not escape.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>Many seek the favor of a generous man, and everyone is a friend to a man who gives gifts.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>All a poor man's brothers hate him; how much more do his friends go far from him! He pursues them with words, but does not have them.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>Whoever gets sense loves his own soul; he who keeps understanding will discover good.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>A false witness will not go unpunished, and he who breathes out lies will perish.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>It is not fitting for a fool to live in luxury, much less for a slave to rule over princes.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>Good sense makes one slow to anger, and it is his glory to overlook an offense.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>A king's wrath is like the growling of a lion, but his favor is like dew on the grass.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>A foolish son is ruin to his father, and a wife's quarreling is a continual dripping of rain.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>House and wealth are inherited from fathers, but a prudent wife is from the LORD.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>Slothfulness casts into a deep sleep, and an idle person will suffer hunger.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>Whoever keeps the commandment keeps his life; he who despises his ways will die.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>Whoever is generous to the poor lends to the LORD, and he will repay him for his deed.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>Discipline your son, for there is hope; do not set your heart on putting him to death.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>A man of great wrath will pay the penalty, for if you deliver him, you will only have to do it again.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>Listen to advice and accept instruction, that you may gain wisdom in the future.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>Many are the plans in the mind of a man, but it is the purpose of the LORD that will stand.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>What is desired in a man is steadfast love, and a poor man is better than a liar.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>The fear of the LORD leads to life, and whoever has it rests satisfied; he will not be visited by harm.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>The sluggard buries his hand in the dish and will not even bring it back to his mouth.
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>Strike a scoffer, and the simple will learn prudence; reprove a man of understanding, and he will gain knowledge.
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>He who does violence to his father and chases away his mother is a son who brings shame and reproach.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>Cease to hear instruction, my son, and you will stray from the words of knowledge.
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>A worthless witness mocks at justice, and the mouth of the wicked devours iniquity.
    <verse number="29" style="v"/>Condemnation is ready for scoffers, and beating for the backs of fools.
  </para>
  <chapter number="20" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>Wine is a mocker, strong drink a brawler, and whoever is led astray by it is not wise.
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>The terror of a king is like the growling of a lion; whoever provokes him to anger forfeits his life.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>It is an honor for a man to keep aloof from strife, but every fool will be quarreling.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>The sluggard does not plow in the autumn; he will seek at harvest and have nothing.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>The purpose in a man's heart is like deep water, but a man of understanding will draw it out.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>Many a man proclaims his own steadfast love, but a faithful man who can find?
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>The righteous who walks in his integrity- blessed are his children after him!
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>A king who sits on the throne of judgment winnows all evil with his eyes.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>Who can say, "I have made my heart pure; I am clean from my sin"?
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>Unequal weights and unequal measures are both alike an abomination to the LORD.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>Even a child makes himself known by his acts, by whether his conduct is pure and upright.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>The hearing ear and the seeing eye, the LORD has made them both.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>Love not sleep, lest you come to poverty; open your eyes, and you will have plenty of bread.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>"Bad, Bad," says the buyer, but when he goes away, then he boasts.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>There is gold and abundance of costly stones, but the lips of knowledge are a precious jewel.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>Take a man's garment when he has put up security for a stranger, and hold it in pledge when he puts up security for foreigners.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>Bread gained by deceit is sweet to a man, but afterward his mouth will be full of gravel.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>Plans are established by counsel; by wise guidance wage war.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>Whoever goes about slandering reveals secrets; therefore do not associate with a simple babbler.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>If one curses his father or his mother, his lamp will be put out in utter darkness.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>An inheritance gained hastily in the beginning will not be blessed in the end.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>Do not say, "I will repay evil"; wait for the LORD, and he will deliver you.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>Unequal weights are an abomination to the LORD, and false scales are not good.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>A man's steps are from the LORD; how then can man understand his way?
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>It is a snare to say rashly, "It is holy," and to reflect only after making vows.
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>A wise king winnows the wicked and drives the wheel over them.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>The spirit of man is the lamp of the LORD, searching all his innermost parts.
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>Steadfast love and faithfulness preserve the king, and by steadfast love his throne is upheld.
    <verse number="29" style="v"/>The glory of young men is their strength, but the splendor of old men is their gray hair.
    <verse number="30" style="v"/>Blows that wound cleanse away evil; strokes make clean the innermost parts.
  </para>
  <chapter number="21" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>The king's heart is a stream of water in the hand of the LORD; he turns it wherever he will.
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>Every way of a man is right in his own eyes, but the LORD weighs the heart.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>To do righteousness and justice is more acceptable to the LORD than sacrifice.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>Haughty eyes and a proud heart, the lamp of the wicked, are sin.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>The plans of the diligent lead surely to abundance, but everyone who is hasty comes only to poverty.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>The getting of treasures by a lying tongue is a fleeting vapor and a snare of death.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>The violence of the wicked will sweep them away, because they refuse to do what is just.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>The way of the guilty is crooked, but the conduct of the pure is upright.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>It is better to live in a corner of the housetop than in a house shared with a quarrelsome wife.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>The soul of the wicked desires evil; his neighbor finds no mercy in his eyes.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>When a scoffer is punished, the simple becomes wise; when a wise man is instructed, he gains knowledge.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>The Righteous One observes the house of the wicked; he throws the wicked down to ruin.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>Whoever closes his ear to the cry of the poor will himself call out and not be answered.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>A gift in secret averts anger, and a concealed bribe, strong wrath.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>When justice is done, it is a joy to the righteous but terror to evildoers.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>One who wanders from the way of good sense will rest in the assembly of the dead.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>Whoever loves pleasure will be a poor man; he who loves wine and oil will not be rich.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>The wicked is a ransom for the righteous, and the traitor for the upright.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>It is better to live in a desert land than with a quarrelsome and fretful woman.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>Precious treasure and oil are in a wise man's dwelling, but a foolish man devours it.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>Whoever pursues righteousness and kindness will find life, righteousness, and honor.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>A wise man scales the city of the mighty and brings down the stronghold in which they trust.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>Whoever keeps his mouth and his tongue keeps himself out of trouble.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>"Scoffer" is the name of the arrogant, haughty man who acts with arrogant pride.
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>The desire of the sluggard kills him, for his hands refuse to labor.
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>All day long he craves and craves, but the righteous gives and does not hold back.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>The sacrifice of the wicked is an abomination; how much more when he brings it with evil intent.
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>A false witness will perish, but the word of a man who hears will endure.
    <verse number="29" style="v"/>A wicked man puts on a bold face, but the upright gives thought to his ways.
    <verse number="30" style="v"/>No wisdom, no understanding, no counsel can avail against the LORD.
    <verse number="31" style="v"/>The horse is made ready for the day of battle, but the victory belongs to the LORD.
  </para>
  <chapter number="22" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>A good name is to be chosen rather than great riches, and favor is better than silver or gold.
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>The rich and the poor meet together; the LORD is the maker of them all.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>The prudent sees danger and hides himself, but the simple go on and suffer for it.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>The reward for humility and fear of the LORD is riches and honor and life.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>Thorns and snares are in the way of the crooked; whoever guards his soul will keep far from them.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>Train up a child in the way he should go; even when he is old he will not depart from it.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>The rich rules over the poor, and the borrower is the slave of the lender.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>Whoever sows injustice will reap calamity, and the rod of his fury will fail.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>Whoever has a bountiful eye will be blessed, for he shares his bread with the poor.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>Drive out a scoffer, and strife will go out, and quarreling and abuse will cease.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>He who loves purity of heart, and whose speech is gracious, will have the king as his friend.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>The eyes of the LORD keep watch over knowledge, but he overthrows the words of the traitor.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>The sluggard says, "There is a lion outside! I shall be killed in the streets!"
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>The mouth of forbidden women is a deep pit; he with whom the LORD is angry will fall into it.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>Folly is bound up in the heart of a child, but the rod of discipline drives it far from him.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>Whoever oppresses the poor to increase his own wealth, or gives to the rich, will only come to poverty.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>Incline your ear, and hear the words of the wise, and apply your heart to my knowledge,
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>for it will be pleasant if you keep them within you, if all of them are ready on your lips.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>That your trust may be in the LORD, I have made them known to you today, even to you.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>Have I not written for you thirty sayings of counsel and knowledge,
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>to make you know what is right and true, that you may give a true answer to those who sent you?
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>Do not rob the poor, because he is poor, or crush the afflicted at the gate,
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>for the LORD will plead their cause and rob of life those who rob them.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>Make no friendship with a man given to anger, nor go with a wrathful man,
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>lest you learn his ways and entangle yourself in a snare.
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>Be not one of those who give pledges, who put up security for debts.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>If you have nothing with which to pay, why should your bed be taken from under you?
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>Do not move the ancient landmark that your fathers have set.
    <verse number="29" style="v"/>Do you see a man skillful in his work? He will stand before kings; he will not stand before obscure men.
  </para>
  <chapter number="23" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>When you sit down to eat with a ruler, observe carefully what is before you,
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>and put a knife to your throat if you are given to appetite.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>Do not desire his delicacies, for they are deceptive food.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>Do not toil to acquire wealth; be discerning enough to desist.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>When your eyes light on it, it is gone, for suddenly it sprouts wings, flying like an eagle toward heaven.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>Do not eat the bread of a man who is stingy; do not desire his delicacies,
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>for he is like one who is inwardly calculating. "Eat and drink!" he says to you, but his heart is not with you.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>You will vomit up the morsels that you have eaten, and waste your pleasant words.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>Do not speak in the hearing of a fool, for he will despise the good sense of your words.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>Do not move an ancient landmark or enter the fields of the fatherless,
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>for their Redeemer is strong; he will plead their cause against you.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>Apply your heart to instruction and your ear to words of knowledge.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>Do not withhold discipline from a child; if you strike him with a rod, he will not die.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>If you strike him with the rod, you will save his soul from Sheol.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>My son, if your heart is wise, my heart too will be glad.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>My inmost being will exult when your lips speak what is right.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>Let not your heart envy sinners, but continue in the fear of the LORD all the day.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>Surely there is a future, and your hope will not be cut off.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>Hear, my son, and be wise, and direct your heart in the way.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>Be not among drunkards or among gluttonous eaters of meat,
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>for the drunkard and the glutton will come to poverty, and slumber will clothe them with rags.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>Listen to your father who gave you life, and do not despise your mother when she is old.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>Buy truth, and do not sell it; buy wisdom, instruction, and understanding.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>The father of the righteous will greatly rejoice; he who fathers a wise son will be glad in him.
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>Let your father and mother be glad; let her who bore you rejoice.
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>My son, give me your heart, and let your eyes observe my ways.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>For a prostitute is a deep pit; an adulteress is a narrow well.
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>She lies in wait like a robber and increases the traitors among mankind.
    <verse number="29" style="v"/>Who has woe? Who has sorrow? Who has strife? Who has complaining? Who has wounds without cause? Who has redness of eyes?
    <verse number="30" style="v"/>Those who tarry long over wine; those who go to try mixed wine.
    <verse number="31" style="v"/>Do not look at wine when it is red, when it sparkles in the cup and goes down smoothly.
    <verse number="32" style="v"/>In the end it bites like a serpent and stings like an adder.
    <verse number="33" style="v"/>Your eyes will see strange things, and your heart utter perverse things.
    <verse number="34" style="v"/>You will be like one who lies down in the midst of the sea, like one who lies on the top of a mast.
    <verse number="35" style="v"/>"They struck me," you will say, "but I was not hurt; they beat me, but I did not feel it. When shall I awake? I must have another drink."
  </para>
  <chapter number="24" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>Be not envious of evil men, nor desire to be with them,
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>for their hearts devise violence, and their lips talk of trouble.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>By wisdom a house is built, and by understanding it is established;
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>by knowledge the rooms are filled with all precious and pleasant riches.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>A wise man is full of strength, and a man of knowledge enhances his might,
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>for by wise guidance you can wage your war, and in abundance of counselors there is victory.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>Wisdom is too high for a fool; in the gate he does not open his mouth.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>Whoever plans to do evil will be called a schemer.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>The devising of folly is sin, and the scoffer is an abomination to mankind.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>If you faint in the day of adversity, your strength is small.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>Rescue those who are being taken away to death; hold back those who are stumbling to the slaughter.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>If you say, "Behold, we did not know this," does not he who weighs the heart perceive it? Does not he who keeps watch over your soul know it, and will he not repay man according to his work?
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>My son, eat honey, for it is good, and the drippings of the honeycomb are sweet to your taste.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>Know that wisdom is such to your soul; if you find it, there will be a future, and your hope will not be cut off.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>Lie not in wait as a wicked man against the dwelling of the righteous; do no violence to his home;
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>for the righteous falls seven times and rises again, but the wicked stumble in times of calamity.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>Do not rejoice when your enemy falls, and let not your heart be glad when he stumbles,
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>lest the LORD see it and be displeased, and turn away his anger from him.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>Fret not yourself because of evildoers, and be not envious of the wicked,
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>for the evil man has no future; the lamp of the wicked will be put out.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>My son, fear the LORD and the king, and do not join with those who do otherwise,
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>for disaster from them will rise suddenly, and who knows the ruin that will come from them both?
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>These also are sayings of the wise. Partiality in judging is not good.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>Whoever says to the wicked, "You are in the right," will be cursed by peoples, abhorred by nations,
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>but those who rebuke the wicked will have delight, and a good blessing will come upon them.
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>Whoever gives an honest answer kisses the lips.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>Prepare your work outside; get everything ready for yourself in the field, and after that build your house.
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>Be not a witness against your neighbor without cause, and do not deceive with your lips.
    <verse number="29" style="v"/>Do not say, "I will do to him as he has done to me; I will pay the man back for what he has done."
    <verse number="30" style="v"/>I passed by the field of a sluggard, by the vineyard of a man lacking sense,
    <verse number="31" style="v"/>and behold, it was all overgrown with thorns; the ground was covered with nettles, and its stone wall was broken down.
    <verse number="32" style="v"/>Then I saw and considered it; I looked and received instruction.
    <verse number="33" style="v"/>A little sleep, a little slumber, a little folding of the hands to rest,
    <verse number="34" style="v"/>and poverty will come upon you like a robber, and want like an armed man.
  </para>
  <chapter number="25" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>These also are proverbs of Solomon which the men of Hezekiah king of Judah copied.
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>It is the glory of God to conceal things, but the glory of kings is to search things out.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>As the heavens for height, and the earth for depth, so the heart of kings is unsearchable.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>Take away the dross from the silver, and the smith has material for a vessel;
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>take away the wicked from the presence of the king, and his throne will be established in righteousness.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>Do not put yourself forward in the king's presence or stand in the place of the great,
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>for it is better to be told, "Come up here," than to be put lower in the presence of a noble. What your eyes have seen
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>do not hastily bring into court, for what will you do in the end, when your neighbor puts you to shame?
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>Argue your case with your neighbor himself, and do not reveal another's secret,
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>lest he who hears you bring shame upon you, and your ill repute have no end.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>A word fitly spoken is like apples of gold in a setting of silver.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>Like a gold ring or an ornament of gold is a wise reprover to a listening ear.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>Like the cold of snow in the time of harvest is a faithful messenger to those who send him; he refreshes the soul of his masters.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>Like clouds and wind without rain is a man who boasts of a gift he does not give.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>With patience a ruler may be persuaded, and a soft tongue will break a bone.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>If you have found honey, eat only enough for you, lest you have your fill of it and vomit it.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>Let your foot be seldom in your neighbor's house, lest he have his fill of you and hate you.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>A man who bears false witness against his neighbor is like a war club, or a sword, or a sharp arrow.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>Trusting in a treacherous man in time of trouble is like a bad tooth or a foot that slips.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>Whoever sings songs to a heavy heart is like one who takes off a garment on a cold day, and like vinegar on soda.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>If your enemy is hungry, give him bread to eat, and if he is thirsty, give him water to drink,
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>for you will heap burning coals on his head, and the LORD will reward you.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>The north wind brings forth rain, and a backbiting tongue, angry looks.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>It is better to live in a corner of the housetop than in a house shared with a quarrelsome wife.
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>Like cold water to a thirsty soul, so is good news from a far country.
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>Like a muddied spring or a polluted fountain is a righteous man who gives way before the wicked.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>It is not good to eat much honey, nor is it glorious to seek one's own glory.
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>A man without self-control is like a city broken into and left without walls.
  </para>
  <chapter number="26" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>Like snow in summer or rain in harvest, so honor is not fitting for a fool.
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>Like a sparrow in its flitting, like a swallow in its flying, a curse that is causeless does not alight.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>A whip for the horse, a bridle for the donkey, and a rod for the back of fools.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>Answer not a fool according to his folly, lest you be like him yourself.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>Answer a fool according to his folly, lest he be wise in his own eyes.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>Whoever sends a message by the hand of a fool cuts off his own feet and drinks violence.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>Like a lame man's legs, which hang useless, is a proverb in the mouth of fools.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>Like one who binds the stone in the sling is one who gives honor to a fool.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>Like a thorn that goes up into the hand of a drunkard is a proverb in the mouth of fools.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>Like an archer who wounds everybody is one who hires a passing fool or drunkard.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>Like a dog that returns to his vomit is a fool who repeats his folly.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>Do you see a man who is wise in his own eyes? There is more hope for a fool than for him.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>The sluggard says, "There is a lion in the road! There is a lion in the streets!"
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>As a door turns on its hinges, so does a sluggard on his bed.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>The sluggard buries his hand in the dish; it wears him out to bring it back to his mouth.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>The sluggard is wiser in his own eyes than seven men who can answer sensibly.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>Whoever meddles in a quarrel not his own is like one who takes a passing dog by the ears.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>Like a madman who throws firebrands, arrows, and death
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>is the man who deceives his neighbor and says, "I am only joking!"
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>For lack of wood the fire goes out, and where there is no whisperer, quarreling ceases.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>As charcoal to hot embers and wood to fire, so is a quarrelsome man for kindling strife.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>The words of a whisperer are like delicious morsels; they go down into the inner parts of the body.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>Like the glaze covering an earthen vessel are fervent lips with an evil heart.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>Whoever hates disguises himself with his lips and harbors deceit in his heart;
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>when he speaks graciously, believe him not, for there are seven abominations in his heart;
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>though his hatred be covered with deception, his wickedness will be exposed in the assembly.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>Whoever digs a pit will fall into it, and a stone will come back on him who starts it rolling.
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>A lying tongue hates its victims, and a flattering mouth works ruin.
  </para>
  <chapter number="27" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>Do not boast about tomorrow, for you do not know what a day may bring.
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>Let another praise you, and not your own mouth; a stranger, and not your own lips.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>A stone is heavy, and sand is weighty, but a fool's provocation is heavier than both.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>Wrath is cruel, anger is overwhelming, but who can stand before jealousy?
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>Better is open rebuke than hidden love.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>Faithful are the wounds of a friend; profuse are the kisses of an enemy.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>One who is full loathes honey, but to one who is hungry everything bitter is sweet.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>Like a bird that strays from its nest is a man who strays from his home.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>Oil and perfume make the heart glad, and the sweetness of a friend comes from his earnest counsel.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>Do not forsake your friend and your father's friend, and do not go to your brother's house in the day of your calamity. Better is a neighbor who is near than a brother who is far away.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>Be wise, my son, and make my heart glad, that I may answer him who reproaches me.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>The prudent sees danger and hides himself, but the simple go on and suffer for it.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>Take a man's garment when he has put up security for a stranger, and hold it in pledge when he puts up security for an adulteress.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>Whoever blesses his neighbor with a loud voice, rising early in the morning, will be counted as cursing.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>A continual dripping on a rainy day and a quarrelsome wife are alike;
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>to restrain her is to restrain the wind or to grasp oil in one's right hand.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>Iron sharpens iron, and one man sharpens another.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>Whoever tends a fig tree will eat its fruit, and he who guards his master will be honored.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>As in water face reflects face, so the heart of man reflects the man.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>Sheol and Abaddon are never satisfied, and never satisfied are the eyes of man.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>The crucible is for silver, and the furnace is for gold, and a man is tested by his praise.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>Crush a fool in a mortar with a pestle along with crushed grain, yet his folly will not depart from him.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>Know well the condition of your flocks, and give attention to your herds,
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>for riches do not last forever; and does a crown endure to all generations?
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>When the grass is gone and the new growth appears and the vegetation of the mountains is gathered,
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>the lambs will provide your clothing, and the goats the price of a field.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>There will be enough goats' milk for your food, for the food of your household and maintenance for your girls.
  </para>
  <chapter number="28" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>The wicked flee when no one pursues, but the righteous are bold as a lion.
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>When a land transgresses, it has many rulers, but with a man of understanding and knowledge, its stability will long continue.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>A poor man who oppresses the poor is a beating rain that leaves no food.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>Those who forsake the law praise the wicked, but those who keep the law strive against them.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>Evil men do not understand justice, but those who seek the LORD understand it completely.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>Better is a poor man who walks in his integrity than a rich man who is crooked in his ways.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>The one who keeps the law is a son with understanding, but a companion of gluttons shames his father.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>Whoever multiplies his wealth by interest and profit gathers it for him who is generous to the poor.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>If one turns away his ear from hearing the law, even his prayer is an abomination.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>Whoever misleads the upright into an evil way will fall into his own pit, but the blameless will have a goodly inheritance.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>A rich man is wise in his own eyes, but a poor man who has understanding will find him out.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>When the righteous triumph, there is great glory, but when the wicked rise, people hide themselves.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>Whoever conceals his transgressions will not prosper, but he who confesses and forsakes them will obtain mercy.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>Blessed is the one who fears the LORD always, but whoever hardens his heart will fall into calamity.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>Like a roaring lion or a charging bear is a wicked ruler over a poor people.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>A ruler who lacks understanding is a cruel oppressor, but he who hates unjust gain will prolong his days.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>If one is burdened with the blood of another, he will be a fugitive until death; let no one help him.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>Whoever walks in integrity will be delivered, but he who is crooked in his ways will suddenly fall.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>Whoever works his land will have plenty of bread, but he who follows worthless pursuits will have plenty of poverty.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>A faithful man will abound with blessings, but whoever hastens to be rich will not go unpunished.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>To show partiality is not good, but for a piece of bread a man will do wrong.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>A stingy man hastens after wealth and does not know that poverty will come upon him.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>Whoever rebukes a man will afterward find more favor than he who flatters with his tongue.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>Whoever robs his father or his mother and says, "That is no transgression," is a companion to a man who destroys.
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>A greedy man stirs up strife, but the one who trusts in the LORD will be enriched.
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>Whoever trusts in his own mind is a fool, but he who walks in wisdom will be delivered.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>Whoever gives to the poor will not want, but he who hides his eyes will get many a curse.
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>When the wicked rise, people hide themselves, but when they perish, the righteous increase.
  </para>
  <chapter number="29" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>He who is often reproved, yet stiffens his neck, will suddenly be broken beyond healing.
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>When the righteous increase, the people rejoice, but when the wicked rule, the people groan.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>He who loves wisdom makes his father glad, but a companion of prostitutes squanders his wealth.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>By justice a king builds up the land, but he who exacts gifts tears it down.
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>A man who flatters his neighbor spreads a net for his feet.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>An evil man is ensnared in his transgression, but a righteous man sings and rejoices.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>A righteous man knows the rights of the poor; a wicked man does not understand such knowledge.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>Scoffers set a city aflame, but the wise turn away wrath.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>If a wise man has an argument with a fool, the fool only rages and laughs, and there is no quiet.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>Bloodthirsty men hate one who is blameless and seek the life of the upright.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>A fool gives full vent to his spirit, but a wise man quietly holds it back.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>If a ruler listens to falsehood, all his officials will be wicked.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>The poor man and the oppressor meet together; the LORD gives light to the eyes of both.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>If a king faithfully judges the poor, his throne will be established forever.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>The rod and reproof give wisdom, but a child left to himself brings shame to his mother.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>When the wicked increase, transgression increases, but the righteous will look upon their downfall.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>Discipline your son, and he will give you rest; he will give delight to your heart.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>Where there is no prophetic vision the people cast off restraint, but blessed is he who keeps the law.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>By mere words a servant is not disciplined, for though he understands, he will not respond.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>Do you see a man who is hasty in his words? There is more hope for a fool than for him.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>Whoever pampers his servant from childhood will in the end find him his heir.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>A man of wrath stirs up strife, and one given to anger causes much transgression.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>One's pride will bring him low, but he who is lowly in spirit will obtain honor.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>The partner of a thief hates his own life; he hears the curse, but discloses nothing.
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>The fear of man lays a snare, but whoever trusts in the LORD is safe.
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>Many seek the face of a ruler, but it is from the LORD that a man gets justice.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>An unjust man is an abomination to the righteous, but one whose way is straight is an abomination to the wicked.
  </para>
  <chapter number="30" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>The words of Agur son of Jakeh. The oracle. The man declares, I am weary, O God; I am weary, O God, and worn out.
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>Surely I am too stupid to be a man. I have not the understanding of a man.
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>I have not learned wisdom, nor have I knowledge of the Holy One.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>Who has ascended to heaven and come down? Who has gathered the wind in his fists? Who has wrapped up the waters in a garment? Who has established all the ends of the earth? What is his name, and what is his son's name? Surely you know!
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>Every word of God proves true; he is a shield to those who take refuge in him.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>Do not add to his words, lest he rebuke you and you be found a liar.
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>Two things I ask of you; deny them not to me before I die:
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>Remove far from me falsehood and lying; give me neither poverty nor riches; feed me with the food that is needful for me,
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>lest I be full and deny you and say, "Who is the LORD?" or lest I be poor and steal and profane the name of my God.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>Do not slander a servant to his master, lest he curse you and you be held guilty.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>There are those who curse their fathers and do not bless their mothers.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>There are those who are clean in their own eyes but are not washed of their filth.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>There are those- how lofty are their eyes, how high their eyelids lift!
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>There are those whose teeth are swords, whose fangs are knives, to devour the poor from off the earth, the needy from among mankind.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>The leech has two daughters; "Give" and "Give," they cry. Three things are never satisfied; four never say, "Enough":
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>Sheol, the barren womb, the land never satisfied with water, and the fire that never says, "Enough."
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>The eye that mocks a father and scorns to obey a mother will be picked out by the ravens of the valley and eaten by the vultures.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>Three things are too wonderful for me; four I do not understand:
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>the way of an eagle in the sky, the way of a serpent on a rock, the way of a ship on the high seas, and the way of a man with a virgin.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>This is the way of an adulteress: she eats and wipes her mouth and says, "I have done no wrong."
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>Under three things the earth trembles; under four it cannot bear up:
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>a slave when he becomes king, and a fool when he is filled with food;
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>an unloved woman when she gets a husband, and a maidservant when she displaces her mistress.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>Four things on earth are small, but they are exceedingly wise:
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>the ants are a people not strong, yet they provide their food in the summer;
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>the rock badgers are a people not mighty, yet they make their homes in the cliffs;
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>the locusts have no king, yet all of them march in rank;
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>the lizard you can take in your hands, yet it is in kings' palaces.
    <verse number="29" style="v"/>Three things are stately in their tread; four are stately in their stride:
    <verse number="30" style="v"/>the lion, which is mightiest among beasts and does not turn back before any;
    <verse number="31" style="v"/>the strutting rooster, the he-goat, and a king whose army is with him.
    <verse number="32" style="v"/>If you have been foolish, exalting yourself, or if you have been devising evil, put your hand on your mouth.
    <verse number="33" style="v"/>For pressing milk produces curds, pressing the nose produces blood, and pressing anger produces strife.
  </para>
  <chapter number="31" style="c"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v"/>The words of King Lemuel. An oracle that his mother taught him:
    <verse number="2" style="v"/>What are you doing, my son? What are you doing, son of my womb? What are you doing, son of my vows?
    <verse number="3" style="v"/>Do not give your strength to women, your ways to those who destroy kings.
    <verse number="4" style="v"/>It is not for kings, O Lemuel, it is not for kings to drink wine, or for rulers to take strong drink,
    <verse number="5" style="v"/>lest they drink and forget what has been decreed and pervert the rights of all the afflicted.
    <verse number="6" style="v"/>Give strong drink to the one who is perishing, and wine to those in bitter distress;
    <verse number="7" style="v"/>let them drink and forget their poverty and remember their misery no more.
    <verse number="8" style="v"/>Open your mouth for the mute, for the rights of all who are destitute.
    <verse number="9" style="v"/>Open your mouth, judge righteously, defend the rights of the poor and needy.
    <verse number="10" style="v"/>An excellent wife who can find? She is far more precious than jewels.
    <verse number="11" style="v"/>The heart of her husband trusts in her, and he will have no lack of gain.
    <verse number="12" style="v"/>She does him good, and not harm, all the days of her life.
    <verse number="13" style="v"/>She seeks wool and flax, and works with willing hands.
    <verse number="14" style="v"/>She is like the ships of the merchant; she brings her food from afar.
    <verse number="15" style="v"/>She rises while it is yet night and provides food for her household and portions for her maidens.
    <verse number="16" style="v"/>She considers a field and buys it; with the fruit of her hands she plants a vineyard.
    <verse number="17" style="v"/>She dresses herself with strength and makes her arms strong.
    <verse number="18" style="v"/>She perceives that her merchandise is profitable. Her lamp does not go out at night.
    <verse number="19" style="v"/>She puts her hands to the distaff, and her hands hold the spindle.
    <verse number="20" style="v"/>She opens her hand to the poor and reaches out her hands to the needy.
    <verse number="21" style="v"/>She is not afraid of snow for her household, for all her household are clothed in scarlet.
    <verse number="22" style="v"/>She makes bed coverings for herself; her clothing is fine linen and purple.
    <verse number="23" style="v"/>Her husband is known in the gates when he sits among the elders of the land.
    <verse number="24" style="v"/>She makes linen garments and sells them; she delivers sashes to the merchant.
    <verse number="25" style="v"/>Strength and dignity are her clothing, and she laughs at the time to come.
    <verse number="26" style="v"/>She opens her mouth with wisdom, and the teaching of kindness is on her tongue.
    <verse number="27" style="v"/>She looks well to the ways of her household and does not eat the bread of idleness.
    <verse number="28" style="v"/>Her children rise up and call her blessed; her husband also, and he praises her:
    <verse number="29" style="v"/>"Many women have done excellently, but you surpass them all."
    <verse number="30" style="v"/>Charm is deceitful, and beauty is vain, but a woman who fears the LORD is to be praised.
    <verse number="31" style="v"/>Give her of the fruit of her hands, and let her works praise her in the gates.
  </para>
</usx>
